[MUSIC].
We've come to the last section of the
course.
this at this stage we 're going to talk
about how higher level languages like
Java are implemented in computer systems.
And we're going to leverage the knowledge
we have about how things are done using
C.
what we focused on as our language so
far.
So we're going to start that process by
going back to the very beginning and sort
of replaying the course at a much faster
pace.
And not just talk about how data
representations, pointers, and references
procedures or methods in the case of Java
are represented in a, in this higher
level language.
And we're also going to talk a little bit
about virtual machines, a special runtime
system we use for languages like java
which are interpretted and not compiled
directly.
So we'll get, as I said we're going to do
this really quick this time.
because we have a lot more background to
base things on now.
So let's start turning out attention to
Java.
Before we do that just to make a meta
point about this this lecture, is none of
things we're going to talk about here are
guaranteed by Java.
What we're doing here is just trying to
understand one implementation of a higher
level language so we can get a sense for
what the basic underlying concepts are.
useful ways to think about our programs
and what is going on underneath, but none
of, none of what you hear in this set of
videos.
In this section should you take to be the
gospel truth about a particular
implementation.
Let's begin by looking at how data is
represented in Java.
integers, floats doubles, all those
things all those numbers that we were
looking at before in the beginning of the
course and see or represented exactly the
same way in Java.
there's no differences there.
And yes a Java has pointers as well,
however, there are some differences
there.
in Java pointers are referred to as
references.
And there not quite as general as a, C
pointers are.
remember with C we could point to any
byte in memory, any arbitrary address.
We'll see that in Java our references are
always pointing to the start of an
object, the start of a data structure.
So not quite as general as C pointers.
Just like in C, null is typically
represented as a 0.
and we're going to review characters and
strings, arrays and objects.
So let's start with looking at characters
and strings in Java.
the first thing to to note is that the
character set that a Java uses has two
bites per character rather then one.
Rather then using the Latin alphabet
focused ASCII encoding.
we use two byte unit code characters
which allow us to represent many more the
world's alphabets.
So it's much more general modern computer
code for all the character sets that are
out there.
So the other difference is that unlike in
C where strings are bounded by a special
byte that has a null or a zero in it as
in this example here.
You'll notice the strings ends when we
hit the zero.
We don't know in advance how long the
string is going to be.
We often have to read the entire string.
And keep checking every byte as we read
it to know when we get to the end.
when we get to that zero.
On the other hand, in Java, the first
four bytes are an integer that has the
length of the string represented as as a
number.
in this case the number six for the six
pairs of Unicode bytes.
for the six characters in CSE351.
Okay, so, a, with a, with java at the
very beginning we know the length of the
string already.
That first thing we read is an integer
that tells us how long it is and how far
we'll need to go.
The same approach carries through into
arrays.
you'll notice that arrays in Java have an
integer at the very beginning that tells
us how many elements there are in the
array.
Another difference in arrays in Java, is
that they're already initialized to 0.
and unlike in C, where the array is
placed at some locations in memory and
it's starting values are whatever was
there.
Whatever bits were currently at those
memory locations.
instead in Java there's a special effort
made to put zeroes there to start.
So that we know that whenever we read a
value for the first time, it will in
fact, be a zero.
That nice first value there, the length
of the array is accessed by a special
method called length.
That we can call on the array and that
will return the value of that field.
So that anytime we can find out how big
this array is.
And why is that there, what can that do
for us.
Well what's, what happens in Java is
every time we access an array, every time
we index an array.
we actually go and take, you know in this
case, for example, let's say we had
written array three.
we will actually go and take that value
three and compare it against this one
stored at the very first position in the
object.
And make sure that we're not addressing a
location that's out of bounds.
an, an element of the array that is
actually defined.
in this case 3 is definitely okay, it
really corresponds to this element right
here and we can go ahead and read that.
If we had put a 7 here then that would've
been somewhere out here.
in C and we would've just generated an,
an address and read whatever was at that
memory location.
In Java on the other hand, we compare
that seven against the five and say, well
we're clearly out of bounds.
Let's throw an exception and and cause
the program to stop because we're clearly
addressing something in an incorrect way.
So this is one nice advantage of writing
Java programs that we get these extra
bound checks for free.
That means that there's extra code
executing that we didn't bother to write
to check that bound but was inserted for
us automatically in the Java
implementation to do that bounds
checking.
Okay, let's take a look at data
structures in Java, or objects as they're
referred to.
the difference between structs in C and
objects in Java, is that objects can only
include primitive data types.
Not composite data types.
So for example, you'll remember maybe
this example that we used before.
Here we have a struct that has an integer
as its first element, and then an array
of three ints as its second element.
That's not a primitive structure or
primitive data type, that's a composite
data type, it actually consists of three
integers.
And then another primitive data type that
is a pointer, okay?
when we access these in C, what we can do
is allocate some space for for the, the
struct.
Get a pointer to that region of memory,
and then we can refer to it using that
arrow notation which says, hey take that
pointer, dereference it, offset by the
amount that you need to offset to get to
the various pieces of the, of the struct
and assign a new value to them.
And you'll notice that we can not only
reference a, but we can reference an
element within a, and assign a value to
one element of the array.
here, we're assigning an address of
another struct to that pointer.
Okay.
So, in memory, this looks like.
An integer, followed by three more
integers that represent the array, a, and
then another four bytes that are the
pointer, that is the third element.
Let's see what that looks like in Java.
You'll notice that in Java, yes, we do
have the integer as the first element and
the reference to another object a pointer
like thing, as the third element, but in
the middle we don't have the actual array
of three integers, we have a pointer to a
new structure that is an array of three
integers, so rather than actually
representing the three integers there.
We actually just represent a pointer to
the array.
So to, let's just take a look at that
map.
So here in this case, our memory has our
four byte integer at the beginning, our
four byte pointer to an array and another
four byte reference to another object.
So that pointer a is not the actual
array, but rather points off to a region
of memory where the array is stored.
Here are the three ints, but remember
they're preceded by the length of the
array.
So there's an extra integer there at the
beginning.
That tells us how many elements there are
to this array.
When we reference them in code, when we
reference the struct in code you'll
notice theres a slightly different
syntax.
We don't bother doing malloc to call the
memory allocation to get us a space in
memory.
We use the keyword new which is actually
something that does that malloc for us
and creates a new space in memory, in
this case two new spaces in memory.
One for the first level of the struct and
then one for one of, another area for the
composite data type that makes up that
that struct.
That extra array that has to be created
and it initializes these, this pointer to
point to that array.
The references to the elements are very
similar to what we did in C, but you'll
notice that we've changed the notation a
little bit.
Instead of the arrow, we just used a dot.
It's it's a little bit shorter, easier to
read, and since we're always using a
reference that's to the start of an
object.
we implicitly do the do reference so we
don't bother with that extra step, and
can just use the dot notation.
Alright, so you've seen a, a little bit
about these pointers, let's see, a, what
that implications that has.
So a pointer in C, again, can point to
any memory address.
In, in Java though, it can only point to
the beginning of an object.
only it's first element, not, it cannot
point to the middle of it.
So what implications does this have?
Well you, here's our struct again and
you'll notice here we're calling a
function with one element of the array
that makes up that struct and we can do
that with a single expression.
We go to that struct, look at its a
array, and then the second element of
that array.
And the address of that element, and can
pass that on to the function.
So in this case what we're doing is
passing a pointer to that function, some
fun As an argument and that ar, that
argument points to a particular integer
in the middle of that array.
In Java, we can't do that.
Remember our pointers?
Our references can only go to the
beginning of an object so, we actually
have to specify it in two parts.
First, we have to say the array Address
and then, which element of the array.
we, because we can't point to the middle
of the array directly.
So remember, that's what our struct looks
like in our object looks like in memory.
These two discontiguous parts, and we
cannot generate a pointer to the middle
of that array so the way we have to do it
is by pointing first to the array by
getting that pointer stored at this
location, and then providing an index
that tells us which element to the array
we want, and that index will be compared
against the length of the array and
checked for us.
to make sure that we're not over stepping
the bounds.