[MUSIC].
Let's take a look at our road map.
We're at our first section that will
address the issues of data and
addressing.
Namely, how do we store information in
memory, how do we represent it in terms
of 0's and 1's.
And how do we reference that data, in
other words, what addresses do we provide
so we can find the data we've put in
memory again.
So to before we get into that.
And the other topics in this section.
We're going to start with a few
preliminaries about how we organize our
hardware.
Lets take a look at this first picture
that is a logical view of a modern
computing system.
You'll notice that very prominently are
the CPU, the Central Processing Unit, and
the memory.
There's a hide bandwidth channel between
the memory and the CPU because the CPU
has to go to that memory to get all the
data and instructions it will need in
order to know what to do and to what
pieces data.
So that is going to be a very big focus
of this course that connection is
actually going to be a little bit more
complex than shown in this diagram.
There's going to be various levels of
memory that we'll be looking at.
in addition, the CPU and memory are
connected to a common bus that allows
data to flow between all the elements of
a computer.
Some of the other elements are disks,
which provide even more memory for us to
use.
But are slower and little bit further
away from the CPU will also have a
connection to the network.
So that we can get data over the internet
we'll also have connections to peripheral
devices like mice and keyboards and
cameras and those are often over a USB
interfaces.
universal serial bus as well as others
that might be available depending on the
computing, computing system you have.
Let's go a little deeper and look at a
semi logical view.
In this case we're breaking things down a
little bit, not only into a main CPU
shown here at the top.
you'll notice that it's connected to a
bunch of memory on one side and maybe
some specialized memory and processing
for graphics functions on the other.
below it is another large chip that's
often common in most computers.
And that's a IO controller, something
that really orchestrates that common buss
that connects to all the other devices.
Some of those other devices might be the
audio system the hard disc drives the USB
interfaces and so on.
That are, make up the rest of the
computer.
If we go yet a level deeper and go to the
physical view of the device.
here we'll see a, a, a motherboard.
A board that includes all those major
components of a computer.
Here in the center is the the CPU chip.
it's surrounded by an IO chip, that
controls those peripherals connections
for adding memory to the system.
And connections for hard disk drives to
be connected to that common bus.
In addition, at the back of the machine,
we'll typically see a whole bunch of
connections to those peripheral devices.
Including audio components, mice,
keyboards and networks.
If we focus then on the part that will be
most concerned with, namely the CPU and
memory that we say at the top of our
first figure.
We go a little deeper in and we'll see
that the CPU is composed of some things
that hold data, we're going to call these
registers.
And some things that hold instructions
and that will typically be called an
instruction cache.
the thing that we need to understand at a
very high level for now we'll get into a
lot more detail on this later but for now
we need to understand that data.
Namely, the things we operate on are
moved from memory to the registers.
That's where the CPU can actually have
operations on that data.
And then, the results from those
registers are moved back to memory.
This is done on the program control.
In other words, we'll have specific
instructions to go get memory at a
particular location in the memory and
bring it into a particular register.
And similarly going in the other
direction from a specific register to a
specific location in memory.
We'll also be getting instructions from
memory into our instruction cache where
the CPU will find.
The instructions to execute.
this is done under hardware control.
In other words, the CPU has it's own
devices for getting that ins- next
instruction.
And figure out whether it needs to go to
the memory to find it, or if it already
has it in it's cache.
why might it already have it in its
cache?
Well if it's executing a loop for example
or a common procedure that had just
recently executed, it might already be in
the cache.
But that's done on the hardware control,
we don't worry about where to get the
next instruction.
What we worry about in our programs is
where to get the data, and where to put
the date once we've operated on it.
We also want to talk about the
performance of our computing systems and
performance is not just about CPU speed
mainly the clock rate the, the speed at
which we connect to get one instruction
after another.
Its also about getting those instructions
and the data they have to operate on from
memory to the CPU.
That CPU memory bandwidth can limit
performance.
And we have two common strategies for
trying to improve that performance.
The first tries to make the memory wider.
Namely we get more bits at once from the
memory.
So, rather than getting.
one instruction at a time, we might get
several instructions at a time, or not
one piece of data but several.
Another, possibility is to move some of
the memory into the CPU itself, and
actually have a smaller, but much faster
memory available to the CPU.
This works particularly well when The
data and instructions are located near
each other.
Or are a very small set of the all the
possible locations in memory.
So, this memory in the CPU will be much
smaller than the larger main memory.
We call this a cache, namely some place
where we store our valuables.
nearby so that we can get to it easy.
Now that we've talked about how our
computers are organized.
we also have to talk about how we
represent those zeros and ones that we're
going to be building all of our data and
instructions from.
You'll notice that that bottom in this
slide, there's a figure that shows that,
in fact, the 0 is represented by a low
voltage.
A 1 represented by a high voltage.
And those can fluctuate a little bit.
And it also takes a little bit of time to
go from a 0 to a 1 when we have some
voltages that are intermediate.
We really don't want to be in this region
because that can be confusing.
And that is in fact what limits the speed
of our computing systems, how quickly we
can make these transitions between 0 and
1 and 1 to 0.
So electronics are designed to make it
easy to represent a value at this voltage
and a value at a low voltage and not
worry about the values in between.
Rather, we restore our values as often as
we can to these nicer voltages at the top
and bottom.
How do we represent numbers?
Well here's a number in base 10 the
number 351, that's the number of this
course here at UW.
And this is in base 10 we're very
familiar with this number representation,
we've seen it since elementary school.
the binary representation, of 351, is
this number.
Now, how did I decide on how many 0's and
1's to use?
Well, that was kind of arbitrary.
In this, I could have also represented it
by the much shorter string of 1's and 0's
that doesn't have that leading set of
0's.
That would be the same thing as writing
351 base 10 or 0's, 0, 0, 351 base 10.
You'll notice that we can always put
leading 0's in front of something that
doesn't change the actual value.
So we'll have to decide how many bits we
want to use to represent numbers.
And that's where we'll be going next.