[MUSIC].
There's a lot more to talk about in how
we organize and address data in memory.
Let's start with a very important
distinction between addresses and
pointers.
You'll notice that I've drawn a memory on
this slide, that has bytes grouped into
four byte units.
That, that are 32 byte words.
You'll also notice that the first word is
shown at address 0.
The second word at address four then
eight.
And then c.
This is now in hexadecimal notation.
So c corresponds to the decimal 12.
Hexadecimal one zero corresponds to the
decimal 16.
So here we're adding four for each
address as we move down our memory, since
we're takling about words.
In this particular case, I've shown you
the detail of one word that happens to
have the value 00001015F in hexadecimal.
That corresponds to the decimal number
351.
Now, an address is a location in memory,
as we've said.
So we have these different addresses here
from 00 hex to down to 24 hex, for all
these various locations in memory.
A pointer, unlike an address, is a data
object that contains an address.
So, let me give you an example.
I can put a pointer to that address of
0004, at a different memory location,
let's say at the address 001C.
So now you'll see that what I've shown in
the memory is that at that location,
001C, I have a value that happens to be
the address of another location in
memory.
That's what makes it a pointer, the fact
that I interpret it that way.
I could have just as easily have
interpreted that number as just the
number 4.
That would have been a beta value stored
at that location but I am now choosing to
interpret it as an address in which case
it is a pointer to a different location.
Let's take a look at another example I
can have a pointer to that location in
the address 0024 by placing the value
0000001C at the location 0024 in memory.
Again, I am choosing to interpret this as
a, as an address, therefore, it is a
pointer to another memory location.
If I had interpreted as just a number,
what number would it be?
It would be the, the hex number 1C, which
is 16 plus 12, or 28 decimal.
And not an address.
Okay.
So, it's purely a an interpretation
question.
Will I interpret this value as a pointer
and therefore an address to another
location.
Or will I interpret it as a value.
That's the distinction between addresses
and pointers.
Another example is if in that memory
location zero zero one four I had put the
value zero c.
Well is that an address?
Well it could be an address.
It's part of our memory certainly, there
is a, a, word with that address but am I
interpreting it as an address.
Well I maybe, or it maybe just a number
12 corresponding to that hexidecimal c.
In in C, in C and in Java we have many
different data types.
And how we represent them in our machines
varies because of the amount of bits that
we need to represent them.
So, this table just gives you a quick
comparison of how that's done.
In both the 32-bit machine, and a 64-bit
machine.
So, you'll see that a boolean data type
requires just one byte.
Now, in reality, we can probably do it in
one bit, but it's since we address things
in terms of bytes It's going to take up
eight bits to do that.
a byte, of course, requires one byte.
In C, a byte is also a character in a
character string.
Java has a more complex structure for
characters we'll, that we'll get to a
little bit later on.
That takes up two bytes per character.
a, a short integer or a 16-bit integer
takes up two bytes in both.
While a regular integer takes up four.
This is, based on the fact that we have a
lot of programs that were written for
32-bit machines.
A floating point number also takes up
four bytes.
We'll discuss.
How we represent floaty point numbers
later.
On 64-bit machines, we also have a
long-end data type, an integer that takes
up 64 bits or 8 bytes.
we also have double floats and long longs
and long doubles that can be particularly
Large range of numbers taking up 16
bytes.
And then we have addresses or references
or pointers which in a 32 bit machine can
be up to four bytes by definition.
And in 64 bit machine can be up to eight
bytes by definition.
Alright the next question is how do we
order the bytes within a word, there's
actually two ways to do that one way is
what's called big endian and the other is
little endian.
Yeah.
And these two different conventions come
from the names for them come from
Gulliver's Travels.
You can read about this in the in the
textbook by Bryant and O'Halloran that
we're using as a reference text for this
class.
but basically the idea is that in in a
big endian notation, the most significant
byte of the number goes to the lowest
address.
and in the little endian notation, the
least significant byte goes to the lowest
address.
So let's do a quick little example to
demonstrate that.
Suppose I have the following eight digit
hexadecimal number.
01234567, okay.
And I want to store that at a word at
address 100 hex.
Now, in a big Endian computer system, it
would be stored as follows.
Okay, the most significant byte In other
words the highest ordered digit go to the
first byte.
Then the next two go to the next byte.
The and so on until the lowest
significant digits go in the last one at
103.
And little in the end notation well it's
in the opposite order.
The lowest order digits come in first, at
address 100.
And the highest order digits end up going
at 103.
These are two, these are the two natural
choices to do, and you notice that the
little endian one looks a little
backwards from our original number.
but that is in fact, the one that the x86
architecture uses.
So, that's what we'll be seeing a lot in
the memory maps that we'll be looking at,
and when we look at memory values and
memory, they will be arranged this way.
Just a quick another example.
looking at the decimal value 12345.
in binary that's represented right below
as those binary digits which are the hex
three zero three nine.
Okay so you'll see that in a 32 bit
architecture.
We put the least significant digits at
the lowest address.
And the most significant digits at the
highest address.
While it's in the opposite order on a Big
Endian Architecture.
for negative number, and don't worry
about the, this right now, but this is
the number minus 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
represented in two's complement notation
that we will get to a bit later.
But again, the lowest significant digits
are represented first while in the big
end, it's the other way around.
Now, here you'll see why little end might
be somehow, somewhat advantageous in a
32-bit architecture to a 64-bit
architecture, you'll notice that the
correspondence of those locations is the
same.
When then there's a lot more zeros, of
course, in the 64-bit notation to pad
things out.
While in the big NDN notation we can't
just simply extend in this direction with
zeros.
We have to actually go in the other
direction, and move this down, which is a
bit more complex.