[MUSIC].
Okay, now, that we've seen how to
organize an address data in memory, we're
going to look at how we manipulate that
data, in a language like C, that let's us
directly manipulate the contents of
memory.
Okay, in the C language, just like in
many programming languages, we have many
variable declarations.
In this case at the top here, we're
looking at two variables, x and y.
They're both of type integer, and that's
how we describe them in C.
Int x,y And the semicolon to end that
declaration statement.
So, this is going to go and find two
locations in memory, in which to store
our two integers.
given that they're two integers, they'll
take up one word each or four bytes, per
number.
Now, we can also declare pointers in C,
or addresses, of variables, and we do
that using the star.
A so in this case you'll see a statement
that stays in star PTR well PTR is the
name of a variable that points to an
integer.
So it doesn't actually have the value of
the integer it points to the place in
memory where that integer is so it will
store an address rather than a value.
And this is again or because we're
interpreting it that way.
And we're telling C that that's what
we'll be doing.
Okay, so now we can, also we have an
assignment statement to a pointer.
And in order to get an address to go put
into a pointer, we have the ampersand
operator.
So, you'll notice here in this third
statement, ptr equals ampersand x.
That ampersand x means I don't want the
value of x, I want the address of x.
And let's put that into the ptr variable
which, of course, points to an integer so
this type matches.
We've gotten the address of an integer
and putting it into the pointer to an
integer.
Okay.
Now to use the value that a pointer
points to we also have a second use for
the star operator.
in these examples, this first statement,
you'll notice that we, doing what we just
did before, we're getting the address of
x, putting it into ptr.
Our next statement then, can add 1 to the
value pointed to by the pointer, ptr.
What this is, what this construct says is
take the value in the pointer ptr,
interpret it as an address.
Go there in memory and get the value
that's stored there.
And then we're going to add 1 to that
value and put the result in y.
This is the same as if we had written y
equals x plus 1.
Okay.
So so far, doesn't seem too useful.
But let's take a look at the next line.
In this case, we can say that ptr points
to y, now.
The address of y.
And when we use that same statement
again, add 1 to whatever ptr is pointing
to.
Then that's the same as saying y equals y
plus 1 now instead of x.
But you notice this statement didn't
change at all.
It stayed the same.
This is going to allows us to do more
general functions in C than we would have
otherwise been able to do if we were
restricted to only use the name of the
variables.
Okay.
Last example on this slide.
star ampersand x.
What is that equivalent to?
Well again, &x is just the address of x.
Okay.
But when we dereference that address,
using the star, we now get the value at
that address.
Well, what is the value with that
address, well that's just x.
So, in fact star ampersand x is the same
as writing just x, okay.
Good.
Now lets go on to some more interesting
examples.
Well for one thing we can add values to
pointers.
So in this case we're using a pointer as
if it were a variable.
And just saying add one to that value.
But in reality pointer is being
interpreted by c as being an address.
So, when we say add 1, C says wait a
minute.
You are pointing to an integer that's
what ptr is a variable that points to
integers.
So, if you are adding 1 to that you
really don't mean you want to add 1, you
really mean you want to add 4.
And why 4 because that's the size of an
int you are not going to want to just add
1 to that address and point to the next
byte that doesn't make much sense.
You probably want to point to the next
integer or the thing following that
integer in memory, so we are going to add
4 instead for you, okay.
Well this can be very useful, but it also
can be quite dangerous when we don't know
exactly what is following that Variable
in memory.
So if we know what's immediately after x,
that's great.
Maybe it's the value y.
But there is no guarantee that, in fact,
y was placed in that location in memory.
Alright.
Just remember that, and we'll be coming
back to that several more times.
Alright.
In general, what we haven't C is in, is
an assignment statement, is a left-hand
side and a right-hand side, on the two
sides of the equal sign.
The left-hand side has to evaluate to a
memory location, a place where we can put
a value.
And, the right-hand side, has to evaluate
to a value, the value we're going to go
put there.
And because we also have pointer
variables, that value could be an
address.
So, let's look at a series of examples
here that'll highlight this.
What I'm showing here on this slide, is
again a memory map that goes from
location 0 to location 24 hex.
I've placed the variable x at the
location 4, and the variable y at the
location 18.
you'll notice that y is initially this
hex value.
that corresponds to 3CD02700.
And you'll notice that it's in reverse
byte order in the memory here.
And the reason I've done that is because
from now on we're going to be talking
about little endian machines.
And so we're going to but the least
significant byte in the first byte
position and the most significant byte in
the last.
So, you'll be seeing a lot of these
reverse order bytes for our integers.
Okay, so that's the value of y stored
there and the value of x is 0.
let's take a look at a sample statement
and see.
This case, we're saying x is equal to y
plus three.
Well, let's take a look at the right hand
side.
It says go get the value of y and add
the, the number 3 to it.
And then we're going to take that result
and go put it where x is stored.
Okay, the memory location of x on the
left hand side.
So what we expect to see happen then is
to take this value here.
Add 3, and have it appear up here.
Okay, and that is, in fact, what happens.
You'll notice, that that least
significant byte is the one that had the,
the, that changed, when we added the 3.
Okay.
Another example, this time you'll notice
our declaration is a little bit
different.
We've declared now rather than the, an
integer x.
An integer pointer x.
So, we're going to interpret the values
stored at x at location 4 as an address.
In this case, you'll notice, our
assignment statement also looks a little
different.
Now we have to get an address to go put
there.
Well, what we're going to do is get the
address of y.
And add 3 to that or are we really adding
3?
Well, remember because C knows this is an
address to an integer, instead of adding
3 it is going to add 12, 4 times 3,
because that's the size of an integer.
So it's going to go Get that address of y
18.
And then add 12 which in hex is just c.
The result of 24 is now going to be
stored at the variable x which is a
pointer variable.
So it can store addresses and so we see
the number 24 appear at that address.
for x.
Okay lets move on to another example.
In this case we're saying lets take the
value stored at x interpret it as an
address.
Okay.
Go to that location in memory and put the
value of y there.
Let's try that again.
On the right hand side, you see just the
value of y.
That's that hex value stored at location
18.
And we're going to go and place it not at
x, as we did in the previous example.
But at the address pointed to by x, that
extra star in the front is a de-ference.
It is saying don't interpret that x is
the address but rather go to that
location, find the address and then go
there.
In this case what's that x.
Well, it's that at that number 24 that we
put there previously that address.
so we're going to go and place the value
at the address 24.
So we'll see it appear at this last
location in memory.
And that's in fact what happens.