Alright, the last section of our memory
data and addressing portion, is going to
cover a little bit about Boolean algebra.
The kinds of things we need to know, the
kinds of operators we need to know about
to do some bit level manipulations on the
bits were storing into memory.
let's go through the basics of Boolean
algebra really quickly.
Boolean algebra was developed by Goerge
Boole, that's who it's named after, in
the 19th century.
And basically it's an algebraic
representation of logic.
We encode True as a 1 and False as a O.
again, binary number system and we have a
few basic operators.
A very important one is the logical AND
often represented with an ampersand as in
operator.
that says if the variable A and the
variable B are true, then the AND, the
product of their values in Boolean
algebra is also true, okay?
So, A&B is 1, when both A is 1 and B is
1.
similarly we have the OR operator which
as you'd expect, is true if, A is 1 or B
is 1, or both.
And then of course we have the exclusive
or operator.
Often abbreviated as XOR.
which is true if A is true, or B is true,
but not both.
So, it excludes that case.
That's where that X comes from.
And then finally we have a Unary operator
in Boolean algebra.
That says the NOT of A, or the complement
of A, is is just the opposite value.
So, if A is 1, then its complement is 0.
And vice versa.
If A is 0, then its complement is 1.
interesting law in Boolean algebra that
can be derived from basic principles is
De Morgan's Law.
Which basically says the complement of
the OR of two variables is the same as
the AND of the complemented variables.
And this can be very valuable when we
want to eliminate ORs to have only ANDs
or eliminate ANDs to have only ORs.
In a logic expression.
Here are another representation of these
basic operators in what are called Truth
Tables.
Here we see the operator, in this case
the AND.
And the val, the possible values of one
variable.
And the possible values of another
And this is the AND of the two.
So, when they're both 0, then the AND is
0.
When they're both 1, the AND is 1.
And when either one of them is 0, then
the result is also 0.
So, in the case of AND, it is 1 only when
both are True or 1.
For the OR, which we use the vertical bar
you'll see that it's a 1 whenever either
one of them is a 1 and only 0 when both
are 0.
For the Exclusive OR, again, if one is a
1, but not both so, in this case, we
want to make sure that this is a 0 as
well.
That's the difference to the OR case that
we had here.
And then, the Unary operator, of course
is only one variable and it's just the
opposite of the, of the value.
So, that's the basic of Boolean algebra.
How we use this to manipulate bits?
Well, we can have two bytes in memory.
Here we're showing two bytes.
And we can AND them together bit wise one
bit at a time.
So, we can AND 0 and 0 and of course that
result would be a 0.
1 and 1 the result would be a 1.
In these two, the next cases these are
all zero the result except for the last
one where again the two values are one so
we would expect the one as a result okay?
So, this would be the resulting AND
across these two variable, so the OR case
the same values again.
As long as one of them is a 1, we expect
to see a 1 down here.
So there's only two cases where we would
end up with a 0, here and here, where
both variable values are 0.
finally, for the Exclusive OR.
where would we expect to see zeros?
Well, certainly here, where they're both
0.
certainly here, where they're both 0.
But also where they're both 1.
And that's here at the end.
And also right here in the second column.
So, that result, is the corresponding one
for XOR.
And then for the bit wise compliment or
not, we would just expect to see the bits
flip, okay?
So, this is the the Boolean operators
applied to bit vectors.
In this case just the bytes lengths of
bits.
And in C we have these exact same
operators available to us and they can
apply to any integral data type long,
int, short, or character.
remember character being just a byte.
and the arguments to these operators
appear are treated as bit vectors.
And the operations apply bitwise.
So, you can see here we've declared three
byte variables a b and c.
you'll notice here that we're setting the
value of a to the hex four one.
That's represented here in its bit
notation.
And when we take the compliment of a.
and assign it to b, this is the value we
get and assign it to b.
In hex, this is BE, not immediately
obvious, from the 41.
Okay, but you can see that the 1 and e
add up to 16, and the 4 and b add up to
16.
Alright if we take the value of 0 and put
it in a, as in this case, then the
compliment is just FF all ones.
Here's a case of an AND.
we've taken 69 and 55 as bit vectors
represented here in
In these values.
This should say 69, not 41.
And, sorry about that error there.
This is a 6, and 9.
And, the, the bit vector is correct
however.
And, a and b, is just this string of, of
1s and 0s.
Again, similar to the example on the
previous page, which results in a 41.
Okay.
So, this is how we do bit-level
operations in in C just using those basic
operators.
Okay.
So, the other thing we should know is
that zero is always viewed as false and
anything that is non zero is true.
So, the value doesn't have to be one to
be true.
Anything that is not a zero is
interpreted as true.
Now, when we're talking about bits, of
course, the only values we can have are
zero or one.
But if we apply a logical operator to an
entire series of bits.
For example, an entire byte at a time, or
an entire int at a time.
Then it will only be considered false if
that entire int is equal to zero.
In other words, all the bits are zero.
And anything else.
So as long as there's any one anywhere,
then it will be considered as true,
alright?
This is very useful, for early
termination of if statements.
And, we'll see that a little bit later
on.
but let's take a look at a few examples.
here's the compliment.
Again this is now the logical operator,
not the bitwise complement, so we're
using a different symbol.
The exclamation point or bang rather than
the tilda.
And so the complement of 41 is what we'd
expect from our logic is to be zero,
false.
You'll notice its not the bitwise
complement, that was a different value In
this case, it's simply zero.
If we take the complement of zero, what
would we expect to get?
Well, actually anything would do that has
at least a one, one in it, that would be
true, but by convention, we'll just flip
one bit and make it equivalent to a hex
zero one.
Alright, if we and 69 and 55 as we did on
the previous page, we know this result
would've been 41, if we had done a lot
bit wise operation.
But in this case, this value is
interpreted as true, this value is
interpreted as true.
So, our result is simply true.
Or one.
if we then do 0 and with 55, a 0 is
false, so our results should be false, as
it is.
again let's do an an OR operation and we
would see 69 true or 55 also true, is
just going to result in a 1.
Okay?
So, how does this early termination help?
Well, for example, suppose that we're
looking to increment the value at which p
points.
P is a pointer.
to a particular value.
And, what we're concerned about is that
we actually do have a pointer, and that
our pointer isn't null, or all zeros.
So, we can first say, well, is p true,
meaning not zero?
so, by putting into an, a logical AND
statement, we can do that test.
Here, if p is all zeros, a null pointer,
we know that the and is going to be false
in the end.
So, we can just not do that, not continue
evaluating this expression, and it would
stop right there.
On the other hand if p is something else,
other than zero, then we can assume it's
not null.
And it's probably a valid address.
And we can de-reference it.
Go to the place it points.
Get the value and increment.
Okay?
So, this is a shorthand notation for if p
is true, then increment the value at that
pointer.
But often in C you'll see this as a quick
shorthand instead of having to write that
in.
But this could be placed in the middle of
an expression even to help check that
pointer.
Alright, lastly I want to show you how
Boolean algebra can be used to represent
sets.
We'll be using this in a few places
during the rest of the course.
So, we can take a bit vector of w bits
let's say maybe that's just eight bits
for now.
so, what we can do is have each bit
represent an element of a set, in this
case the set can have up to eight
elements.
And you'll notice in this example here I
have this particular vector, and I can
have each bit represent 1 element of the
set.
So, this bit sequence would represent the
set of element 0, element 3, 5, and 6.
Because those are the ones I've set to 1,
okay?
Here's another example.
Slightly different set.
0,2,4,6.
Okay.
So, you kind of get the hang of how we
could represent a set using a bit vector.
And now our operators, our bit wise
operators, are pretty interesting.
The AND can be viewed as set
intersection, because it will only be
true if the element is in both sets.
So, if we AND these two bit vectors
together, we would get this result, which
says that 0 and 6 are elements of the
intersection, 'kay.
Similarly, OR corresponds to set union.
If we OR those two values, we would get
this bit vector, which represents 0, 2,3
,4, 5, and 6.
You notice that is the union of these two
sets.
All the elements present.
Exclusive OR corresponds to what's called
the symmetric difference.
In other words, elements that are in one
set, but not both.
In this case, the elements 2, 3, 4, and
5.
And a Compliment is obviously the
complimentary set.
So, the compliment of the first one, of
the second set here is 1, 3, 5, and 7,
alright.