[MUSIC].
Let's go back to our road map and look at
the next topic that we'll be covering.
we're going to focus next on integers and
floats, the representation of numbers in
in memory.
That's going to be an important precursor
before we can man, look at all the
instructions for manipulating that data
values.
So this section is going to cover the
representation of integers.
Both signed and unsigned.
And how we treat integers and c.
talk about some shifting and signed
extension operations that will be
important for arithmetic.
And then we'll close with a section on
floating point numbers.
basically, how do we represent binary
numbers that are fractions rather than
just integers?
And then, we'll get into a little bit of
detail on the IEEE floating point
standard for floating point numbers.
And how we do floating point operations.
And the rounding that they entail.
As well as look at floating point numbers
and see.
There's a lot more to floating point
numbers.
And we, we'll leave a lot of those topics
to the text to cover.
but we will do some of the basics.
But before we get to integers Just wanted
to talk about a encoding problems in
general.
So suppose we have a 52 card deck.
A, you know, the typical playing card
setup with 13 cards of each suit
organized into four different suits.
and we want to figure out how to
represent these in binary numbers how do
we use zeros and ones to represent all
these cards, well we could start by
thinking about the operations we want to
be able to do on the cards so we probably
want to be able to tell if a card is
higher than another.
or if they're the same suit that might
help us think about the kind of encoding
we have, lets take a look at some
examples, so heres a very simple encoding
to start with we have 52 different cards,
so lets use 52 different bits, with bit
corresponding to the card that we haev
set to one.
So that would let us use 52 bits of a 64
bit word, let's say.
In what's called a one hot encoding.
And meaning that there's only going to be
one bit set to one, all the others will
be set to zero.
So we can have the first bit represent
lets say the ace of clubs.
Okay and the next bit represents the two
of clubs and so on.
What are some of the drawbacks to this?
Well it's going to be really hard to
compare values and suits because we have
individual bits throughout those 52.
where we have to look for the value in
the suit of the card and we sure have a
large number of bits to represent 1 card
an entire 64 bit word.
This is called a 1 hatting code where
only 1 bit is on another possibility to
do do a 2 hotting coding where we might
use 4 bits to represent the suit and
another 13 bits to represent the 13
possible values of the card.
So now two bits would be set to one.
So the fir-, the first bit in the suit
might be set, to indicate the suit clubs
and the, the first bit in the value might
be set to indicate an ace.
okay.
So now it's a lot easier to tell if two
cards are of the same suit, because
they'll have the same 4 bits here.
And, we can tell, if a card is greater
than another, by looking at the position
of the 1 in the remaining 13 bits.
But that's still a bit cumbersome.
It's easier to compare suits and values
but it's still a large number of bits.
in this case 17.
This is what's called a two-hot encoding
now, because we have two bits set to one
for each card.
Let's continue with this exercise and
look at two possibly better
representations.
we could just do a binary encoding of all
52 cards, we only need 6 bits to
represent 64 diferent numbers so we can
take care of 52 in just 6 bits, that
would allow us to fit a card into just a
bit and use the low order 6 bits to do
that.
So that's kind of nice.
It all fits in one byte.
and it's much smaller than the one or
two-hot encoding.
But how can we make the value comparisons
easier?
the suit comparisons easier.
we're still going to have all the cards
numbered from one to 50 bit, one to 52,
and that will not make it easy to do
those comparisons.
so we can do something that's a bit of a
hybrid, we can use two bits for the suit,
four bits for the value.
Two bits for the suit because we have
four possible suits, so we need four
possible binary bit patterns here, 00,
01, 10 and 11.
One and then four bits for the value.
Because the card can be anything from an
ace to a king 13 different values.
Okay so this makes it now easy to still
do that suit comparison, and just check
if a number is smaller or greater than
another take away the value.
Okay.
So, let's take a look at how we would
implement these operations if we were
doing it in in C.
So, if we wanted to check if 2 cards are
of the same suit, what we would do is
have 2 bytes representing each card,
Okay?
Maybe an array to represent a five card
hand.
We would take two cards out of the hand
and ask if they're the same suit.
And this function sameSuitP is
implemented here below.
It returns a boolean value just zero or
one.
And takes the two cards as, arguments.
What it does, you'll notice, is, it takes
the first card, and does a bit wise and
with the suit mask.
What is the suit mask?
The suit mask is a special value set to
hex 3, 0.
Why hex 3, 0?
Well that corresponds to 00110000.
You'll notice that when we do a bit wise
and with this mask, we will only have non
zero results for these two bits.
All the other bits will necessarily be
zero.
Because we have a 0 here and 0 ended with
anything will result in a 0.
So this will essentially extract the
value of the suit form the card
representation.
It will only have a nonzero value
possibly in these 2 bits okay.
So, then we can do an exclusive OR with
the suit of the other card.
Okay and why do we do an exclusive OR?
Well remember, an exclusive OR says
either one is true or the other is true
but not both.
Okay?
So, we would only get a perfect zero
result If these two suits matched
exactly, in other words, they had the
same zeros and ones in these two
locations, if they have that, then the
result will be all zeros.
And that's a bouillon false, and by
taking the complement of it logically, we
can say then that, tho, those two cards
match.
That our result is true.
Okay.
So what we actually implemented here was
the opposite of the x or by using the
not.
In otehr words, we said, rather are the
two suits different bits.
We, we're asking, are they the same bits?
By just doing the compliment of the X0.
All right, that would have been the same
as saying this using the equals, equals
boylean operator that says these 2 things
exactly match I just showed you what we
could do with the boylean operators
Alright.
Let's take a look now at comparing the
values of two cards.
Again we have our array of five cards,
our hand.
And we compare two cards, card1 and
card2.
So which has the greater value?
Is card1 a greater value than card2?
So you'll notice here what we're going to
do is Apply a different mask to the card.
This mask is value 0f, the value mask.
It has a one in the low order four bits.
So we're getting f-, the low order four
bits, which represent the value and
zeroing the suit.
And the way we get the suit zeroed is by
applying the logical AND with a mask that
has zeros in these positions.
So now the result won't necessarily be
there and if we compare 1 of those
extracted values to the other we can
simply get the greater relationship
between the 2.