[MUSIC].
Now that we've seen a basic encoding.
Let's turn our attention to encoding
integers.
And we're going to talk about both
unsigned integers positive numbers, as
well as signed integers.
Integers that can represent both positive
and negative values.
Let's start with a basic example of
binary number representation.
Here we see an 8 bit value represented by
8 binary bits labelled b7 through b0.
The most significant bit to the least
significant bit.
The reason we call them most significant
and least significant, is you'll notice
that b0 is a coefficient on 2 to the 0,
or 1.
This represents the ones column of the
number.
And b1 is the twos column of the number.
B5 is the 32s column.
And B6 is the 64s column, and so on.
A useful formula to remember is that if
we have an n bit quantity, then the
largest number we can represent is 2 to
the n minus 1.
In the case of 8 bits, with n equal to 8,
that would be the number 255.
Namely, 128 plus 64 plus 32 all the way
down to plus 1.
So let's take a look at a simple example
of addition and subtraction.
using basically the normal carried borrow
rules that we use for decimal addition
and subtraction.
Only in this case, since we have base-2
numbers, we'll be doing things with only
the digits 0 and 1.
Here's an example, 63 plus 8.
Is of course equal to 71.
The number 63 is represented by these
bits.
The number 8 is represented by these bits
and you should make sure that, that makes
good sense to you.
And when we add them up, you'll notice
we'll do a 1 and a 0 as a 1, a 1 and a 0
is also a 1.
A 1 and 0 again is 1.
But now a 1 plus 1 in this column yields
a 0 with a carry of 1.
So, we now add 1 0 plus the carry of 1
yields a 0 again, but a carry of 1.
So we do 1 plus 1 plus 0, again yields a
0 with a carry of 1 that ends up in this
position.
And this is the number 71, our result.
To do subtraction we do something very
similar.
Let's take, let's say we have the number
12 in binary and we wanted to subtract 7.
7 is represented by 0111.
And so if we do the subtraction we would
say 0 minus 1, of course is a 1 with a
borrow of 1.
1 minus 1 is a 0 and a 0 now because we
borrowed earlier.
0 minus 1 is a 1 again.
Without and we leave this as a 0 so the
result is 0101 which is in fact equal to
the number 5 what we'd expect, okay.
So, that's the basics of addition and
subtraction in binary.
So let's do the natural thing for
representing positive numbers.
they're going to rep, they're going to
correspond to all the unsigned integers
of the same value.
So in 8 bits, for example, we can go from
the x00 to the x7F and represent 127
different positive number.
But since we need about half of them to
be negative.
We're going to to save the other half
from 128 to 255 to really be used to
represent negative numbers rather then
those larger positive numbers.
So we're going to use the high order bit,
that b7, to indicate whether a number is
negative or not.
And often that most significant bit is
the sign bit.
This is called a sign and magnitude
representation.
Let me give you a few examples.
Here we have the number 0 and you'll
notice that it has a 0 in the most
significant bit.
So it's non-negative because the sign bit
is 0 and the value is 0.
Here we have another postitive number a
non-negative number.
where except for the sign bit, all the
other bits of 1.
That corresponds to the number 127.
Okay.
Now the other 2 numbers in these examples
are both negative numbers.
They have a 1 in the most significant
bit.
And can be used to represent for example
a minus 5.
In this case, this is the number 5 but
we're saying it's negative.
So we're going to basically just use that
sign bit to say whether we put a minus
sign in front of it or not.
In this case we have minus 0.
Which get's into one the problems of sign
and magnitude notations.
There's the 2 representations for 0.
The first line here was the positive 0.
This is the negative 0.
Well they're both 0s so this kind of,
this will cause some problems for us if
we use this representation.
Okay, so let's talk about sign and
magnitude negative numbers in a bit more
detail.
Here I'm showing a number wheel for 4-bit
binary numbers.
It starts at 000, and as we increment by
1, we move around to 1111.
And of course if we continued to
increment we'd go back to 0000.
Now, what I've also noted on the outside
of the circle is the number corresponding
to each bit pattern.
So you see here, we have our 0, 1, 2, 3,
all the way around to 7 and then we have
the negative numbers on this side with
the first bit being a 1.
Alright, so a minus 1 in binary is always
represented by the inside magnitude
binary with a leading 1 for the sign.
And then a value of 1 for the remainder
of the bits.
Okay, for the magnitude.
All right, so, the unfortunate side
effect of this, as we've said, is that we
have 2 values for 2 values that
correspond to 0.
A negative 0 and a positive 0.
So why is this an issue?
Well it makes math a little cumbersome.
Let's take a look at a little example.
If I do 4 minus 3 that corresponds to the
number 4 here 0100 minus 0011.
And if we do the arithmetic for that, of
course we see that the value is 1.
But now if we look at the nu-, the 4 plus
minus 3 which should yield the same
result, we see that in fact, 4 plus a
minus 3 yields minus 7.
Well that's not the same as 1.
so we now would have to worry about how,
what order in which we do the additions
and subtraction.
this is not something that we want to be
dealing with when we think about
arithmetic in our programming languages.
So instead of using sign and magnitude
numbers computer systems today use what
is called Two's Complement negatives.
And let's go back to that representation
of a minus 1.
So instead of using the sign bit at the
front to, the most significant bit to
just represent the minus sign in front of
the 1.
What we're going to do is give that most
significant bit a large negative weight.
Alright remember each of the bits has a
certain weight corresponding to the
column that they're in.
So bits 0 through the second to last bit
represent the values 1, 2, 4, 8, 16 and
so on.
Well what were going to do is have the
most significant bit represented as the W
minus 1 bit.
Or in this case would correspond to that
b7 we had in our previous slide when W is
equal to 8.
It would actually add a na, a negative
weight to the number.
In this case, the negative weight would
be minus 128.
2 to the 7th is 128.
And then minus 128.
So let's take a look at an unsigned
number here.
1010, that corresponds to 1 times 2 to
the 3 plus 0 times 2 to the 2 and so on
to yield the number 10 decimal.
In 2's complement, 1010 would be
interpreted a little bit differently.
You notice that now we have a minus 1 for
the first bit, the most significant bit.
Alright?
That's that large negative weight.
In this case minus 8.
So that when we add this up we see that
this corresponds to the negative number 6
in base 10.
using two's complement notation.
So a minus 1 is represented as 1111,
right.
Minus 8 plus 7 for the remainder, so that
would add up to minus 1.
All right, so that looks, a lot like, we
solved our problem here because what
we've essentially done is shifted our
number wheel a little bit.
So now the numbers are the same on the
right hand side.
You see we go from 0 to plus 7 but the
numbers with deleting 1 are now in a
different order then they were before.
We started minus 1 up here go around to
minus 2 to minus 3 to minus 4.
[COUGH] All the way to minus 8.
What's important to note here is that now
we only have one representation of 0,
namely all the bits are set to 0.
And you'll notice that minus 1 is
immediately adjacent to 0.
So, it looks like things can flow on a
number wheel by doing basic addition and
subtraction, and get that to work.
For example, if I start at 2 and take
three steps back I do in fact get to
minus 1.
That wasn't the case with sign magnitude
notation.
The other nice thing about two's
compliment notation is that its very easy
to obtain the negative number from its
positive of magnitude.
All I have to do is take a bit wise
complement of the number, of the positive
number and add 1.
And that gives me the negative version of
that original number.
Interesting interesting fact that makes
it very easy to take the negatives of
numbers.
Okay, so let's take a look at 2's
complement arithmetic in some more
detail.
What's nice about 2's complement is the
same addition procedure now works for
both unsigned and 2's complement
integers.
So we only have to build one kind of
adder in our processors.
Let's take a look at the example 4 plus
3.
Here we have the positive number 4 the
positive number 3.
We do a straight addition and we get a
result of 7.
That works out well.
On the righthand side we have minus 4
plus 3.
'Kay, you'll notice that when we add that
up we get all 1s.
That corresponds to minus 1.
That's correct as well.
Now let's take a look at the middle here.
4 minus 3 that's the example we did
before that should have yielded 1.
And now with 2's compliment numbers we
have a 40100 but our minus 3 is 1101.
And when we add this up we get the
result, 0001.
Of course we do have a carry out of 1
that we're going to drop.
And because we have our 4 bits of
precision here.
And the result is 0001.
Exactly the value we expected to see.
the drop and carry makes this modulo
edition.
So we say that this is addition modulo 2
to the w, or modulo modulo 256, in this
case, with w equal to 8.
Or in the examples here with w equal to
4, it's modulo 16.
Why does 2's complement notation work out
so well?
well, let's try to look at it a different
way.
Whenever we have a positive integer we'd
like the negative number representation
of that same integer.
to always add up to 0 if we sum it with
the positive version.
So let's take a look at the numbers
00001.
what we have to add to that in order to
get all zeros, right.
What we really want to be negative 1 is
whatever bit pattern gives us that same
result.
And we know now that, that in fact is the
pattern all 1s.
Which when we add will cause a carry to
ripple down this entire sequence of one's
to yield all 0s with a carry out of 1.
That we'll be dropping and ignoring,
because we do modular 256 arithmetic.
In the case of the number two, we want
the number minus 2 here.
What bit pattern would yield that?
Well, we'd expect it to have a 0 here.
So that 0 plus 0 would come out to 0.
[COUGH].
Then a 1 in the second position, so that
one plus 1 is also a 0.
And then a sequence of 1s to ripple that
carry through.
So a minus 2 looks like this value, okay.
And you'll notice that that's just the
bit pattern of the number 2 complemented
and then adding a 1.
So if we complemented every one of these
bits.
We would get 111101, but then when we add
1, we would actually get this value here,
which is our minus 2.
And then for 3, it's the same situation.
The pattern that, the pattern that would
yield all the 0s looks like this.
Which you'll notice again, is just a bit
wise compliment of the original 3 plus 1
added in.
Okay, so that's how 2s compliment works.
If we look at these numbers now in terms
of the possible big patterns that we can
have in four bits.
From 000 to 1111, we'll notice that for
the first 7 numbers the positive values,
signed and unsigned numbers are exactly
the same.
But now for unsigned, we continue on to
8, 9, 10 all the way up to 15.
While for signed representations, the
value that would have been 8 now
corresponds to minus 8.
And the value that would have been 15
corresponds to minus 1.
Now, of course both signed and unsigned
integers have limits.
There's only so far we can go until we
run out of patterns to use.
So, for example, if we tried to add 6
plus 4, the result would be 10, and we
could not represent that as a signed
number.
There's just not enough bits to do that.
You notice that there is no pattern that
corresponds to the number 10.
If they were unsigned numbers we could,
because we have a pattern of 10, for ten.
in seeing we also use the notation 15u to
signify an unsigned number.
In this case 15u plus 2u.
Yields 17 and that would not fit into any
of our representations, signed or
unsigned.
Okay.
We can also have a number that is too
small for example minus 7, minus 3
unsigned would yield as signed numbers
would yield minus 10.
And you'll notice that there is no
pattern for minus 10.
We only get up to to minus 8.
And then if they were unsigned we still
have a problem because 0 unsigned minus 2
would be negative 2.
Well we cannot represent negative numbers
in unsigned formats.
So we'd be in trouble there as well.
So the CPU.
when it's when it's given this kind these
kinds of arithmetics to do will throw an
exception.
Meaning it will signal that it got a
number that it can't represent.
and it does that for signed values.
But most CPUs do not do this for unsigned
values.
And, C and Java, both languages, will
just cruse along and not bother checking
that the arithmatic was correct or not.
So you have to do an explicit check if
you really want to know if the arithmatic
worked out correctly.
And we'll see that again later on.
Alright, jsut a quick visualization of
what is going on here.
If we start off with a 2s complement
number that can go from minus 2 to the w
minus 1 to plus 2 to the w minus 1.
When we move it to unsigned value a
represented as an unsigned value.
Of course those positive values stay the
same but the negative numbers now look
like big positive values.
'Kay.
And similarly, going in the other
direction.
If we start with an unsigned number, the
smaller numbers can just move straight
across the 2s complement notation.
But the large positive numbers, the ones
that start with that leading 1.
Now get interpreted as negative numbers,
if we think of the representation as 2s
complement.
So, we have to remember which type of
number we have in memory.
Is it a 2s complement number or is it an
unsigned integer?
And that's part of how we get into types
in these different languages data types
in these different languages.
Here were showing the addition of 2
numbers can yield a value that's very
negative or a value that's very positive.
the values again that are in teh midrange
can just move straight alogn no problem
to the 2s compliment representation.
But the very large positive numbers get
interpreted as negatives.
The very large negative numbers end up
getting interpreted as big positives.
Okay, so that's where we would run into
trouble in our arithmetic if we generate
too large a number, or too negative a
number.
Okay, some values to remember when we're
thinking about integers is for unsigned
values.
we have a special value called UMin,
which is the smallest number we can
represent that's 0.
The pattern of all 0's and the maximum,
UMax is the unsigned max, is all 1s
obviously.
And that would correspond to the 2 to the
w minus 1.
While in 2's compliment TMin is 2's
compliment minimum is the biggest
negative number we can have which would
be the pattern of 1 all 0 followed by all
0s.
And then TMax is 0 followed by all 1s.
So the maximum numbers only half as big
as it was before the unsigned values.
And a negative 1 is represented by the
sequence of all 1s.
Ffff we would do in 32 bits.
Okay.
So for a word size of 16, we would see
these value for UMax, TMax, and TMin.
these would be the x representations of
them and their binary representations.