[MUSIC].
In this video we're going to talk about
shifting operations for both unsigned and
signed integers and see how that how, how
we need to do some sign extension for
sign values.
Let's get started with just the case of
unsigned integers.
What I'm showing here is both the, Left
shift operation, and the Right shift
operation, in[UNKNOWN] and you'll notice
we used the double less than sign, and
the double greater than sign to indicate
those.
But don't think of them as less than or
greater than.
Those are just symbols for those shift
operators.
we just use those because they kind of
look like a move to the left and a move
to the right.
So, when we say x shifted to the left by
y, what we mean is we're going to move
the bit patter of x to the left by that
many positions the value of y.
Let's take a look at this example here,
here's the number six.
represented in eight bits and we're going
to shift to the left by 3.
So, in this case the y value is 3.
And what we'd expect to have happened, is
that those bits would move over by three
positions, okay?
And you'll notice that high order three
bits, the most significant bits.
we're going to kind of lose, they're just
going to drop off the end.
And we're going to have a hole left over
on the right of, three bits that we need
to fill.
And we're just going to fill that with
zeroes.
Okay?
Now, the right shift is very analogous.
We're just going to move things over by
two.
In this case we've lost the one and the
zero, the two least significant bits.
And we have a hole of two on the left to
fill in.
And we're just going to put zeros in
there.
Okay, so that's the basic left-shift and
right-shift operator.
Let's take a look at another example.
But before we do that actually, let me
just take a look at these values here.
I said that this was the number six.
This turns out to be the number 48.
And this is the number one.
So, when we did a left shift by 3, what
we did was essentially multiply that 6 by
the value 8.
How did we get 8?
That's 2 to the 3rd power.
the number of bits were moving to the
left.
Okay?
so we can use shifts to often do
multiplications quickly, by, because
these are much simpler operations to
implement in hardware than a multiplier
would be.
but of course, we can only do powers of
two.
Similarly a shift to the right is a
division operation, in this case we took
the six and divided it by two to the two
or four and we got one as a result.
Now you see in fact we probably wanted
one point five but we cant represent
fractional values, so it got rounded down
to one okay.
Let's take a look at this other example
with the number 242.
represented in our eight bits when we
shift to left by three we're going to
multiply that by eight, so we're going to
get this value, which is actually the
number 144.
Well that's not 242.
Multiplied by eight.
Well, that's a much larger number and way
larger than the 255 which is our maximum
value for an 8-bit unsigned integer.
So, we're, we're, we have an overflow
here, so we're going to get a value that
doesn't really make any sense.
So, this tells us that.
You know, when we're thinking about doing
multiplications using shift.
We've got to check the number before we
shift it, to make sure that the result
will in fact fit in the, in, in the eight
bits that we have, or whatever number of
bit word we have.
But, if we do a divide by four, or a
right shift by two we would expect to get
a result of 60.5 and in fact that is the
value that we get.
This is 60.
Of course it got rounded, it's not 60.5
so we have that rounding issue again.
Okay, let's take a look now at a signed
integers.
It's a little bit different situation.
here I'm showing a signed integer that's
equivalent to the number 98.
and we're going to left shift it by 3
multiply by again this is way too big a
number.
we're going to get a result that is
equivalent to 16 which is wrong of course
because we should have got 784.
Alright, so now let's try the right
shift, divide by four.
right shift by two and we would want to
see the number 24.5 of course we can't
get the 24, we can't get the 24.5 we're
just going to get 24.
The rounded version of 24.5 okay, now, in
in dealing with signed integers, we have
to think about that sign pit that we
didn't have to think about before.
So in, we also have another kind of right
shift called an arithmetic shift, where
instead of filling in those two bits with
zeroes, we're going to fill in those two
bits with a copy.
Of the signed bit, the most significant
bit.
In this case that turns out to be exactly
the same thing so we see any difference.
But let's take a look at what happens
with a negative number.
so down here we have an example with the
number minus 94 and again multiplying it
by eight.
Doing that left shift by three, is going
to yield too negative a number and we're
going to end up with a result of 16,
which is just clearly wrong again.
and again that's because now we've had an
underflow, we had too negative a number
as a result.
When we divide by 4 by shifting to the
right by 2.
We would want the result to be minus
23.5.
But if we just fill in with zeros, as we
do for our logical shift then we're
going to get a result of 40, which is
also clearly wrong.
It's not even negative.
we've totally lost that sign bit.
And that's why we have arithmetic shifts.
In this case, again we're going to copy
that most significant bit.
Into those bit positions, so instead of
ending up with a positive number we still
have a negative value.
In this case we have a negative value
minus 24 which isn't the minus 23.5 we
would want but again it's a rounded
version of that okay it's minus 24.
And one thing to keep in mind is in C
things are undefined if we shift try to
shift by a negative number or by
something larger than the word size.
The result is undefined and we could
expect to just get junk as a result of
that.
Alright let's see how the shift
operations can be used for more
interesting things though than just doing
basic multiplication and division by a
power of two.
Here I'm showing how we can extract the
second most significant byte of an
integer using Shift and Masking.
All right, so, the example we're going to
start with is this 32-bit pattern.
And we want the second most significant
byte.
That's the one with the red box around
it.
And we can get that to all the way over
to the right by shifting that value by 16
to the right.
Okay?
So, now we've moved that byte over to the
low order eight bits.
And you notice we padded with zeros on
the far left end.
Our next operation is what is called a
masking operation, were going to use this
bit pattern which is all zeros except for
ones in the low or the byte.
That's represented by the value 0xFF in
hexadecimal.
So, all 1s in the, in the low order byte.
And when we mask that, or AND, do a
logical bit-wise AND with our our shifted
value, we will just get the result of
that first byte, because ANDing,
remember, with a 1 the result is just the
other value.
While ANDing with a zero, the results
will always be zero.
And we'll just end up with all zeros
everywhere else, okay.
So, that masking operation is very
powerful that way.
We can also use shifting and masking to
extract the sign bit on an integer.
For example, if we just wanted to know if
it was positive or negative.
What we can do is take the, the signed
integer x, shift it to the right by 31
bits, so that the signed bit ends up in
the low order bit position.
And then AND it with the number one,
which just has a one in that one
position.
Right, about low order bit.
And everything else will get cleared out
to zero, so that's how we can extract the
sign bit and our result will either be
zero if the sign bit was zero or a one if
the sign bit was one.
And that makes it easy for us to test at
that number.
what's positive or negative.
We can also do conditional as Boolean
expressions, remember, let's assume that
the Boolean value is either zero or one
for now, not anything else.
In C, I can do a conditional with an if
statement.
I can write if x meaning if x is true,
then assign the value of y to a,and if x
is false, the else clause assign the
value of z to a.
In C I can also write it in this notation
using a question mark, so that i can fit
it all into an assignment statement.
This says a is equal to either y or z,
depending on the value of x.
If x is one then it will be y.
If x is zero it will be the value z and
we use that question mark and colon to
delineate those.
Okay, so that's how we can see how we can
use these conditionals using shift
operations.
What you'll see down here is two
expressions.
One for the if part of the clause and the
other for the else part of the clause,
and lets look at the one on the.
left first.
You'll notice that what I'm doing is
shifting x first to the left by 31 and
then to the right by 31.
Well, that doesn't seem to make much
sense it's kind of doing, should be
ending up back where we started but in
fact we don't.
Because when we shift to the left by 31,
we're losing 31 bits off the end.
And then when we shift back the right
we're doing an arithmetic shift that will
copy that most significant bit all the
way down through all 32 bits.
So, our result will be, if we started
with x of 0, we'll end up with all zeros,
and if we started with an x of equal to
1, we shifted that 1 lowered bit all the
way over to the left.
And then arithmetically shifted back it
over to the right, filling in behind it
with all 1s.
So, we'll either have a vector that's all
zeros or all ones.
And when we and that with y and it's all
zeros, we'll just come up with a bunch of
zeros, and that'll be it.
And if they're all ones, we'll just have
the value of y.
On the other side, we're just doing the
complementary thing by first
complementing x and then doing that shift
to the left and shift to the right.
So, now we'll end up with z effects was 1
to begin with was 0 to begin with and all
0's effects was 1.
Okay?
Then the addition operator will just
combine those values and one of them will
be 0, so we'll just end up with the other
one, and that's how we get y or z.
Into the value, into the variable a.
Okay, that might be a little convoluted.
You might want to spend some time looking
at that.
but sometimes you'll see expressions like
this in a C program and it's important to
understand where they came from.
Alright, so that sign extension is really
important and so let's take a look at
that in a little bit more detail.
What we're showing here is a value of x
represented in w bits and we're
converting it into a value of x into
something larger then w bits.
Let's say we're going from 32 bits to 64,
what we're going to do is copy the 31 low
order bits just directly down into the
larger representation.
But then the most significant bit we will
copy throughout the upper 32 bits and we
do that to keep the number positive.
If it was originally positive or negative
if it was originally negative.
Okay, so lets take a look at some sign
extension examples here I'm showing a
short int that is representative in 16
bits.
Okay, and then were going to cast it into
a 32 bit int.
So, we're going to go from short int to
int.
And what we'll see is for the number
12345, it's represented in 16 bits with
that pattern, and then when we cast it
into 32 bits, we're just sign extending
that 0 sign bit into all the upper 16
bits.
Of the larger word.
For a negative value, if we use negative
12345 it's represented by this bit
pattern.
You can tell it's a negative number
because the higher order bit is a one and
when we sign extend it into the larger
representation of 60, of 32 bits, we copy
that one throughout those upper 16 bits.
Okay?
And so sign extension is used both when
we're doing arithmetic shifts to the
right as well as when we're casting a
value into a larger bit path.