[MUSIC].
Hi, my name is Caitlin Bailey, and I'm
here today to talk to you about C.
C is one of my favorite programming
languages to work with, but sometimes it
can be a bit intimidating to people to
begin with.
the reason why is a little bit more crazy
in what it can allow you to do.
But we're going to take you through two
simple programs today, to show you how
the basic C works, and you'll learn more
over the course of this course.
Okay, so I'm working today in a virtual
machine in a terminal inside that virtual
machine.
You can do this on your own computer,
whether that's a desktop or a laptop or
remotely or some other way.
Just make sure you have access to a
computer with a command line that you can
use.
Now, I'm assuming that you have some
basic familiarity with command line
arguments, and with some program language
whether that's Java or C++.
Something that introduces you to if else,
while, for and other things like that.
Variable declaration.
Okay.
So, really briefly a couple of command
line arguments you might find useful.
So, you can do PWD, which I've actually
already done here, which shows you where
you are on the computer.
You can also change the directory and you
can see this reflected here.
so you can CD back and print where you
are.
And then you can CD back into intro C,
which is where I am.
Okay.
You can also list the contents in the
directories you're in with LS.
And that shows you the files we're
going to look at.
so I've compiled a couple of these, but
the non complied versions are
hello_world.c and print_bytes.c.
Unsurprisingly, they end in C.
So, I'm using EMacs today, which is one
of my favorite editors, but just find
something that you're familiar with and
use it.
So that could be EMacs, that could be VI,
that could be VEM, TextMate,
Textwrangler, or something you can pull
of off the internet.
It doesn't really matter, just find
something you're really comfortable
editing in.
Okay, so the structure this Hello World
program is really, really simple.
We've got a header comment, which just
puts your name, the date, what the
program is about, pretty standard stuff
for comments.
And then we've got some include
statements.
the include today is standard IO and
standard lib, and that allows you to
print things out to the terminal and
include basic types like int, okay?
You're later going to want to include
more and more things as you pull in more
and more defitinions from outside
libraries.
Because these are included in angle
brackets, you're going to know that there
are system libraries.
So they're installed in /user/lib no
/include.
Sorry, mistake.
If you wanted to include your own files,
you could include them using quotation
marks.
So you could include, myheader.h.
Just like that.
And that would include your header
definitions in .h.
I don't have that file in my directory,
so I'm going to delete that, but if you
did, you could include that way.
Now, Main is kind of special in C, it's
got to include these two parameters: Arg
C and Arg V.
Arg C is the count of arguments you want
passed to Main and Arg V is those
arguments.
So a lot of times these are the command
line arguments because you usually invoke
C from the command line.
So if you've included two parameters, so
for instance the name of your program and
some file you wanted to output
information to, there would be two
arguments.
The second is an array of strings that
puts to those arguments.
Now, I said its an array of strings, but
it kind of looks like it's an array of
something else, right?
Because we've got a char star instead of
string.
Well that's because in C, char stars are
strings.
Okay?
They're an array of string array of
characters is actually a string.
We'll talk more about that later when we
get to basic types in this course.
Now, I'm going to actually print out a
statement.
Print F, allows you to print out Hello
World, and end it with a new line /n.
Okay?
Now, this is slightly different than in
system.out.
println in Java, you don't include the
new line by default.
But other than that, it's pretty similar.
And the you're going to return zero.
Now that return indicates excess and
matches the return tape we have up here.
Okay, simple.
To compile it, you're going to do this.
And, I'm not including any other flags,
but you could if you wanted to.
Compile with GCC-O.
Hello in this case is the executable, and
Hello World is the source.
Compile with no warnings or errors,
great.
Always what we want to see.
You're going to run it, and if I spell it
correctly, you'll see that it actually
works, runs.
Hello world, great.
To move on to the next program, we're
going to open it up.
And you're going to see print bytes.
Now, the structure is really similar
here.
We've got the header, we've got our
includes, the same includes and we've got
a Main.
If you wanted to add in other functions,
you do that above main, because you have
to declare them before you use them.
Now you can just declare it above and
define it later, but usually you see
declarations and definitions in one line
and man ends up at the bottom of the
file.
Okay.
So, you've got a function here.
To call it, you're just going to go down
into main and you're going to type it in.
Pretty simple stuff, again some of the
other languages you might have seen.
And I'll call it using the number that
I've already defined, which is 4058.
So that's a variable declaration and
definition here.
I've called my new function and now I'm
going to call print F.
But this print F looks slightly
different, it's got format characters in
it.
That's percent D and percent X.
Now, both of those refer to num, and
that's because you can print it off in
different formats.
So the first one, percent D, allows you
to print it off in decimal format.
The second one allows you to print it off
in hex, which is percent 08X.
Now, I did 08 because I'm expecting eight
characters, and I want to print them all
out.
Anything I don't have I'll print in
zeros.
That's what the zero is for.
Now, the next thing I've got down here is
a for loop.
So, we've got inti, which is just the
counter for the for loop.
And then the for loop includes: i equals
zero, i less than some limit, i plus
plus.
Again, very standard, the control fluency
looks very similar to anything else
you've seen.
So, my limit here is actually size of int
and because that's dependent on the
architecture, whether its 32 or 64 or
something else, or it could be dependent.
we use size of, which automatically plugs
in the appropriate sizes based on the
system definitions.
My other variable declaration here, is
the mask.
And that is just 0xff which in hex means
one byte.
Okay?
Anything else is zeros and that means
that if I end this with anything else,
you'll get just one byte.
The least significant byte.
This is exactly what we want.
One byte at a time we're going to do
this.
Now to isolate the first bit, we just
need to end it with that mask.
But to get the others, we need to shift
them over.
And so I'm using a shift by eight bits
times i.
You can go through this later and see
what it looks like, but it ends up
printing them all out.
And to print it, I'm going to print the
decimal and then I'm going to print the
hex of that single byte.
So, again, this is really simple.
It just shows you some basic control
flow, print statements and variable
declarations.
So that's what it looks like and if you
wanted to compile it, you would do this.
Print bytes.
No warnings, no errors, exactly what you
want to see.
And you can call it, and there we go.
So you can see Hi, which was my function
definition before, just printed out hi,
and here's the main.
So, we have our announcement, that this
is what we're going to do.
4058 in hex is actually this number.
You can do it out on paper or in your
head and it works out to be FTA.
And if we print them out starting with
the least significant byte, you get DA,
and then 0F, and 00 and 00.
So, our shifting worked to move over just
a couple of characters at a time, or one
byte.
Very effective.
This is the really basic introduction to
C.
I hope that you get more comfortable with
it as the course goes on.
There's lots of resources online and in
books.
I definitely recommend using K&R which is
the classic C book Kernighan and Ritchie
and good luck.