[MUSIC] Welcome to the hardware, software
interface.
My name is Gaetano Borriello.
>> And my name is Luis Ceze.
>> And we're going to tell you a little bit
ourselves, about ourselves to start
things off.
Ah,I've been at UW since 1988.
I have a PhD from UC Berkeley in Computer
Science.
And my hometown is Naples, Italy where
we're famous for wood fired ovens that
make delicious pizza.
And I have a research trajectory that's
taken me through quite a few research
communities.
I started off as an integrated circuit
designer and moved through network
sensors.
And now, I am building mobile
applications in the developing world.
>> And I'm Luis Ceze.
I was born and raised and San Paolo,
Brazil.
I haven't been at UW quite as long as
Gaetano.
About, you know, 20 years later, I
started UW.
And I got my PhD at University of
Illinois.
And I did work on computer architecture
and compilers.
And now it's[INAUDIBLE] work in those
areas as well as energy efficiency.
So Brazil is known for beaches and I love
going to the beach.
However Brazil is also known for soccer,
but I do not like soccer.
So don't talk to me about soccer, I don't
know anything about it.
>> Okay, we also wanted to show you where we
work.
that's the Paul G Allen Center for
Computer Science and Engineering, at the
University of Washington.
And it's a gorgeous building, with a
beautiful six story high atrium.
And we're also known for the cherry
blossoms on our campus.
Which just recently bloomed, this March
and our mascot the husky.
lastly, we're also known for Mt Rainier
and some of the gorgeous mountain views
around campus.
>> Who are you?
So there are literally thousands of you
and, so that means we don't get to know
you face to face.
It's too bad.
But please do fill out our online forms,
so we get to know a few things about you.
And we're going to report aggregate
statistics so we know who you all are.
>> Hi, so what is this class about.
The has an interesting title.
The hardware, software interface.
And so, what is hardware?
And what is software?
And what do we need to understand about
this inner, interface in between.
So hardware of course, is the, the,
physical hardware.
The chips that run the instructions that
make all of our modern computing systems
possible.
Software is the code that we take through
a series of steps.
And compile down to the basic
instructions that, that hardware knows
how to execute.
And what this class is about is how do we
get from those high level languages down
to the primitive instructions that are
present in our hardware processors.
That's what the hardware software
interface is about.
>> So we expect you to, to know some, some
things.
For example basics of Binary numbers.
So we have an example, we have two
numbers both base 2.
So they're both Binary numbers and say if
you're trying to add 1001.
With 001, you get 1010.
We also expect you to binary logic
operators like And, Or and Not.
For example A and B, A and B is true if
and only if A is true and B is true or
false otherwise, okay.
We also expect you to know introductory
programming in Java or C would be even
better
And none of the fancy stuff, just if
statements, loops, and procedures and
methods would be enough.
We also expect you to have access to
modern personal computer.
So you can run the tools required to run
the assignments in this class.
>> Okay, so what are the outcomes of this
course?
As Louise said, we just expect you to
have some of the basics of computer
programming, nothing too fancy.
most of our students here, at UW know
Java.
But other languages are probably just as
good.
we are going to take you into this class
to help you understand those abstractions
that exist between those programs.
And that hardware that they run on.
But not only what those abstractions are,
but why they exist, and how they build
upon each other.
That's really the important aspect of
this course.
And to do that, we're going to take you
through some of the implementation
details of these underlying abstractions.
The hope here, is that this will make you
more effective programmers.
Able to understand the many factors that
influence a programs correctness and
performance.
So, in the end we hope you'll be much
better setup for following on to future
classes in computing.
With a good solid foundation for how this
stuff really comes together.
>> And to achieve the outcomes that Gaetano
just told you, here's what we're going to
have you do.
You're going to have 5 programming
assignments.
1 every 1 to 2 weeks.
And we're also going to recommend pencil
and paper problems for your own benefit.
And we're going to point you to relevant
sections of the book.
So we are, that said we really want to
make the lecture self contained.
And review the text book main
supplementary material for second point
of view.
But we do expect you to read them.
>> Okay, so about those reference texts.
And again, these are purely recommended,
they're not required in by, in it, by any
means.
but you might find them helpful.
the, the first is the Computer Systems
text by Bryant and O'Hallaron.
This is a great book that the second
edition came out just a few years ago.
And, you can get it from lots of places.
The book also has an extensive web site
at CMU.
And, we also would like you to have a
reference for the C programming language
which we'll be using in this class.
Now there's lots of options here.
we recommend, we have a few
recommendations here on the slide.
But really anything will do.
And there's lots of info even available
on the web, if you don't want to bother
purchasing a text.
>> it takes a lot work to put a class
together, and this class is no exception.
So there's a lot of people that were
behind in, in making this course happen.
First the TA's that work behind the
scenes.
In as well as the previous Coursera
instructures, instructors at UW who
taught us about all of the things that we
should and should not do when teaching
this class.
and this class actually being taught,
this, version of this class is being
taught in many places.
In, including CMU where the authors of
the book that we just talked about are.
Like Randy Bryant and David O'Hallaron
and all the instructors at CMU.
And you know?
Mike, Matt Welsh, she used to be at
Harvard,.
And now a Google's Shadow also taught
this class, and gave us a lot of material
and feedback.
And the instructors at UW Peter Hornyack,
Hal Perkins, and John Zajhorjan.
>> Alright, so thank you.
And we look forward to having you in the
class.
>> Definitely, see you soon.
>> Bye bye.
>> Bye.