[MUSIC] So what is this class about?
Well, this class is about the hardware,
software interface.
But to understand that, first let's see
what's hardware.
Well, hardware is the part of the
computer made of atoms, it's the physical
part of your, computing device.
Okay.
In software, it's this thing made of bits
which is the program that runs on top of
your hardware.
Okay.
But for that to happen effectively there
are many many layers of abstractions
between the hardware and the software,
okay?
And this will be called the hardware
software interface.
And the reason we want you to understand
what the hardware software interface is
is that it's going to help you understand
better how computers work.
It's going to make you a more effective
programmer, it's going to make you better
at writing efficient codes.
And it's just going to make you a better
computer science, scientist.
So, let's look at these three pieces of
code here.
So, here we have a simple statement that
does a conditional and performs an
assignment.
And this is written in, you know, a
language like C or Java, okay?
Now, this piece of code here is also a,
well it's also a program.
And this is written in what we call the
assembly language, okay?
The assembly language is just a much
lower level language that's pretty to
close to hardware.
And it just happens to be an abstraction,
a simple way of looking at machine code.
Okay, so the machine code is just a
sequence of 0's and 1's.
Processors only understand 0's and 1's it
interprets them in different ways.
Now, so what's in common between these
three pieces of codes?
Well all of them we're exactly the same
thing their equivalent but you'd rather
write in this language here because it's
much easier.
it's much more natural for humans to
write, okay, so it's much more human
friendly.
But as I said before the hardware likes
bit strings.
So 0s and 1s.
So a digital computer likes 0s and 1s
because it's very easy to represent with
electronic sequence because 0s is a low
voltage and 1 can, can be represented as
a high voltage, okay?
So and the, the, the machine machine
structure is actually much shorter than
the number of bits we would need to
represent the characters in the assembly
language.
It's a, much, it's a much more dense
encoding of the assembly language, the
assembly instructions that we see here.
Okay?
There's a very direct correspondence
between these, simple assembly
instructions, and some of the bits in
machine code.
Now let's look at a hard or soft
interface from a historical perspective.
So at first the hardware, the hard or
soft interface was very, very simple
because in because hardware was simple.
Hardware was very, very primitive when
computers started.
Okay.
So humans was were able to write code
directly to hardware without any
abstraction at all.
But then people got [INAUDIBLE] and that
means that software was very primitive.
Because the the soft improvements
reflected the hardware pretty closely.
But then people got really excited about
computers.
It's like hey,computers can do all these
things.
So they decided, they end up writing more
and more complex pieces of code.
That meant that humans could no longer,
you know keep up with the complexity of
writing machine code directly.
So, uh,the assembly language was
invented.
The assembly language, as I said before
is a very very simple computer
programming language.
That's pretty close what a hardware can
do in terms of it's primitives and one
assembly instruction translates to one
machine instruction.
Okay?
So but the big difference is that the
assembly language is much easier for
humans to read because they have, first
of all, they have characters strings as
opposed to just bits.
Okay so humans can understand much, much
easier so it's much easier to read and
write.
And you can also use symbolic names for
values.
And you can use thing like writes their
names, a, b and so on, okay.
So now there's a piece of code here
called Assembler.
That takes a program written in Assembly
and generates zeros and ones Machine
code, which is what the hardware likes.
But even then that, that wasn't enough
because you know, programs were getting
more and more complex.
We needed yet another level of
abstraction that's much higher level.
Okay?
So this is thing so these languages such
as languages like C and java they're
much, much higher level.
You can write statements like you know, a
equals b plus c for example.
Okay?
And one statement in, this high level
language can translate to many, many,
assembly language instructions.
Okay?
So, but now, we have yet another, another
component in our path from the user to
the hardware here, which is a C compiler.
Okay.
The C Compiler takes C code and generates
assembly code.
[UNKNOWN] this is assembly.
Okay.
So and that's much high lever that means
you must have much more productive at
writing code for that.
So now, let's look at the entire lifetime
of a computer program.
And computer program has three basic
steps in it's life time.
There's coding time which is the time
that humans spent writing the program
high level language like C.
Compile time is the time it takes to get
your C program, and generates machine
code executed by the hardware.
Okay?
And when the hardware's executing the
code, we call that run time.
Okay?
So, now compare time is something that
happens just once, and if you execute
Your program many, many, many times.
That means that it can advertise a cost
of compilation a lot, because, you know,
if you spend some time compiling the
program you're going to execute so many
times.
It doesn't matter if you spend a little
bit more time doing compilation, okay?
And in fact, during this process here.
During the compilation process, the
compiler can spend a little bit more time
generating the code.
In order to do optimizations that are
going to make.
You program faster without having the
programmer improve the code itself.
Although if you do want to generate
really fast codes, you do want to
regenerate, you do want to start with
good algorithms first.
Okay?
So a big thing in this class then is how
to hardware software interface, okay?
So just, so that includes how to
hardware, you know, with 0s and 1s and
processor executing instruction.
Relates to software In other words your,
your for example your Java program.
And the other big, the other part of this
thing is that computer's about
abstractions.
Computer systems are complex.
In order for humans to understand and
design effective computer systems, we
need abstractions.
Okay.
So, computer's a lot about abstractions
but, we can't really forget reality.
Well, the goal of an abstraction is to
abstract reality and make it simpler to
think about.
But we don't to completely ignore reality
because that leads to inefficiencies and
leads to other problems.
Okay.
So, what, we also going to talk about
what are the abstractions that, that we
use and what do you need to know about
them, okay.
So well, you know when they break down
and you have to peek under the hood.
You also want to know because it will
help [INAUDIBLE] bacause it helps with
what kind of bugs can they cause and how
you find them and so on.
But knowing the hardware and software
interface ultimately is going to make you
better programmers.
It's going to help you begin to
understand important concepts that have
evolved er, in building ever more complex
computer systems.