[MUSIC] Let's take a look at the roadmap
for the course what we'll be going
through over these next eight weeks.
We're going to start off with the topic
of memory and data.
How do we organize data in the memory of
a computer system?
And then we're going to move on to, how
do we represent numbers?
How do we encode different types of
numbers?
both integers and floating point numbers,
in the bit patterns that we can put in
memory.
we'll then turn our attention to how we
encode instructions, that basically the
machine code.
That the CPU will interpret to figure out
what to do, what data to find in memory,
where to find it, and what operations to
perform on that data.
This these instructions are normally
represented in an assembly language
that's a little bit more machine readable
than those ones and zeros.
this is one of the languages we'll be
looking at.
It's the X86 assembly language for the
popular Intel processors that are in many
of our computer systems today.
However, any assembly language is really
going to be very similar.
So, we're hoping this is just a, an
example of one possible assembly language
albeit, a very common one.
We'll then turn our attention to some
approaches to managing how we keep track
of our programs and how they're
executing.
Namely, what procedures are being
executed, where a procedure should return
when it completes.
And that'll get us into the stack
discipline, that we use for representing
that information.
we'll then turn our attention to
representing some more complex things in
memory besides just numbers namely arrays
of values and structs more complicated
data structures.
where multiple values are represented in
one entity.
then we'll turn our attention to memory
and caches.
So, we'll be looking at memory from the
point of view of performance.
How a processor moves the data that it
needs most often.
And keeps it close to the CPU.
By close we mean in a faster access
memory rather than the slower larger
memories that we might also have
available.
Then we'll turn our attention to two
important Illusions that are common in
modern computer systems.
The first one is the concept of a process
namely, a program that runs in parallel
to a whole bunch of other processes.
And, we have to figure out how to give
the illusion that each process has full
control over the processor, so that a
programmer doesn't have to worry about.
How to hand off control to another
process, how to save the state it might
need.
All these things are going to be taken
care of automatically, and this will help
us touch on a little bit about how
operating systems handle these things for
us as programmers.
The second illusion is, virtual memory,
namely the ability to think about a huge
memory that is available to each program,
when in reality there's only a much
smaller finite memory available.
that is way, way smaller than the
possible memory we may want to use.
So, this will get us into how do we page
different parts of memory from disc into
the physical memory.
And again, deal with some operating
systems issues.
Finally, we'll close the course with some
issues in memory allocation.
Namely, how do we decide where we put
stuff in memory, and how does that impact
performance?
And lastly, how do we deal with higher
level languages, like Java which abstract
the away a lot of those memory allocation
issues from us.
And we'll compare Java to C, which is a
lower level language, where we actually
consider each of those memory allocations
each one in turn and have to free up
memory when we're done using it.
Have to keep track of quite a few more
things, than in a higher level managed
language like Java.
So, that's the road map for the course
and we'll bringing you, we'll be bringing
you back to this slide over and over
again at the beginning of each section.
to give you an orientation of where we
are as we progress through the course.
Before we start the first section, I'd
like to talk about three little themes
that are part of this course.
The first one is, representation.
We'll be coming back to these themes over
and over again.
Representation is the issue of how do we
represent things in zeros and ones.
And by things or everything, we mean
numbers, characters, instructions
pointers namely the addresses of that
data in memory.
And we'll be talking about how we do an
efficient job of representing all of
these different types of data items.
the second little theme is, translation.
namely, how do we go from language to
language.
You've heard me talk about a few already.
I've mentioned Java as a high level
language C, as a lower level language X86
assembly language as something being
closer to the machine code of the CPU.
Well, to do those translations, as with
any language, we need to do word by word
translations.
We need to do, translation of phrase
structures, and eventually the larger
grammar of the language itself.
So, we're hoping that you know a language
maybe like Java, as a programming
language.
You've seen that in an intro programming
class, or maybe you've had C already.
so we'll be talking about those
languages, and encountering a few of the
things in between, like Java byte-codes
as well.
That'll come near the end of the course.
lastly, the, the third theme is control
flow, namely how do computers orchestrate
the many things they're doing and make it
look like they're doing them all in
parallel.
When in fact, of course, they're only
executing one instruction at a time?
So, how do we keep track of where we are,
when we call a method and then another
and another and so on?
what do we do when we hit a return
statement?
And how do we give the, the user the
ability to run multiple programs
seemingly at the same time?
So, these are the little themes we'll be
coming back to again and again throughout
the course.