[MUSIC] This video is to help you set up
a Virtual Machine environment on your own
computer.
so that we can have a common environment
for every student in the class to use.
If you go to our course webpage on the
Coursera website you'll find a.
In our nav-, left navigation bar the,
the, the heading Virtual Machine
Installation.
Click on that and you'll get a detailed
set of instructions on how to install a
Virtual Machine.
That will give us all a common
programming environment in which to do
the assignments in the course.
The important things to do first are to
download a Virtual Machine player.
Now, we're going to be doing this for the
Windows environment so we're going to be
loading a free VMware player.
for those of you running Macs or Linux,
you might want to try out Virtual Box to
do that.
We won't be supporting anything other
than the Windows environment.
But you can find a similar set of
instructions will work on, for Virtual
Box as well.
So if we click on the VM Player, we'll go
to the VM Ware website, where you'll find
a Download button.
to click on and see a whole set of
possible VMware players to use.
We're going to choose the Windows 32-bit
and 64-bit player.
And click on that Download.
That will let us save an exe file on our
machine.
[SOUND] After the file is done
downloading, you'll see this icon on your
desktop.
Just double-click on that and run the
installer for the VMware.
Once that's completed, you'll find the
following icon on your desktop for the VM
player.
But before we do anything else, let's go
back to our instructions.
And, and look at the next thing we need
to do.
As we go further down, you'll see
download instructions for the actual
Virtual Machine image we'll be using.
That is available here under the Linux VM
installation and Setup.
We'll be using a Linux Virtual Machine.
This is a very large file.
It's about 1.3 gigabytes, so we recommend
that you allocate enough time to get this
downloaded.
the file is also compressed, so you'll
need the compression utility called 7zip.
So if you don't have that on your
machine, you'll find a link here to go
find 7zip and install it.
again, I'm going to install the 64 bit
Windows version and put that on my
machine as well.
[NOISE].
For those of you who are not on Windows,
further down on this page you'll find
instructions for Mac OS and Linux
versions of 7zip.
Okay, the next thing then we'll need is
the actual Virtual Machine file itself.
you can download that here by fetching
the Virtual Machine image directly from
the Coursera server.
Or you can set up a bit torrent to help
you download the file.
We'll leave that to you to figure out.
All the instructions are here.
I am just going to download the Virtual
Machine image directly.
And you'll notice it's a file called
VM.7z.
And place that on my desktop as well.
So, after the file has downloaded, and
that could take a while, you'll find two
more icons on your desktop.
One is the Virtual Machine.
File itself zipped, and the other is the
7zip installer.
So let's get the 7zip utility installed
first.
just do the basic recommended
installation.
That shouldn't take very long.
And then we can, right-click on the
Virtual Machine file.
And ask, 7zip to extract it here.
So what it will now do is extract the
file into a folder, in this directory.
Okay, when that's completed, you'll have
a folder called VM.
And if you double-click on that, you'll
see a set of files in that.
let's not worry about that just quite
yet.
we'll we'll be using the VMware player to
play one of those files.
And set up our environment for us.
So if we click on VMWare, we can open a
Virtual Machine.
And what we'll do is naivgate to that
file.
And you'll notice, there's only one file
that we can actually open.
called Fedora 64-bit.
We'll open that.
And then click Play our Virtual Machine.
Just click I copied it to get things
started.
And just remind me later or okay to the
various things that will ask.
And you'll now see it install.
The actual Virtaul Machine that we'll be
using.
OK, once that decompression is completed
we'll have a VM folder.
That contains our Virtual Machine image.
We're going to execute, that Virtual
Machine by using the VM Ware player.
So double-click on the VM Ware icon.
And open a new Virtual Machine.
On that folder, navigating to it if
necessary.
And then selecting that, Virtual Machine,
and playing it.
Just click I copied if that pops up.
And remind me later if, necessary.
And you'll see it go through a sequence
of installation.
Operations for that Virtual Machine.
This may take a few seconds.
Okay, when it's completed the
installation, we'll see a window on,
through our Virtual Machine, and a log in
for our default users, happy user.
If we click on that, we'll see that it
brings up a screen with a few icons on on
the top of the screen.
And a few icons in the menu bar up at the
top.
One of the first things you'll want to do
is click on the Eexclamation point,
either here or here.
And this is a little script that we've
included that updates all the course
materials.
So, what I've just done is updated the
course materials so that I can get
started on the first homework assignment,
the first laboratory assignment, Lab
zero.
Okay.
The next thing I'll want to do is open up
a terminal window using the icon here in
the Applications menu, and type Setup-VM.
That will now let me set a new password
for my Virtual machine.
oops, thats a mistype.
And then a new password for my user.
Okay so now setup is complete and I can
get started using my Virtual Machine.
There are a few more things left to do at
this point and we're going to go back to
our instructions.
And you'll notice that as we've just
completed part A.
And I've shown you how to do that the
next thing to do is to set up part B.
And I'll leave that up to you to follow
these instructions carefully.
you'll notice there's a bunch of commands
you'll have to give to the prompt in the
Terminal window.
And this will finally set up everything
so that it's ready for us to use.
the next video will look at how we get
started on Lab zero.