Okay in this video we're going to look at
how we go about submitting our first
programming assignment, lab zero.
In the previous video we showed you how
to install the virtual machine you'll be
using, so lets go back to that VM player
icon and double click on that.
to get our VM started up again.
And this time you'll see that it'll be
listed in the set of VMs available.
And we can just double-click that and get
it to start playing.
And again, just dismiss those windows
that pop up.
And it'll go through the installation
process again.
Since we started it from scratch again.
And we'll get to our
When this is completed we'll get to our
log in screen.
for our happy user.
I will.
Click on the happy user, type in my
password, that I set up previously and
we'll get started in our virtual machine.
So, to get started on this first
programming assignment, we're going to go
to the course materials folder.
Since we already updated the virtual
machine, previously.
We will see that labs, there's a lab zero
folder already set up now.
Every time you do update course, we will
download a few more files that'll help
you with the next homework assignment.
So, let's open up lab zero and we'll see
that there's a C file called Arrays.C.
We can edit that file using the Emacs
editor, although you can set up to use
any editor you like.
There's many available here under the
Applications menu or the Accessories
menu.
So, I'm just going to up to our menu bar
and click Emacs.
Once Emacs comes up.
I can go and open an existing file.
And navigate to course materials.
Lab zero Arrays.C.
And here we'll see the contents of that
file inside of Emacs.
And I can.
Now edit this file following the
instructions for the homework assignment.
Once I'm done, once I'm done with all of
the things that I have to do for lab zero
and I've finished my edits to the
Arrays.C file.
I can save it from Emacs and then go to a
terminal window by just clicking on the
terminal icon.
And navigate to the lab zero directory.
I can do that Linux by using the
directory listing command, ls.
and then the change directory command.
In this case, I'm changing the directory
to course materials.
then listing its contents and changing
the directory again to lab zero, where we
see the Arrays.C file.
At this point I can type submit homework,
lab zero.
Submit homework-homework is a little
utility we've provided to help you with
the submission process.
And it asks me for my email address that
I will need for my submission, if I can
spell it correctly.
And then, for my submission password.
The submission password is not your
Coursera password, but a single use
password that's generated on the website.
for your particular username.
So, if I go to programming assignments,
at the very top here I will see my
submission log in, my email address I'm
using, and a submission password.
I can generate new passwords by just
clicking on this.
And then I have to make sure to use the
most current one.
so I'm going to use this one right now
and go type that into the my virtual
machine.
I can take that password and type it in
here.
You will not see it being echoed to the
screen so be careful in typing it in and
making sure that you have all the .
.
capital letters and lower case letters,
correct?
And then you can confirm that is in fact
the file that you want to upload and, you
can officially get credit for, this lab.
We allow you to do up to three
submissions and then we'll take the
maximum score across the three.
And that will be the general policy for
all the homework assignments in the
course.
And you'll, be following essentially the
same procedure for each one.