[MUSIC]
.
Welcome back, it's time for the fifth
section of the course Procedures and
Stacks.
What we're going to talk about here is
another aspect of Assembly Language.
Namely how we define procedures or
methods in Assembly Language.
And how do we keep track of where we are
in the execution of a set of nested
procedure calls.
So, this this section will cover quite a
few topics.
We're going to start with talking about
the concept of a stack.
A special memory construct that we're
going to use to keep track of this
calling history through our programs.
then we're going to talk about return
addresses and return values, namely when
we return from a method or procedure.
where do we return to and how do we
remember that and what value do we
return?
how is that stored?
we'll then talk briefly about stack based
languages and the Linux stack frame.
A particular type of stack that we'll be
using throughout the rest of the course.
Then we'll get into some other aspects of
stacks.
Namely how we pass arguments to
procedures on the stack and allocate
local variables for a procedure.
and some of the conventions we have to
follow to make sure we keep all of this
stuff straight.
we'll also talk about the differences
between the 32 bit and 64 bit
architectures.
So, let's start, this video with, the
first topic which is basically what is a
stack in memory and what are some basic
stack operations.
Okay, so, if we look at memory, the way
we ordganise it for, our programs.
Is that we'll have an area where we will
keep all of our instructions all these
assembly language instructions you've
been learning about.
they will be usually stored in the area
starting at the low end of the memory
here shown at the bottom.
Then aboce that we'll, store some
literals in the program, by literals we
mean data that doesn't really ever
change.
Things like a string that I might want to
print, as an example.
we'll also do the same thing with static
data, variables that we know we're
going to need, maybe big arrays of
values.
that will know that we always will have
that storage available to them.
And allocate those in memory in a static
location meaning there'll always be in
the same place.
This is the case, for example, with
global variables in C.
that's where they're placed, then, we
have some more interesting areas of
memory.
We have a dynamic data area, also
referred to as the heap.
Often and the heap holds data that we
create just for a place to store some
values temporarily.
While we might be in the middle of a
procedure or in a phase of our program.
but we'll probably reclaim this memory
later, because we won't need it for very
long during the execution of our program.
these variables, this space is allocated
using things like New and Java or Mallock
in C basic memory allocation procedures
that we can call.
To get us a new space for the particular
data type we need.
And this region grows as we ask for more
and more dynamic data space and it grows
up in the memory to higher addresses.
The stack is yet another area of memory
where we're going to store this procedure
context as we do these procedure calls.
And it's going to start at the high end
of memory and grow down in the other
direction.
and we'll see in a second what's what's
going to be in that stack to you know,
what is, what do we mean by procedure
context.
For now the important thing to see, is
that in fact the stack grows down.
The dynamic data grows up, in addresses,
and the, these two could meet, and that
would be a really bad thing.
either that we're putting to much
requirements on our call stack, we're
going to deeply nested into procedures.
Or we're just asking for too much data at
one time.
And this is the kind of error we'll see
in our program sometimes when we, when
the operating system says its out of
memory.
Meaning that its overfilled this area and
those two regions, the stack and the
dynamic data are running into each other.
and potentially override it.
Okay, another thing to keep in mind about
these memory areas is that the
instructions, the literals.
And the static data are initialized when
the process starts up.
When the program starts up.
The dynamic data is managed by the
program, meaning we're writing in the
program when to allocate more memory,
when to create a new object.
while the stack is managed automatically
by the compiler.
It's there's instructions inserted by the
compiler to add things to the stack or
remove things from the stack, okay.
Another aspect of these areas is that
you'll notice that the instructions are
read-only and executable.
Meaning, we interpret the bits there as
the instructions for the CPU.
The literals are also read only because
they're fixed, we're not changing those
strings ever.
But they are not executable.
Okay?
We're not going to try to execute our our
data strings.
So, that's really important because that
keeps things from getting confused.
should we accidentally jump to this area
to try to execute instructions.
The static data is, of course, writable.
We have to be able to change it but it is
also not executable.
The dynamic data, the same way and the
stack the same way.
this, this are important limitations that
the stack is actually just data values.
And addresses that were used but that are
not instructions.
So, its not executable and we will see
this is an important aspect of security
in modern computer systems.
Okay, we'll see that in one of our
assignments.
Okay, so let's take a look at the call
stack for the IA32 architecture.
as I mentioned we'll put the bottom of
the stack at the top of the memory
And the bottom[LAUGH], of the stack or
the top of the stack at the bottom so the
stack rose in a downward direction.
And this is just a convention that we use
it of course is kind of counter
intuitive.
given that we're going to talk about the
top of the stack[LAUGH], being at the
bottom.
But bear with us for that, this is
typically how it's drawn upside down.
The important thing to remember is that
as we add things to the stack, the
addresses get lower.
And as we take things off the stack, the
addresses get higher, as we move up.
Okay.
There's a special register in the I30,
IA32 architecture called ESP for the
Extended Stack Pointer.
That always points to the top element of
the stack.
the last thing that was placed on the
stack.
Okay.
So, the first stack operation we're
going to look at is the push instruction
and here I'm showing a push long meaning
a 32-bit value.
And it's given a source register to or
memory location to push from.
And what basically that does is it takes
the value at that source, whether it's a
register or a memory location and adds it
to the top of the stack.
It also decrements the stack pointer by
four.
And why four?
Because it's a push long, remember?
Right?
Four byte's a 32-bit word.
So, the stack pointer is decremented, and
now points to the new location in memory,
where we've added a or copied that value.
into the memory, okay.
So, that's pushing something onto the
stack, placing it on the top of course
here at the bottom, as we've drawn it
upside down.
All right as you'd expect, there's a
corresponding pop instruction, taking
things off of the stack.
And in this case we also give it a
destination to go take that value we pop
from the stack.
and where to go put it?
We need the address of that.
And that again can be a memory location
or a register in the, in the CPU.
So, the way that works is we remove that
remove in quotes for now.
we remove that value from the top of the
stack and adjust the stack pointer for
up.
Again for four bytes of that 32-bit word.
Now, when we say remove this word, we're
not really removing it.
it's still there in the memory we're just
not referencing it anymore.
We've adjusted our stack pointer to point
to the next value down the stack.
but that, those bits if you will, are
still in the memory at that location.
It's just that we don't we, we
acknowledge that they're not to be
interpreted anymore.
We've effectively removed them in that
sense and that we can reclaim this space
and push something new onto the stack.
And overwrite those bits, because we
don't care about them anymore.
We've popped them off, and gone and saved
them away in our destination, okay?
So, they are now safely stored there and
we can use the stack for other things.