Okay, so we just saw how a stack can be
used to keep track of the return address
in a procedure call.
Let's take this a little bit further now
and look at stack-based languages in
general.
Alright, that's the next part of this
section.
So, stack-based languages are really
common.
that's in fact the majority of the
languages we use today.
they're languages that support recursion,
namely a procedure that calls itself.
so these are languages like C, Pascal, if
you remember the, from the old days, and
Java as well.
to make it possible to support recursion
in a programming language code must be
what we call re-entrant.
Meaning that we can have simultaneous
instantiation of a single procedure.
What does that mean?
That means that we've just called a
procedure and in the middle of executing
it.
And then that procedure can call itself
again and start executing a new copy of
itself.
And that one can call itself again and
execute a new copy of itself and so
forth.
So that's a, you can imagine is an
interesting problem to try to keep track
of all of that.
And in order to make that happen, what we
need to do is to make sure to have a
place to store the information for each
instantiation of that procedure.
And what information do we need to hold
on to?
Well that's called the procedures state.
And that includes the arguments we called
it with any local variables it has to
work on, and of course a return address
or return pointer.
to where it should go in the procedure
that called it, including potentially
itself.
and to do that we're going to extend this
stack discipline.
Okay.
So bascially the state for a given
procedure is all this stuff above the
three check marks there.
That are things I need for a limited
amount of time while that procedure is
executing.
And then when it returns I can remove
that state, I don't need it anymore.
so the callee fortunately always returns
before it's caller.
Because we're returning back to the
caller and then continuing the execution
where we left off in the caller
procedure.
So one last definition we're going to
call these allocations on the stack
frames, procedure frames, or stack frames
in general.
And for each procedure instantiation we
will have all the state in one of these
frames.
So let's take a look at an example of a
call chain, a string of procedure calls.
Alright so here we have some fun funny
functions the function yoo which calls
the function who.
Okay, and we can see in the that we
somehow started with the function the
procedure yoo and it then calls who,
okay?
Now the procedure who in its turn calls
amI twice.
and in between It probably does some
other things, okay?
So were going to call amI then return
back to this point and do some other
stuff and then call amI again.
so here we see the two calls to amI.
That happen one after the other in who.
But the function amI is a recursive
procedure that calls itself.
So heres the definition of amI and yoo
see that inside it calls itself again.
Alright you have already seen factorial
functions that do this for example.
So amI here you noticed in the first
call, called itself once and then that
copy of amI call itself again.
But then it stopped and returned and
returned and then may the second call to
amI here.
And then amI returned again back up to
who and then who returned up to U and
then U returned to wherever it was called
from okay.
So here we see that chain descending down
the tree of cause that we have here and
basically following that a path.
Okay.
So, let's see how this looks on the
stack.
Okay, so, let's take a, review that stack
frame concept again.
In the Linux IA32 architecture.
the contents of a stack frame includes
the local variables, arguments to the
function any information about return
addresses that it needs to go to.
And then maybe some temporary scratch
space.
This this function might need.
Maybe things like it's another version of
local variables if you will.
But maybe more temporary.
All right.
So here's the previous frame on the
stack.
Okay.
And when we call a function, we create a
new frame for it by adjusting the stack
pointer to create a space for all of
these things that are going to have to go
into that frame, okay.
What we're going to do is since we have a
pointer to the top of it in the stack
pointer We're also going to use another
special register called the base pointer.
you've seen this alread ebp, the Extended
Base Pointer register, to point to the
bottom of that stack frame.
Okay.
So the management then of these frames is
such that when a procedure is first
entered, we run it's setup code that
creates the stuff in this frame.
And when we return before we do that we
run some finish code, that sort of cleans
up what's in this frame before changing
the stack pointer.
to go back to the previous frame Alright?
So again lets take a look at how our
example is going to do this.
right?
So here remember it is our call chain,
that went through this.
Sequence of things calls going down,
returns coming back up.
So here we are in the middle of a
procedure yoo, and we're about to call
who, right.
So, here's our yoo, yoo stack frame on
the stack, there's a base pointer to the
bottom of it, stack pointer to the top of
it.
That helps us define that size of that
stack, the size of that frame, okay?
But now we've just called who, and we've
put a new frame on the stack, okay?
And of course, our base pointer got
adjusted and our stack pointer got
adjusted.
And you'll recall from some of the
previous examples you might've seen
assembly language examples.
You might've seen the old ebp saved away
first before we did this, so we can reuse
that registry, okay?
The next that's going to happen is we're
going to call is amI.Okay.
And here we go.
Another stack frame is put onto the
stack.
Again, we've had to save that, that
previous value of ebp that was there,
because we had to change that again, so,
we've had to find a place to put that.
we're going to go along and execute amI
now.
And it's going to call itself So we're
going to say another stack frame from amI
appear on the stack, again with updated
pointers.
And, yet a thrid one as it calls itself
yet again.
Okay.
So now we're at the bottom here of our
call chain and we're about to execute our
first return in the thridy copy of amI.
So when we do that we remove its stack
frame, put the ebp and esp back to where
they were for the previous instantiation
of amI.
Okay.
And we're now going to return from that
one and remove that from the stack by
adjusting the, the pointers again.
So we have a new value for ebp, a new
value for esp, okay?
And now our next thing is to return from
this instance of amI back to who.
And when we do that, we'll eliminate the
last of those frames for amI.
And we're now back at the frame for who
with its base pointer and stack pointer
at either end.
So we're now in the middle of the
procedure, who and where about to do our
second call to amI where so that another
copy of amI's stack frame on the stack.
We'll return from that, back to who, and
then done with who, so will return back
to yoo.
And just have that left on the stack.