[MUSIC].
We're now starting a new section.
We're going to be seeing how to manage
memory.
How, how to further allocate memory as
they run, so they can use it for their
data structures.
'Kay?
So this section is a little long.
It has quite a few parts to it.
Okay?
We're going to start with a, with a quick
intro right now and then we're going to
see how dynamic memory allocation works.
How and the reason we need dynamic memory
allocation, is because the size and
number of data structures may be only
known at run time, dynamically.
'Kay?
And then we're going to see how we
implement that, that dynamic memory
location in a number of ways.
We're going to look at something called
garbage collection which automates a lot
of the memory management process from the
programmer's point of view.
And then we're going to see how memory
related bugs really can make your life
hard and how, what are some of the common
memory related bugs you see.
that happening so you can avoid them in
your code.
Kay?
So what is Dynamic Memory Allocation?
The first thing to realize is that it's
often impossible for a program to know
how much memory it's going to need, until
it's actually running.
Let me give you an example.
Suppose that you write a piece of code
that takes whatever the user's typing on
the keyboards and stores it in memory.
Well, until the program runs, it doesn't
know how much the user's going to type.
So it doesn't know how much memory it's
going to need.
'Kay?
So and therefore, it's not going to
locate it on the stack.
So we're going to, we're going to
allocate this in a pa, in the region of
the, the memory layout of the program
called the heap.
'Kay?
So the heap is where dynamically
allocated memory goes.
It's a region of the heap that where when
programs allocate memory dynamically,
that's where it's allocated from.
'Kay?
So the programmers use dynamic memory
allocators such that it can acquire
memory at run time.
They can acquire pieces of it's address
base at run time to store data.
'Kay?
Again, this is for data structures that's
only known at run time.
For anything that's known statically, it
can allocate this in, in a different part
of memory.
We're talking about the heap is
everything that's allocated explicity.
'Kay?
And we going to be using something called
malloc as a dynamic memory allocated
which I'm sure you've seen.
So the dynamic memory allocators, they
manage this part of the other space, as I
said, called the heap, at this region
here of your address base.
That's where all of your regions of
memory are allocated with, with malloc
go.
So let me tell a little bit more about
the allocators.
Kay?
So as I said, the allocators maintain a,
a heap.
Right?
The heap is a collection of blocks.
'Kay?
They can be of different sizes, and these
blocks can either be free or allocated.
'Kay?
So, and these blocks reside in the heap,
and the heap region itself might have to
grow.
Because if the program uses a lot of
memory, the region's set aside, the
region of the other space set aside.
So the heap might not be large enough so
the process has to request to the
operating system more chunks of the
address, of the virtual address space, to
to have the heap there.
'Kay?
So C application objects are typically
smaller than pages.
The allocator manages blocks within
pages.
'Kay?
So but that's not a restriction,
applications could have objects much
bigger than pages, but typically they are
not.
So the allocator, so this is not done by
the operating system.
This allocator runs in user space and
manages the actual smaller blocks then,
that's that's, that forms the heap.
'Kay?
So there's two basic types of allocators,
called the Explicit allocator, where
applications both allocates blocks and
frees the block.
That's, that's what malloc and free does
in C.
That's explicit because the program
explicitly requests, and explicitly free
up them.
There's also something called Implicit
allocator.
So in thi, using this allocator the
application request memory, allocates
memory, but does not free, because that's
done automatically.
'Kay?
And this is what garbage collection is in
say, Java ML and Lisp.
So you are going to be looking at the
malloc package, this is part of the
standard C library, and here's what
malloc does.
Malloc receives a size of the parameter,
that's the size of the block that's going
to be allocated.
And it returns a pointer that doesn't
have a type, because we don't know what,
what kind of data is going to be there.?
'Kay?
So, if it's successful it, it returns a
pointer to the new memory block, that has
at least size bytes.
'Kay?
And if the size is equal 0, it returns
NULL.
'Kay?
Because then, why are you allocating if
the size is 0?
Right?
Now, so, and if the, if malloc cannot
find enough free memory to, to allocate
the requested block, it returns NULL and
sets an error number.
So you know why that happened.
And now, free doesn't return anything,
but it takes a parameter of pointer p,
that is a pointer to the beginning of a
block.
'Kay?
So and p must come from a previous call
to malloc or realloc, but a realloc just
resizes the, the size of a block.
'Kay?
And what free does, it returns this block
pointed by p, back to the available pool,
so it could be used in the future.
So let me give you an example.
by the way, the, the other functions are
also calloc that is a new another version
of malloc that sets the allocated block
to 0.
Realloc just resizes the block.
And sbrk is using internally by the
allocator to grow or shrink to size of
the heap, that's the system call.
'Kay?
So now I'm going to give you an example.
Suppose I have my function called foo
here it has two parameters int n and int
m, and what we are doing here, and there
is a pointer p here.
When we call malloc, what malloc's going
to do is going to get in, and multiplied
it by the size of int, its going to
allocate an array of int.
'Kay?
So this is an int, and its going to have
in elements.
So the size of this array is, n
multiplied by the size of int's, and
that's what we passed some malloc.
It's the number of bytes we want to
allocate.
And since we're going to be stored int's,
storing int's, we cast the pointer
returned by malloc, to a pointer to a, a
pointer to an integer, to an int star.
'Kay?
So if p is NULL, that means there was a
problem with malloc, and the process
exits.
All right?
Malloc may, may not have found enough
free memory.
But if it, if it doesn't, if it's not
new, that means that right here we have a
valid pointer starting p.
So now we can execute a loop that just
populates that this, this array here with
0, 1, and so on.
'Kay?
So, but now let's say that this wasn't
enough.
So we could do, we could call realloc.
Which retakes p, the original block, the
pointer original block as a parameter,
and takes a new size, and what it does is
it just resizes the block.
It returns a new pointer.
Okay?
Which might not be the same.
So, and now we can go and extend it.
We can write more elements so, so realloc
just extends the array here.
And then we can go and start using these
again.
And now we're going to print a new array,
and so on.
'Kay?
See you soon.