[MUSIC].
Okay.
Let's now start digging into how memory
locators work.
Okay.
Let's, let's start with the assumptions
made in this lecture.
Okay.
So first of all, memory is word
addressed.
Okay.
So each.
So each word, you know, each word can
hold a pointer.
And a block size, the allocator of free
block size is going to be a size that's
multiple of words, okay?
For example if, if here we have our heap.
So we'll have for example, have an
allocated block here that happens to be
four words, and have a free block here
that happens to be two words.
And so on.
'Kay, another free block here, and so on,
and this, this is a free block, and this
is an allocated block.
Okay.
So let me give an example, okay.
So that's the order we're going to make
these calls.
First, when we call malloc, this is our
heap, okay, this is our heap, and then
when malloc says, I want a block of size
4.
We're going to allocate four words, okay?
Now, now it could say allocate five, I'm
going to allocate another five words.
and now I can allocate six, I counted six
words.
Then now we're going to free p2 and note
that we're passing some parameter, a
pointer that was earlier returned by
malloc.
'Kay.
So that's, so when we do that, this block
is now free.
Now we have some holes in our heap.
And when I allocate 2, we have two
options, could go there or there.
We just chose to allocate it here, and so
on.
One important question is that when we
were implementing this allocator, what
information, what information does it
need to keep track of?
Well, it needs to keep track of where the
heap is, where it starts.
Right?
And the word ends so it is the size of
the heap.
And that's what keeps, it needs to keep
track of what are, what parts of the,
the, the heap are allocated.
Like this allocated, allocated and
allocated, and what part is free, 'kay.
And it also needs a data structure to, in
order to find blocks we need to allocate
it and you need to also be able to know
what, what parts of course know parts of
the heap are free.
So you are allocating it there and so on.
Let's look at what constraints the
allocators have.
So first from the application point of
view it can issue an arbitrary sequence
of mallocs in free requests.
Okay.
So and free requests must be made only to
a previous malloc block.
I've said this two or three times already
because it's actually really important.
And allocators, from the allocator point
of view, the first thing it's important
to know is that they really can't control
the number size of allocated block.
This is something that the application
does.
The application does the requests and the
allocator just serves those requests.
So it doesn't really know what the
application is going to need.
In the future.
'Kay.
And we want it to be able to respond
immediately to Malloc Requests.
'Kay?
So in other words, it cannot reorder or
buffer requests.
So a synchronous call.
When you call Malloc, when it returns, it
has to have done the job.
It can't just reorder them.
It has to prompty respond immediately.
Right, it have to be So otherwise it
creates a, a big problem.
Of course we only want to allocate blocks
from free memory.
If you allocate blocks from allocated
memory, it's going to be a big mess.
You're going to be over writing data from
the application.
That is not going to be a good thing, for
sure, contains bugs, and hard to find and
so on.
So blocks can't, cannot overlap.
So and also it has to align blocks.
And by alignment, it means that the
pointers at the beginning of the block
has to be a multiple of a certain number.
'Kay?
For example the GNU malloc library
allocates blocks in an eight byte
criminality.
Okay?
So this just is just satisfy a bunch of
alignment requirements.
And, of course, once an allocated block
has been allocated it can not move.
And so in other words compaction is not
allowed.
Why?
Well imagine the following, you call
malloc, you get a pointer.
And now you assume that the data is in
that pointer and then the allocator just
moves it around.
If you don't update the pointer then
you're going to be pointing to stale data
and that's going to be again a big mess.
Okay, so allocators have to follow a very
strict discipline.
And now from the performance point of
view there's two components, the first
one is throughput Okay?
Instead it means the following.
Given sequence of malloc and free
requests.
Their goal is to maximize throughput
okay?
So their goal is to maximize that.
And the other component by the way of
performance is peak memory utilization.
We want to use memory, we want have as
few holes as possible.
We want to use as much memory as
possible.
Okay.
So, and this goal is often conflicting
because if you want to maximize
throughput you want to do things very,
very fast.
Therefore you can't afford to do very
sophisticated, do a lot of work in
managing memory to increase big
utilization.
So in the throughput here is a number of
completed request per unit time.
For example, you want to do 5000 mallocs
in a 5000 free calls in 10 seconds,
that's throughput and what we are doing
here is it will be a total of 10, total
of 100 operations per second, because we
had 10000 operation than in 10 seconds
1000 operations per second.
The other performance goal of allocators
is peak memory utilization, okay.
Let me tell you what it is now.
So again we have our sequence of requests
from R0 to Rn minus 1 and the aggregate
payload Pk is the total useful memory
provided by the malloc.
Blocks.
Kay?
So, the, that's the payload P of a malloc
block is isn't the number of bytes
requested by the application.
Kay?
So, say the aggregate payload Pk is the
total by, the total number of bytes that
malloc provided but it's requested by the
application.
At request Rk OK and now we define the
heap size the current heap size is hk and
its monotonically nondecreasing, it only
grows as we need more heap space and this
is done by the system called sbrk as I
mentioned before and now, now that we
know we defined the current heap size and
the aggregate payload.
'Kay.
Which is the, the aggregate number of
useful bytes in a, in a sequence of
[UNKNOWN] and free requests.
What we want to do is if I'm peak memory
utilization as the maximum of the payload
up to request K.
Right, that's the peak memory utilization
at the moment when you call a certain
request here RK.
Okay?
And so the pigment memory utilization is
the fraction of the heap that was useful
in the past.
Okay, remember that the heap never
decreases so that's why we, we, we're
using max.
Okay, so the pigment memory utilization
is the maximum aggregate payloads divided
by the size of the heap.
Okay?
And the goal is to actually maximize this
number.
We want to make the heap as useful as
possible, do whatever allocated leap as
useful as possible.
Okay?
Why is this hard?
This is hard because something called
fragmentation all the wholes that appear
in our heap okay.
And by the way managing that has an
effect on throughput because it has
overheads.
It takes work by the memory allocator to,
to provide that.
So let's go towards fragmentation now.
There is two types of fragmentation from
internal fragmentation and external
fragmentation An internal fragmentation
is the fragmentation within a block, and
the reason we have that is that, this is
for example, here's our block, 'kay?
And the actual payload is just a part of
this block.
The payload, that's what, that's what
useful to the application, and it's
smaller than the block size.
'Kay?
So all of these parts here they are not
useful.
These are, they are the source of
internal fragmentation.
'Kay?
So, and this is caused by overhead of
maintaining, in space overhead in
maintaining the heap data structures.
Like you know, things like markers
whether the block is free or not,
pointers among the blocks, and so on.
Also the padding for alignment purposes,
we just had earlier that one of the
requirements of dynamic memory locators
that they need to provide aligned blocks.
Kay?
And also this internal fragmentation is
caused by, by explicit policy decisions.
Kay?
So, you could return a big block to
satisfy a small request.
Why would you do that?
Because of performance reasons, okay?
So and one interesting thing about
internal fragmentation is that depends
only on the pattern of previous requests
so it's easy to measure, okay?
So now what's external fragmentation.
Well it's external because it's external
to the block.
So that means that it's, it occurs when
there is enough aggrogate heap memory.
But no single free block that's large
enough.
So let me give you an example here.
So suppose that we had the sequence of
mallocs, here, and then we had the free,
so we have, you know, five free here and
two free.
And what if I all, if I allocate six, I'm
not going to do that.
So what happens, so actually I have is 5
free here and I have 2 free here, so I
have a total of 7 free.
But, none of them are large enough to
honor this, this request of 6, so what
will happen now.
Well, nothing we can so in, by the way
this is actually depend on the pattern of
future request.
Its actually difficult to measure.
Where the fir-, external fragmentation is
a problem or not.
See you soon.