[MUSIC].
Now that we know the basics of dynamic
memory allocation let's see how it is
implemented.
So the main implementation issues and
questions are.
First, how do we know how much memory to
free given just a pointer, right,
remember that free just takes a pointer
as a parameter.
So just based on the pointer we need to
know how much memory to, to free.
So how do we keep track of which blocks
in our heap are free, okay?
So how do we pick a block among the free
blocks to be allocated.
That's when many of them might be
suitable.
How do we pick the best one?
Okay.
Is it, it could be because we want to
reduce fragmentation, we want to be fast
enough and so on.
and also if you happen to pick a free
block that is bigger than what you need,
what do you do with the rest of the
block?
How to make that useful somehow.
And finally, how do we reinsert a block
when it's freed, okay?
We have to reinsert the block into the
heap.
Let's solve the first question first.
So we need to know how much to free.
So the standard method is just to keep
the length of a block.
In a word preceding the block, so we're
going to make, we're going to have a
header field.
So that's going to require some extra
words.
It's a little bit of overhead.
But it'll be worth it.
'Kay.
So, for example, here's our heap, and we
have this free block here.
When I call malloc, I decide to use this
block, 'kay?
And now what we're going to do, we're
going to use one of the words here.
To store the block size.
So now I know that, you know, there's a
word preceding the pointer where the data
is.
I know that the immediate word always
contains the block size.
So I know how much to free.
'Kay?
So when I call free, I just know, I'm
going to call free, free passing p zero.
Which is right here.
Right?
So, right here.
And I know that the previous words
contains a block size so I know what to
free.
Pretty simple.
'kay?
Now, the next question, keeping the track
of, keeping track of free blocks, a
little bit more complicated.
There's a bunch of options.
The first method is an implicit list
which is going to see now.
We are just going to chain together,
based on the, the, on the length or, or
the size of the block.
We can always determine order of the
blocks, and heap, and so on.
'Kay?
So now there's an explicit.
That's implicit because it traverses and
we look whether it's allocated or not.
The other method is explicit.
So we going to have a link list of all
blocks that are free.
'Kay?
And then, and then there's some other
more sophisticated ways that we can
segregate different free lists based on
the size.
Or we can sort the blocks based by size
just to make it faster and more efficient
to allocate blocks.
Okay?
Alright, so let's look at implicit free
lists now.
So, for each block, we need to know two
things, right?
What is it's size and whether it's
allocated or not.
We could store that into words but it's a
little wasteful right.
This allocator here, fundamentally you
only need one bit.
So using an entire word for it is so
wasteful.
So what we going to do?
Well we're going to use a standard trick
that does the following.
Since the blocks are aligned.
We know that the low-order bits of the
addresses are always zero, okay.
For example, if you have an eight byte
alignment, all our addresses are going to
look like this, you know the lower three
bits are all going to be zero.
So why not use this last bit here and
say, okay we're going to use that bit to,
to tell us whether the block is allocated
or not.
'Kay, so now, so here's the form of ten
allocated blocks.
We have the payload that's the useful
part and p is going to point to here.
"Kay, the p's a pointer to, to the block.
We know that in previous words, here the
previous word contains the size, and the
low order bit is going to tell us if it's
set to one the block is allocated.
If it's set to zero the block is free.
Okay?
And payload might be some padding because
we might have some padding here because
we wanted to honor alignment
requirements, okay?
So note that since we're going to use
this bit for, the lower bit for
allocation, we're not really reading the
size.
We need to mask out this bit.
And you know how to do that because you
know everything about fiddling with bits
by now.
Alright?
Okay, so let's see how this looks in a,
in an example.
It, so suppose that we have a sequence of
blocks in our heap we have two that, and
by the way, this work is size and
allocated.
So we have a block of two that is at size
two and it's not allocated.
Four and one that's allocated and so on,
okay.
So the blocks that are white are free.
The light gray is allocated and used.
And then dark gray is allocated, but
unused, okay.
Right, so, and we're going to use an
example, [UNKNOWN] byte alignment, okay,
so that means that, we may require the
initial word to be unused.
It does cause some internal fragmentation
but it might be worth it.
So, and we have one word here, zero size
zero, which doesn't make sense, should be
zero right, but allocated it's just going
to be a marker at the end of the list.
That, that, that's the end of our free,
of our free list.
Okay?
So, let's see how we find a free block.
The first way we're going to do this is
using something called the first fit.
Okay?
So, and the idea here is just to search
the list from the beginning.
We choose, we choose the first, flee,
free block.
Searching the list that fits.
Here's how the code works.
Okay?
So p starts the beginning of the heap.
So it's we have this loop that why we
have not reached the end of the heap and
the block is already allocated, it's
allocated it's not useful.
Alright?
In the size of the block is lower than
the length.
'Kay?
Is lower than the required size.
And so we do that, we just go to the next
block.
'Kay?
So now.
This, this can take time linear to the
total number of blocks allocated than
free and allocated if like all blocks in
the implicit free list and in practice
this cause splinters at the beginning of
list because we going to have large
blocks you going to find the first one.
So that means that we going to start,
we're not going to use that very
efficiently, okay.
So now the next fit is just like first
fit, but you start from where you stopped
during the last, when, when you stopped
when you did the last malloc.
Okay?
So it should often be faster than first
fit because it avoids rescanning blocks
that are unhelpful.
And then what some, s-, some research
suggests that fragmentation is worse.
'Kay?
Now, there's something else called the
best fit, which you search an entire
list, and you find the best free block,
which is the one with the fewest bytes
left over.
'Kay?
By the way, so, a splinters, in case it
wasn't clear when I said, is when you
have, you tend to find blocks that are
too big for what you need.
So there's a little bit more waste.
Okay.
So best fit, we don't have that problem
because we always going to find the one
that's the best one among the free blocks
that you have.
The one that's, the smaller one that's
sufficient to honor your request.
'Kay?
So this, of course, keeps fragmentation
small, and it helps, so, it usually helps
fragmentation.
Okay?
And typically runs slower because you're
going to have to look at entire lists as
opposed to stopping when you find the
first one, okay?
So let's look at something called
splitting now.
So what is splitting?
Well when you find a, a block that, that,
a free block that's bigger than what you
need instead of just leaving this there
you know, for example here if I allocate
of my block p here and I only need four.
Wh-what's going to happen with this here?
Well, when we allocate, we need only four
we can just split it and leave it there.
Okay, so that's, that's really what, what
we want to do.
Because we don't want to use this whole
six block size of six because then it's
going to be wasteful.
Okay?
And the way this works is as follows.
First, we get, for example, we, we're
calling this function addblock of size
four at pointer p.
Okay, p points right there, we add a
symbol.
We, we add the block of size four.
What going to happens is now we're going
to point to, we're going to create a free
block of size two, right?
6 minus 4.
And then we're going to okay.
So that's it.
Now, here's how we're going to implement
this function called addblock.
And we're going to implement we, we're
going to say new size equals len plus one
shifted by one left, by one is pretty
cool.
You know what this is doing?
Just rounding up to even.
And it's just round, it's rounding up to
even just because of our alignment
requirements, okay?
We're going to have an even number of
words because of our alignment
requirements.
Now we're going to keep the old size
here.
So we're going to mask out we're just
going to mask, mask out a little bit and
get the size.
And now the, the new size here, p has a
new size, and ord with one.
So mark that it's allocated, okay?
But now, the new size is smaller than the
old size.
What we're going to do is p plus the
newsize, which points to the next block,
is going to be oldsize minus newsize.
And we do not set the low bit here,
because the block is free.
Pretty cool, huh?
Okay, so well, now how do we free a
block?
Well, the the simplest way so just to
clean, is just to clear the allocated
flag.
Okay, so we can do this, this allocation
clear the bits by masking it out.
But this is, this is bad because it can
lead to false fragmentation, right?
So now for I have, I have a free block of
four here, free block of two here.
Why not just make it look like a block of
six, because if we don't later if I do
need the block of size six I am not
going to able to honor it because I am
going to think I don't have free enough
but this is not real fragmentation but it
looks like real fragmentation alright, so
that's a big oops.
What's the problem?
Now I want to allocate five, now I can't
honor it.
Okay.
So there is enough free space but the
allocator won't be able to fit it, just
because it got a little confused.
So naturally what we're going to do?
Well we're going to coalesce these three
blocks into a larger one, okay.
So now for example, if we have this, this
pointer.
Be here, to this block four.
When I free it what I want to do is to
make this logically gone and free it and
make the size of the ni, new free block
be six.
'Kay?
How we going to do that?
Well, we're going to clear out the
allocated bit, bit.
Find the next block.
Anything happens to be free.
We're just going to
Adjust the size.
That's all.
Pretty cool, right?
So it just adds to, we just add the sizes
if, if they are free.
And, again, since the allocated bit is
free you can just do this addition
without masking out the bits.
Okay.
But now
How do we coalesce with the previous
block?
Suppose that I wanted to free a block,
and I free the block but the previous one
is also free.
How do I point backwards?
I could just start from the beginning of
the, the heap and scan again but that's
slow and remember, we want to have high
throughput.
So that's why we're going to do, we're
going to do bidirectional, bidirectional
coalescing.
This was invented a long time ago.
And the idea is to use to is to replicate
the size here, the header at the bottom.
Okay, so we, we replicate the header at
the bottom so both the size in the
allocated bit and I can use that to
traverse it backward so we can just join
them pretty cool isn't it.
Okay, so here's a summary of implicit
free lis implicit free lists..
Implementation is very simple, okay.
The allocate cost is linear time on the
total number of heap blocks including
allocated and free, okay.
So the free cost is constant time, okay,
in the worst case even with coalescing,
because I'm going to know how to point
both forwards, and backwards, so we never
have just canned in heap.
And so the memory utilization that we get
is going to depend on the placement
policy, what is first fit, or best fit or
next fit, and so this is not used in
practice for malloc and free because of
this linear time allocation.
That's still not good we can do a lot
better.
You're going to see that.
But it is used in some special purpose
applications.
Okay.
So, but in keeping mind that the concepts
of splitting and boundary tags are
general to all allocators.
Okay.
So we, we're going to use this concept of
splitting, splitting free blocks.
Right.
So we don't.
You, you don't waste the part that was
still free in your block in case you use
a block that is larger than what you
need.
And we're going to use things like
boundary tag to make coalescing fast.
See you soon.