Okay, now that we know how implicit free
lists work, let's look at explicit free
lists.
So in implicit free lists the reason we
call it implicit was because we had the,
a list we could you know, traverse entire
heap and we, we knew implicitly.
In obeys in the bit that was a bit that
tells whether it's allocated or not,
whether the block is free or not.
So it was implicit because it had to
traverse it to figure it out.
Now with explicit free lists we're going
to link free blocks to get explicitly.
How do we do that?
Well, instead of just having the size and
a bit saying it's allocated or not, like
we had an implicit free list for each
block.
What we're going to do is, since in free
blocks, we do not have the payload and
the padding.
We're going to use pointers.
We're going to use, we're going to put
pointers there.
One that points to the next free block.
And one that points to the previous one.
'Kay?
So and by the way, we still going to need
boundary texts for coalescing.
'Kay?
We'll see, we'll see examples of that.
now, and logically it's a doubly-linked
list, as I said.
And we have pointed to it previous, we
going to point it to the next one.
So, logically, it feels like, you know,
organizing some order here.
But physically you know, when you look at
how it's in memory, it could be really in
any order, okay?
So you have one and then the other and so
on.
So let's see how allocating from, from
explicit lists look like, okay?
So, for instance, here we have, this is
before the allocation and we have a
pointer to the next block.
And these are all free blocks, okay?
These are all free blocks.
And this is pointing in one direction,
and pointing in the other direction.
And when we allocate.
Say that we finally choose this one.
So we choose this one.
So, now, that's what we going to return
to malloc.
And this part's allocated, and whatever
is free is going to be split and now we
going to insert this block back into
this.
We going to update the pointers here so
we include this one here in the, in the
explicit free lists.
'Kay, that's how we allocate it.
It's pretty simple right?
Well freeing is a little bit more
complicated because now there's an
insertion policy, right?
Remember that the blocks should actually
be mainly actual order in this list,
alright?
So thinking, where are we going to put
the block once we free something?
Is very, very important, 'kay?
So so to summarize, the insertion
policy's where in the free list you put a
newly freed block.
And there's two basic policies.
The first one is called LIFO,
last-in-first-out.
Policy.
So did we insert a free block at the
beginning of the free list always, okay?
The pro is that it's pretty simple is
constant time because you always have a
pointer at the beginning of the list.
But the con is that studies suggest that
fragmentation is worse than just ordering
by address which is the other policy.
Address order, what it does is just links
them in a way such that addresses of the
previous block, is lower than the others,
the current one and slower than the next
one and so on, so it's just address
order.
The con is that requires linear time
search when blocks are free because it
has to find the way the timing goes, but,
studies suggest that fragmentation is
lower.
And that's an interesting question.
And by the way, memory location in
general is just full of heuristics.
Okay?
It's just very hard to make sure that,
very hard to make a provably best
allocator.
It's nearly impossible, potentially even
impossible.
So, this is just full of of heuristics.
Okay, so let's see how the LIFO policy
works.
Okay?
So we have the first case here.
So the first case is we have a free
block, and there's nothing.
It's a, a, we free a block in the middle
of something allocated, and what we're
going to do is we're just going to free
it and up.
And since we're doing LIFO, last in first
out, it's going to be.
There's, there's going to be sort of the
beginning of the list.
So now the root points to this new free
block.
And then we update the pointers
accordingly.
The, the old one, now, the old first one,
just points backs to the one that was
just inserted.
Pretty simple, right?
Okay.
So let's see the other case.
The other case here is that we are
freeing something, and right before it we
have, right before it we have a block
that's free.
So what are we going to do?
Well, we're going to merge it, okay?
And but now note that the resulting
block, the resulting block here is the
one that gets inserted in the beginning
of the list.
So now the root points here, okay?
Because we just got this old block here
and extended it with the one that we just
freed.
Simple, right?
Great.
Let's see one more case here.
Now suppose that what we could, what we
do, we're going to free a block and right
next to it, after it, we have a free
block.
We're going to the same what we did, as,
as we did before.
We're going to merge into a larger block.
Okay?
We're going to merge this whole thing
into a larger free block.
And then we're going to update the links
accordingly, such accordingly, such that
the root now points to this newly formed
larger block.
We removed the older block here because
it really, it's just part of a larger one
now.
And we're going to update the pointers
accordingly.
Okay?
Good.
So like the, the fourth and last case
here is when you say that you free a
block, and then there's ac-, there's two
blocks that, on either side, and on both
sides of it, that are now can be
coalesced into one large block.
So we're going to, we're going to remove
the old ones from the list.
We're going to create a new large block
and we're going to search this large
block at the beginning of the list so the
root points there now.
Pretty cool right?
Okay, so now we created a big block.
Hopefully this happens a lot so we can
have more lots of large blocks.
So to, to summarize, comparing explicit
free list to implicit free list, the
allocate is linear in the number of free
blocks, instead of all blocks like what
we had in implicit, in implicit free
list, and this is much faster, when most
of the memory is full.
Well, why is that?
Because when most of the memory is full
in the implicit case, we're going to have
to traverse in time memory.
Okay?
So we have, we might have to traverse not
the entire memory, but most of memory
until we find one.
It's likely that we're going to do that.
With explicit free lists you know, it's
just, we just know it, okay?
It's slightly more complicated to
allocate in free because it needs to
splice blocks in and out of their lists,
okay?
We also need some extra space for the
links, so two extra words needed for each
block.
So that means that the minimal free block
size has to be, mine has to be a little
bit larger so it leads to more internal
fragmentation.
Such is life but I think it's worth it.
And so in most common use of explicit
list is with what we call segregated free
lists.
With the idea is to keep multiple link
lists of different sizes.
Of free blocks and even possible for
different types of objects, okay.
That's what we are going to see now,
that's a method three.
Okay, so the concept is very very simple,
we are going to have bunch of size
classes and for each size class we are
going to have eight free explicit free
lists.
So here's for size one and two, you have
one, for size three I have another one
and so on.
'Kay?
And often we have separate classes for
each small size.
'Kay?
And then we have one, you see this, you
know, this, those are the small ones.
And then we have nine in the, in the big,
big one.
'Kay?
So, and for larger size we have one for
each two power size, a power is two size.
So how, how does that work in a little
bit more detail here's how we going to
allocate it.
OK, so given this array of free lists and
each one of some class sizes if you
allocate a block of size n, what you are
going to do first is, you are going to
find a lesser size m that's larger than
the size n that you want, if, if it finds
a block that's appropriate we just
allocate it.
If no block is found, we just try the
next larger class, and we repeat until a
block is found.
And of course if no block is found, you
have to go and increase the size of the
heap using this a system called sbrk that
I had mentioned before as well, 'kay?
So and then when we do that we're going
to allocate a block of n sizes.
of size n from this new memory, and place
the remainders as a single free block in
the largest class.
'Kay.
We want to keep things in large blocks
and then start splitting them.
'Kay?
Great.
So when you free a block, you want to
free the block, look at the resulting
freed block, coalesce it as much as you
can, and then reinsert the block into the
appropriate list.
Okay?
So that's pretty cool right?
So now we might have, and when we free
it, we might actually change the category
and have to insert it in a different in a
different list.
So the advantage of seglist segregators,
segregator list allocators is higher
throughput.
And we have log time for power of two
size classes, right?
There'd be logarithmic time to, to, to
find an appropriate one, and also it has
a better memory utilization because the
first fit search on this allocated on the
segregated free list really approximates
the best fits that we had, that of the
entire heap.
Okay, really it's an approx, not exactly
but some an approximate.
Okay.
So in an extreme case, if you give each
block its own size class, you know, in
the array of lists.
That's going to be equivalent to best
fit.
Okay.
All right.
So to summarize the summary of the key
allocator properties
allocator policies are the placement
policy.
We have first fit, next fit, and best
fit.
Okay.
[INAUDIBLE].
So and this trades off throughput for
last, for fragmentation, okay.
So the observation I just told you is
that segregated free lists approximate a
best fit placement without having to
search the entire free list.
And so we have a splitting policy, when
do we go ahead and split free blocks?
Okay, so that depends on how much
internal fragmentation are we willing to
tolerate.
Okay?
So you might to and so there's also
coalescing policy.
You could do coalescing as soon as you do
free, okay?
When you call free, just do it right
away.
So that might have some throughput
implications because you do more work at
free.
Or it can just delay it as long as you
can.
So you don't pay the throughput but then
you might be paying more for
fragmentation okay.
See you soon.