[MUSIC].
All right, so let's see our last topic in
the Memory Allocation section now.
Which is going to be about memory bugs in
C, memory related bugs in C, and how to
deal with them.
And how complicated and nasty they can
be.
Okay.
there are many, many problems in
manipulating memory and pointers in C
okay.
You could dereference a bad pointer, you
could read memory that was uninitialized,
you could override memory without
noticing.
You could reference non-existent
variables, you could free a block
multiple times.
you could reference free blocks, so you
get garbage that was in memory, whatever,
whatever was there.
Or it might fail to free your blocks and
exhaust your memory and so on.
Okay.
So let's talk about dereferencing bad
pointer.
Okay.
So here's what's happening here.
We declare a variable val, and we call
scanf, which just reads something from
intput and stores it in val.
Okay, and but what we're supposed to have
done here is to have.
Past the address of val just kind of as
opposed to val.
But the problem here is that in the best
case, in the but it's going to have us to
know, it's going to interpret that as a
value and it's going to consider that a
pointer.
So in the best case, your program is just
going to terminate immediately and
because of a seg fault, it's going to
cause a seg fault.
But in the worst case, the contents of
val actually corresponds.
To some valid read write area of memory
that you're going to do it in.
And later in the actual program, you're
going to have some problems, not good,
evil, hard to find, complicated.
So be careful that when, when you pass a
value as a parameter, make sure it
actually, and it happens it's going to be
interpreted as a pointer.
Make sure it's actually passing as a
pointer as opposed to some other random
value.
Okay.
The other problem that happens often is
just reading uninitialized memory.
'Kay?
So, here.
Suppose that I have this vector y here.
Like it allocates space for it.
Has you know n, n ints.
'Kay, as.
Enough space for n ints.
But I don't I don't initialize it.
And here, when I'm doing y of i, plus
equals, and whatever the, the rest of
expression.
I'm implicitly reading y, because it
going to be y equals y plus the rest of
the expression.
So when I read y, whatever was there
before, for the first time I read it,
it's just going to be, whatever was
there.
Some garbage.
So it's going to affect the computation
and leads, for surely, to bad results.
'Kay.
So do not assume that the, the free
blocks in the heap when you allocate it
they're going to be initialized to zero.
Unless you use a function that calls it.
Like c alloc for, c alloc for example
initializes to zero.
'Kay, but normally people don't do it
because it's it's it's expensive.
Okay.
So the other one, it might be overriding
memory because there's many ways of
overriding memory.
And one of them, we're going to tell you
a bunch of those now.
But the first one is, you allocate a
possibly wrong size object.
For example here, i of p, which is
supposed to be point of pointer, a vector
of pointers, okay?
N elements, N pointers.
to the size of int, okay?
So, but later here, I'm going to assign
to p of i, another pointer, but look at
what I allocated here?
Hmm, It's an int as opposed to an int
star.
Bad, right?
So why this potentially overwrite memory?
Well, first of all, whenever I'm doing
this, this if this is a 64-bit machine.
This is going to so int star is 64 bits.
Okay, so this is a 64-bit assignment
okay.
Not good, it's going to overwrite memory,
you can also, another one that's pretty
common is off by one error, okay.
Again, suppose I had the same example
there and now I actually have to write.
the right object size n star so that's
not a problem.
But the problem here is that in this loop
I'm going from 0 to n, so I'm assuming
that it's going to, so this loop's
going to actually traverse n plus one
elements.
But we only have n.
So the last write here, which is going to
be p of n, is overriding whatever is
after n in, after p in memory.
Okay?
So it's going to override stuff there.
For sure, not good.
'Kay?
Now, the other problem is not checking
the size of a string before you write it.
'Kay, so here's an example.
You have you de-, you declare a, a array
of 8 bytes in your stack.
'Kay?
And then you pass it as a parameter to
get s.
And then you go and read the string.
That goes on, that one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight nine.
'Kay?
And we have one extra byte here.
With the slice here.
This already ten bites, but I have only
had eight.
It's going to overwrite stuff in your
stack.
Can, can, it can potentially effect even
the return pointer in the stack.
And, in fact, this is the basis for
classic butter-overflow attack.
You pass something that's bigger than
what's expected end up overwriting things
on the stack.
And you're going to have, actually, we're
going to play with that in one of your
assignments, okay?
So you might also overwrite memory by
misunderstanding pointer arithmetic.
For example, if you have a function
called search.
Okay?
And you pass up the parameter pointer p,
pointer to it.
N, a value, val.
And this, this loop here, just up.
So this going to be, then we going to
have, an array of int's in memory.
And p points to the first element.
And then this loop, it's going to
traverse this int look at each one to see
that it matches val.
Okay,but, and the way that we're doing is
that every iteration of group we're going
to make p bump to the next one, the next
one and so on.
But what I'm doing here, I'm actually
adding size of int's.
But since we're already told the
comparator p is an int because that how
it is declared here, the comparator is
already doing implicit multiplication
with the size of the object.
So there's going to be size of int by
size of.
It's going to be bumping the pointer by
more than it should.
Okay?
And then when you return it, it's just
going to, first of all you're going to
reach stuff, grab from memory, and then
you going to go and return it.
Which could be used in a way, and over
written, and that's going to overwrite
memory.
Again, not good.
Here's another one.
when you reference a pointer you want to
make sure that you actually referencing
what you expect.
Okay?
So if you reference a pointer as opposed
to the object it points to that could be
a problem.
So here's an example.
When I call, when, when I execute sta
size minus, minus here, I am not
decrementing the value of size which is
clearly what intended in this code.
I'm decrementing the size of the pointer
first, okay?
So just pointing somewhere and then when
it passes the parameter, I am not
going to get what I expect.
Okay, we're going to be pointing whatever
comes before size in, in memory.
And that's because the operators minus,
minus and star have the same precedence
and therefore, we go from right to left.
Okay?
So, the decrement happens first.
That's not what it, what, what was
intended.
'Kay?
That's all so be careful when you use
those operators.
Now, the other problem is if you return a
pointer to something in your stack, okay.
So in this example, I have variable val
which is using foo's its going to be
allocated in the stack.
Okay?
And I going to return its pointer.
As soon as I return this pointer the
location of foo permit ends and the stack
frame is freed.
That means it might be there but later,
when you use it, that could be easily
overwritten when you do more function
calls.
So be careful with that too.
Never return a pointer to the stack,
unless it's some very, very special
circumstances.
But even then you, you should find other
ways of not doing that.
So another problem that could happen with
pointers just you free a block multiple
times.
Okay, dangerous.
So for example if I allocate a piece of
memory in n, it is example and store into
x and manipulate and then later I
manipulate I free x after being done with
it.
Then I allocate something at y, and then
it happens to call free x again but what
if this was allocated in the same
position and I freed.
Hmm, that might actually freeing y just
because it happens to be in the same
place, okay?
So in free, it won't return any elements
here because it could, could be there's
still a valid block in that case.
But it's not and you want to free that,
so be careful, okay?
So be careful when calling free and make
sure that you're not calling twice.
And in this case it's a problem because
you have reallocation that could haven't,
happen to be freer.
So just call free only ones for each
object.
Okay?
So the other problem is referencing free
blocks.
This is just evil.
Be careful.
Okay?
So again similar to what we have before,
we allocate a bunch of memory, put in the
x, manipulate it and then I free it.
And the later, I refer x again, data
might still be there but it could have
been, it might have been overwritten.
Because if I do a malloc here, I could
use memory just freed by this one.
Just like the previous one, okay?
And now, when I do x here, it might
affect, in fact be y here, you never
know.
So it could be something and so be, be
careful not to reference memory that you
have freed, okay?
So that can't happen.
So the other problem's what we call
memory leak.
When you allocate something, so you, you
allocate and you use it.
And then, so in this case, this pointer's
going to be dead.
Right?
Because I, the only pointer.
I don't return any pointers here, so.
And the pointer, to, what I just
allocated is, is on full stack, when full
returns.
That's, that's gone.
But I haven't freed it, so I no longer,
I'm no longer going to know the pointer
so I can't free it.
So that's a problem.
So, memory leaks are really a long long
term killer and is slow and silent.
Okay, be careful because it eventually
going to exhaust your heap without
noticing it.
now another problem that happens and that
might leads to failing to free blocks and
lead to memory leaks is the only free
part of a data structure.
Okay, for example, suppose that we have a
struct here called list, it has a
certain, its linked list, right it has a
value as a payload here and a pointer.
Okay, and then, when we create this list,
you know, create a head here, allocate
size of struct, okay?
And then I, I set a next here to, to
know, to not point into anything, just
actually, when I'm allocating here, I'm
allocating space for both the val and the
pointer.
Okay?
I going to create and manipulate the rest
of the list, but then it just free heads.
But for each element, I'm going to do a a
malloc.
But when I do free head, I'm just
going to free the first one.
So you have to be care, not the rest, so
you have to be careful to, if you have a
link list.
And you're going to allocate each element
of the link list in the separately.
When you freed, you free all of them.
You traverse and free all of them,
otherwise it going to have memory leak.
'Kay?
So there are many ways of dealing with
well I wish there were many ways.
There's just a handful of ways of dealing
with memory bugs.
It can use the debugger, gdb.
'Kay?
So it's good for finding bad pointer
references, but it's hard to detect other
memory bugs.
For example, memory leaks are hard to,
to, to detect to find with debuggers.
So, there's a special version of malloc.
For example the University of Toronto's
CSRI malloc.
it has special features, okay?
It's a wrap around the typical malloc and
it detects several memory bugs, okay?
So at the boundaries of mallocs and
frees, okay?
So it detects things like memory
overrides that, that corrupts heap
structures.
it detects some instances of freeing
blocks multiple times.
It detects memory leaks, you know, if you
free it and go, if you malloc and go free
it might alert you, and so on.
But it cannot detect all memory bugs.
Okay?
So it cannot detect overwrites into the
middle of allocated blocks, because it
doesn't monitor all of the reads and
writes to memory.
Okay.
It does it's hard to, to detect freeing
block twice.
It has been allocate, reallocated in the
interim because we saw one of these
problems on the earlier in this video.
And if you allocate it again something
that if you are going to free it again it
could be that what is reallocated.
Don't really know that, that didn't,
you're actually freeing twice so that's
actually very hard to find.
And also does not detect.
Referencing freed blocks because it can
only detect things at the boundaries of
malloc and free calls.
Now, it does instrument all of the
memory, all of the memory accesses, okay?
So there is, there is another one.
There is this tool called val, valgrind
that actually does binary
instrumentation.
Of your program actually moni-, monitors
much more of the execution.
So it's pretty powerful, okay?
It actually rewrites the text of code to,
to do special things.
And it, and it can check each, so and
since it examines your whole program, it
can check each individual reference at
run time.
Things like bad point over writing, and
referencing outside of allocated block
and so on.
And by the way, some malloc
implementations contain some check code.
Okay, so you can actually set.
See, if you use the Linux glib malloc
library, you can set an environment
variable that's going to check some some
of the calls to the memory allocater.
Okay, equivalent things are developing
for FreeBSD.
Well, this concludes our section on
memory allocation.
And I hope you learned what you should
avoid in writing C code with pointers.