[MUSIC].
Hello everybody.
My name's Jeremy, and I'm going to be
showing you how to get started on the
Malloc Lab.
number five for this class.
so I have my terminal, and my lab five
tar all ready, so I'm going to untar
that.
[NOISE] And it's going to, you know,
produce a bunch of files, and we'll get
into the lab five directory that I've
made.
And, so you see we have a bunch of files.
And the only ones that you need to really
worry about are mm.c and the README, in
case you're looking for information about
the lab itself.
So if you look at the README, it will
show you just some information about the
files and how to do stuff.
so you always want to look at your
README's, of course.
so let's look that in mm.c.
open that in emacs, because we're
going to be, updating it in the course of
this lab, and that'll open up.
So, we've got our source file, mm.c and
open in emacs here.
And so this is the starter code, your
going to have to go in and fill in some
function's, to make it actually do what
it's suppose to do.
so we're going to be implementing the
memory allocator malloc.
And the general overview of that is that,
you have, as we talked about, you have
heap in memory, and malloc is the program
that allocates and deallocates space on
the heap as the program requested.
So there's two methods in malloc that we
are going to be implementing.
Malloc, right here, and, whoops, mm_free,
right here.
yeah.
So, what malloc is going to do, is
allocate a block on the heap of a certain
size.
Whatever size the user specifies, and
then it's going to return the pointer to
that memory.
And then when the user's done with that,
they'll call free on that same pointer,
and malloc, and the malloc system will
put it back into the pool of free memory,
that can be allocated.
So, the two functions that you're going
to be implementing in this lab are malloc
and free.
And malloc is kind of the more simple
one.
we give you some code to start with, and
it's going to, basically just take, a
block of the size, and return a pointer
to it.
And that, that's not too hard.
for purposes of this lab.
The harder part, is for free, to take
the, pointer to the memory that the user
is done using, and put it back into the
pool of allocatable memory onto the heap.
And to keep track of all those different
flocks of memory, we're going to be using
a doubly linked list.
As you can see in the source files at the
top, there's a kind of a ascii picture of
that here, and it summarizes the
structure and the structure definition is
just below.
so we're going to have this doubly link
list.
So you have, like a link list, you have a
element and a point to the next thing.
But, with a doubly link list you just
have two pointer's.
One to the next thing, one to previous
thing.
So that makes it really easy to traverse
the list, back and forth when you're
looking for the thing of what, whatever
appropriate size.
And with that there's going to be mostly
in the free method, a lot of management
that you're going to have to do, to keep
the link list, the doubly link list of
the free blocks consistent and helpful.
Because you're going to have to smash
blocks together, if their right next to
each other, or split them if they're too
big so that's what free is going to do.
And, all this is going to have a lot to
do with manipulating pointers.
There's a lot of code in the source file
that is already provided.
So, you have functions for coalescing
free blocks, removing free blocks,
inserting free blocks into the list.
And searching the list for a block of a
certain size, and you're going to be
using all of those to implement malloc
and free.
So once you're done writing your malloc
implementation, and you want to test it
we provide the mdriver program the source
files in mdriver.c, that you can use to
test your malloc implementation.
And you're going to make that, with a
make and it's going to produce this
mdriver program.
To test your malloc implementation you
just run mdriver.
And, of course, my malloc implementation
doesn't exist, because I just untied it
just now.
So, of course, it fails every test.
the mdriver program also has some options
that you can use to generate more
detailed information, and you can find
that by using the H flag.
So that's a general overview of how
you're going to implement and test your
malloc.
pointers are kind of hard, so you may get
frustrated in this lab, but don't worry
about it.
It's, it's a challenging lab so good luck
and have fun.