[MUSIC].
Hello again.
Now we're going to see conditions in
control flow.
And if you recall control flow is the
order in which executions instructions of
your program execute in the processor.
And the way you change the flow of
controlloing your program in writing code
in a high level language is using control
statements like if.
While for loops, and do of for loops and
for for loops, and for loops as well,
these are all ways in which you can
control in which order how the, the
control flow goes in your program.
And a conditional branching instruction
which is a branch is an instruction that
just changes the control flow.
And if you make the control flow
conditional which makes it a conditional
branch, it turns out that that is suf-,
sufficient to implement most of the
control flow constructs offered in the
high, in high level languages like the
ones I just told you about.
and uncon, unconditional branches, which
is branches that just execute no matter
what, regardless of the condition, are
used to implement things like break and
continue.
Breaks just breaks out of a lopp and
continue goes back to the beginning of a
loop.
Those are unconditional, they happen
ayways.
Is, okay?
and so we, we use unconditional branches
for those.
And in x86, we refer to branches as jumps
because it jumps, you're executing, it
jumps to a different part of your
program.
Okay?
Either conditional or unconditional.
So here are the jump instructions
available in x86.
They're in the from of, they start with
the letter j for jump.
Huh, and x is a various ways of doing
jobs.
For example if you do just "jmp," this
means jump, that's an unconditional jump.
And it's also going to take as a
parameter, it's going to take as a
parameter a instruction address that it's
going to jump to.
'Kay.
So here's another one.
If you do "je" you mean jump if equal.
Or zero.
And that's going to be determined by this
special condition code register called
zf.
Okay, so let me pick out an example here.
if you use jl, it's going to be jump if
last then.
And so if you do a less than, if you do a
comparison and it turns out that it's
less than.
this, the jump's going to happen.
Okay, I'm going to, we're going to show
examples of that later.
And I encourage you to read in the book
all of about how all of these
instructions work.
let's look at the, the processes of state
again.
Remember that we have the registers that
we've been playing with already in our
exit, in our assembly programs.
These registers are special.
Again, there's the stack pointer and the
base pointer.
And the instruction pointer tells what
instructions are going to be executed
next.
And note that what do you think is going
to happen when you execute a branch
instruction?
You're actually going to change the value
of the instruction pointer because it
might change.
What instruction is going to be executed
next.
So branch instruction potentially changes
the value of the instruction point.
And finally the thing that is very
important to note here is that we have
this forest wall single bet which is the
condition codes that are set by some
instruction.
We're going to use that to implement
provisional branches.
That's why in this previous here slide I
just showed you, you can determine the
condition of whether or not the jump is
going to happen based on these condition
codes.
Let's see now how, how these condition
codes are set.
The first way we're going to see is
implicit setting.
This happens implicitly when you carry
out some Operations.
So these are the single bit condition
registers that we're going to be talking
about, and they are implicitly set when
you execute some instructions, for
example an addition.
So this instruction in an it, it, it
performs the arithmetic addition
operation, but in addition to that, it
also sets some condition codes depending
what happens to the results.
For example, in the case of adds, the CF
is set if, if there's a carry out from
the most significant bits, which is
essentially an unsigned overflow, an
unsigned overflow happening the addition.
Okay?
So the ZF condition is set if the result
happens to be equal to zero.
The s, the signal flag is set depending
on the result.
If the result is negative then sf is is
going to be set, means it's a negative
number.
Okay.
And now of happens if there is a two's
complement overflow.
If when you add the number will be bigger
than what fits in the register.
With what it, you're going to have this,
this bit set.
And also be careful of using the LEA
instruction.
That also computes some, some expression,
some arithmetic expressions.
you do not set these condition codes,
okay?
So be careful with that.
That's the implicit setting.
The other way, is to set the condition
explicitly.
Using compare instructions.
Okay.
So for example if you do comp l here.
Which compares a 4 byte number.
And you pass, you pass two all
parenthesis of parameters.
Source two and source one.
Okay so and what it does essentially.
It effectively computes A minus B but
without setting the destination.
It just computes this expression.
So that he can set.
The condition codes appropriately.
So, here the CF is going to be sad if the
carryout from the most significant bit is
sad.
Okay so it's used for unsigned
comparisons.
So, the Z f is set, the zero flag set so
that if A equals B, why is that?
Because if A minus B equals zero, it
means that a equals b.
So the set's going to be set.
It's going to be useful, this is useful
for an equality comparison.
Now, if a - b is negative, we're going to
to set a sign flag.
So you know that, then that this also
means that a is less than b.
And also the overflow is set, if there's
an a two's complement sign overflow.
Okay?
Great.
Let's see now how the, to set condition
codes with the test instruction.
Okay, so the test instruction also set to
the same set of also manipulates the same
set of Single bit condition code
registers.
And it takes two operands as parameters,
source two and source, and source one.
And essentially it works like computing a
bit-wise with b.
'Kay, a being source two and b being
source one.
Without setting the destination.
And that's, that's useful to do to have
operands to be a mask because tasks with
masks using the twice and is very, very
useful.
Okay.
So, in this case here tasks if the zf
flag is set if a b twice.
And with b, happens to be zero.
And it, SF is set, if a bitwise and with
b is less than zero.
So, if the most significant bit is set to
one, essentially.
So, now let's look at this example here.
We're doing, essentially, eax bitwise n
with eax.
So, this is interesting because, zf is
going to be set, only if eax is zero.
Oh is essentially just, just checking
whether eax is positive, negative, or
zero.
If it's zero, the zf bit's going to be
set.
If it's negative, the sf bit's going to
be set.
So that's going to be useful when you
have, conditions like f a less than zero.
'Kay, so this is going to be implemented
with a test instruction.
We can also read condition codes.
Okay, in this, set of instructions of,
called set in a bunch of options here.
And what they do is they read the
condition codes and put, and put the
resulting value at zero or one, the whole
by zero or one.
And in a general purpose register so you
can actually read and, and do computation
with the contents of the condition codes
register.
So essentially you get value of condition
code register and you store it into a
general purpose register.
And I encourage you to look at the book
For examples of those.
We're going to see one now, but it should
read how each of these instructions work.
So let's in example now of using the site
instrucions to read condition codes.
So, here we have, we have a function
called GT, that just takes X and Y as a
parameter, and then we want to return,
whether x is greater than y.
And here's the bud of the instruction.
Here, what we are doing is getting y and
storing it in eax.
And now we are comparing y with x,
because x is stored in 8 from ebp.
Okay?
And now we're doing set greater in al.
What is set greater doing?
Set greater is going to get in, we
passing a l here, which is the low order
bytes of the e a x register.
And what they're doing is the following.
here we are reading y and putting e a x,
comparing x and y.
Essentially comparing, doing a
subtraction and just setting the
condition codes.
Then al now is going to be set to to 1 if
x is greater than y, and it's going to be
set to 0 otherwise.
'Kay.
And this instruction here just zeroes,
this, this instruction just zeroes the,
this instruction here just zeroes the
rest of eax, it makes this whole here,
thing here zero.
Okay.
So, in the end, this is going to, hope,
this is going to be, al's going to be set
to 1, then if x squared is in y, it's
going to be set to 0 otherwise.