[MUSIC].
Hi there.
Now that we know how to set condition
codes, let's see how we use branch
instructions that depend on these
condition codes to modify the control
flow of your program.
Okay?
So, x86 supports several branch
instructions of type J for jump X.
And X can be a bunch of things here.
And the first one is an unconditional
branch, means that it jumps no matter
what.
There's no condition.
So the condition for the branch is always
true, is one.
So that's the JXP instruction.
But let's pick another one here for
example, if we have JE here.
JE only jumps to the destination
instruction address if the ZF condition
register is set to one.
Which is used, for example, when you do
an equality comparison.
Right, so if you do a compare a and b for
example.
the ZF condition code is going to be set
to one only if they're equal.
Because if you recall, the comparison
performs the difference.
The difference is zero, it happens that
the numbers are the same.
Then there's a bunch of other jumping
circumstances, they encourage you to take
a look and see how their conditions work.
Now we're going to jump into an example.
So, this piece of code here, absdiff,
does the following.
It receives x and y as a parameter.
And then returns the absolute difference
between them.
And the way we do that is by first
comparing if x is greater than y, and if
so the result is x minus y, because x is
greater.
So and otherwise it does y minus x in
case y is greater than or equal to x.
And this the asembly code in IA32 that
implements this piece of code.
And the first thing to note here is that
we're using two, branch instructions to
jump instructions.
The first one here, jle, says jump less
than or equal.
And, note that there's a new thing here.
There's a doc outside, but that's whats
called a label.
A label simply specifies a location in
your code, where the jumps going to jump
to if the condition evaluates the true.
So, if this, if the comparison does lead
to less than or equal result.
The control flow is going to, so the
program execution is going to go from
here to one of it's instructions.
It's going to go in, jump here, and then
this instruction is going to be executed.
And now there's an unconditional jump
here that just branches to dot L8, it's a
different label, to return from the
function.
Okay?
So, you might have a hard time actually
mapping this code directly to this
assembly implementation here.
Because there's some other thing is going
on here, let me show you what.
First, we when we are looking at this,
is, to put a bunch of goto's, let's
convert this program to use goto's to
make it easier to see the translation to
assembly.
And by the way, we do not I recommend
using goto's in your code.
You can use goto's in C but it's
generally considered bad coding style.
What we're doing here just to make it
clear how the translation happens.
First note that expression in the
comparison here changed from x greater
than y to x less than or equal y.
Because this is determining whether we
should jump to the Else position since
they invert.
Condition, okay?
And if so we execute the Else.
And if we're done with the Else, it comes
back to the exit, which is this part
here, okay?
So the exit here.
Now if this evaluates to false, we
actually executing the then part of your
of your if.
So that means that's called the The
fallback.
When you do not take a branch, it's
called the fallback.
In this case, you have the fallback as
the then position.
Okay?
So, a high level way to think about this,
that we converted this such that we jump
over the then part of your if condition,
'kay and execute the Else only if the
condition evaluates.
Great.
So let's look at this example step by
step.
Now note that we're at the c code that's
converted to goto's now.
these instructions here are just reading
x and y putting them in edx and eax
respectively.
And now that's when I'm performing the
comparison.
Now that x and y are in the eax and edx
registers we're comparing them.
Okay so we're comparing x and y.
That's in implementing this comparison
here.
And if this comparison happens to
evaluate that x is less than or equal.
Why?
Then we jump to L7, to implement the Else
block.
Now let's see how the Else block, okay.
So now if the jump does not happen, we're
executing the, this part of the code.
We're going to execute this search, and
this is how it's implemented here this
where we implement it.
So, the sub instruction here thus edx
equals edx minus eax.
So it's essentially doing X minus Y.
And then it gets the results and stores
it in eax.
And the reason we're storing to eax is
because that's where we put return values
for the function, that we can actually
return the results.
now the next step here is to implement
the Else part of[INAUDIBLE] .
And that's going to implement x minus y.
And we use another subinstruction here,
except that now see that the parameters
are inverted compared to the other one.
Now, what we're doing is, eax equals eax
minus edx.
And then from there we just jump To .L8,
that's going to be return.
And note that we did not have to, we did
not need to copy the result to eax since
that we can return it.
Because the results was, was already in
eax.
so, let's look at conditional expressions
in general and see how their, their
translation happens.
Well, in, C, you can write the following
conditional expression.
You can put a task here, which is any
condition.
For example x greater than y.
And then we, we put the then expression,
means that if this test, evaluates to
true, we're going to return, the then
expression.
Otherwise, we're going to return the Else
So one way to implement the code, we just
showed you, is to say, compare x, whether
x is greater than y.
And if so, we return x minus y.
Otherwise, we return y minus x.
So, and here's the goto version of that.
And so we are evaluating the the opposite
of this expression.
So, in this case it's just going to be
the complement of that expression.
In execute the Else in case it reverts to
true and then otherwise we're going to
execute the then.
So it does exactly what we just saw in
the previous slide.
So now you might be ask, you might be
asking, how can we make this more
efficient?
Just so we can implement this simple
conditional expression, we are inserting
a bunch of branches in our code, a bunch
of jumps.
And this is not very efficient, branches
tend to be expensive, especially modern,
deeply pipelined processors.
So x86 supports a special, x86-64
supports a special type of instruction
that solves that problem.
It's called a conditional move
instruction.
So what Conditional move does is it moves
a value from one branches from the source
to the destination.
Only if a certain condition is met.
And this condition the same ones that we
use for jumps.
So that means we can rewrite this code
here in a way that we perform the
comparison.
And depending on the result of the
comparison here we do a move.
So we say we do move less than or equal.
So essentially, we only move the value
from edx to eax, if the condition is
satisfied.
So we can implement exactly what we just
showed in the previous slide, without any
branches.
So we do the two subtractions here.
We subtract x y, from x, and y from and x
from y.
Store them in ede, eax or edx, and then
here we only move edx to eax if the
condition gets set.
And then we just return it, because we
should put the return value in eax.
Isn't that great?
So, now, this is a way of, executing
conditionals.
Implement some conditional box without
using, branch instructions.
So this can be, a big win in performance
in several cases.
So, one last thing I want to show before
ending this video is, how, addressing
actually happens.
Addressing of the destination instruction
in, in in branches.
'Kay.
And often the destination's specified in
what we call a PC relative way.
It means that the instruction specifies
an offset that should be jumped to
relative to the current instruction
address.
So in, in this example we have this "je"
instruction.
that jumps to, that, that's located in
address 0x102 and then jumps to 0x172.
But note that the destination here is
specified as 0x70.
Because this address here is computed as
0x102 + 0x70.
Which is this value here, let's call PC
relative.
And the reason that this is so important
is because now you can relocate this
block.
You can just change for example here we
change it to different address and now we
still have this compare because if we
change where the code is since everything
is relative you're not going to have to
recompute the targets.
in the branches in your codes.
But note that some branches have absolute
addresses.
In that case they're not relocatable.
See you next time.