[MUSIC] Hello again.
Now that we know how to implement
conditions in assembly, let's see how we
implement loops, which is going to
involve conditionals.
So here I show you a simple example of a
while loop that keeps executing the loop
body.
As long as the condition holds, and in
this case the condition is, while sum is
not equal to 0 it keeps executing, okay.
and when sum is no longer not equal to 0,
it, the, the loop is going to stop.
So, the important thing to note here in
our implementation of a loop in, in, in
assembly is first, there's a con,
unconditional jump here that jumps to the
beginning of the loop.
And second, there's another jump here
that determines when the loop is done.
When this, in other words, when this
condition no longer is satisfied.
So when that happens, we're going to jump
to the end of the loop, because the loop
is done.
So we're going to jump past the loop.
'Kay, and how the compiler transforms
implements, other loops should be
straightforward.
The only trick is where you put the
conditional branch.
At the top, you're going to put either at
the top of the loop, or at the bottom of
the loop.
For example, if you're to implement four,
i equals 0.
It's going to be looping to i let's see y
is greater than 100 or equal.
And you're going to keep implement
incrementing i.
So before the loop starts, we're going to
set i to zero.
We're going to have a condition that
checks while i is less than 100.
And in the body of the loop, we'll keep
incrementing i.
And then we'll jump out of the loop, as
long as this condition is no longer
satisfied.
So let's start with an example.
Start with a do-while example.
The way do, do-whiles work is you have
here's, here's an example: we say do, and
then the loop body and then we check our
condition.
So the loop, the, the first iteration of
the loop is always executed, no matter
what.
Because you know, we're going to execute
at least once before we evaluate the
condition.
If the condition is true we just going to
jump back to the beginning of the loop.
Now we can look this in the form of
Goto's right?
And it's pretty simple, we have a label
at the beginning of the loop.
We're going to execute the body of the
loop.
Evaluate the loop condition.
If it's true, we jump back to the
beginning of the loop.
And if it's no longer true, this, this
goto loop is not going to happen.
So that means we're going to jump, get
out of the loop.
Note that we have what we call backwards
branch, branching backwards to continue
the loop.
And only take this backward branch while
the condition holds.
So let's see how we compile this example.
Here we have our loop using the Go To
version, okay.
And here's our assembly version on the
right.
This is just setting eax to 1, and
loading x into edx.
and this is, this .L11 is just a label
for the beginning of the loop.
Here we're executing the multiplying
structure for this multiply here.
We are decrementing x with this
instruction.
And now, we are comparing, whether edx
how it compares to one.
Okay.
So, now if this compares and says edx is
greater than one, we're going to execute
the loop we're going to jump up to dot L
11, otherwise we're going to jump out of
the loop, okay?
That's pretty simple right?
So here's how to think about "Do-While"
translations in general here is the C
code, we go to the Goto Version, we going
to have a label the beginning.
And we're going to have a lift that
checks whether the tasks for the loop
holds and if it holds, we just back to
the beginning of the loop.
Pretty simple, right.
So let's see how whiles, while loops work
now.
There's, there's likely different.
Know that now we have while at the top,
this is no longer do while loop, it's a
while loop which means that even if for
the first iteration, we have to check
whether it needs to be executed.
Or not.
Okay?
So, what this is doing while x is greater
than one, we're going to execute the body
of the loop here.
And now, the biggest difference here is
this, that you might have noticed, is
this go to middle here.
What is middel doing?
Well, middle is the middle of the loop
and that's where the condition to jump
back to the beginning of the loop is
evaluated.
Okay?
So, we jump to the middle before
executing the first intsr, the first
iteration, precisely because we need to
evaluate it to see even the, to see
whether even a first iteration needs to
be executed.
And if so, it jumps to loop, and it keeps
going.
Okay.
So do we think about this, the first
situation jumps over the loop body
because we don't want to execute it
unless the expression holds.
The expression for the loop evaluates.
So let's look an example here.
So similarly to the do while, we have The
do while example.
We have multiplication that's
implementing this multiplication here.
The decrement here which is implementing
it's decrementing x.
now, here this is where the comparison
happens.
We're comparing edx with, with one.
And if it's greater than, we jump back to
the beginning of the loop.
The main difference here is that now we
have.
A jump to where the condition is, right
here, where, where the condition check
is.
Alright, so that's how we implement while
by just jumping over the, the body of the
loop compared to do while.
Now let's see how you implement of for
loop.
A for loop essentially has bounds in the
number of iterations of the loop.
And in this example here, we are doing we
are implementing a function that raise,
that takes x and p as parameters and
computes x raised to the p power.
It computes this value here, x Raised to
p.
Okay.
So there's a clever algorithm here that
exploits a bit representation of p.
That encourage you to stop and take a
look.
It's, it's really great.
and so it's pretty clever.
And so the way it works is it takes as
many steps as the number of bits in p.
The number, the numbers of bits, bits
necessary to represent P, okay?
And then for every bit of P that's set to
one, we're going to the multiplication
and keep doing it again.
And that's why it's called the Square and
Multiply.
I don't want to get into the details of
how exactly it works and why it works,
but encourage you to stop, take a look at
the slides and and think about it, okay?
Here's how we can think about our For
example I just showed you.
So here's the, the code that I have just
showed you.
And here is a general form of four loops.
And the general form looks as follows.
There's an init expression that's
executed in the beginning of the, before
the loop starts.
Kay?
So that's what we have here.
And the test expression is the expression
that determines whether the loop keeps
going or not.
And, so, in our example here, is whether
P is not equal to zero.
And then there's the update part, that
happens at the end of the loop.
So, in our example is P equals P shifted
right by one.
That's the update part of our, of our
report.
And the, obviously this is the body of.
And one way to make you understand how,
how for loops are translated is to
translate them to while loops.
Okay?
So, here's a general form that I just
showed you.
You can think about an, a while version
of that loop by executing the init
expression at the beginning of the loop.
We have a while loop that executes while
the tasks expression ports.
We execute the body of the loop, okay,
and then at the end, right after the body
you execute the update for what we call
the induction variable, and then when we
go from a while we can again do the goto
version that we had before.
Okay?
So, and note that the main difference
here is that now we have init, here, and
we have update.
That's the main difference between for,
and a while.
So, let's see how we apply this to the
example that I just showed you in the
previous slide.
So here's the general version of the loop
and the goto version, here's the code of
our example and note that the Init here
now appears in the beginning, even before
you evaluate the expression, whether the
loop keeps going or not.
So now we have to go to middle here, the
same thing we had in while.
That's where we're going to jump to
evaluate whether the condition holds,
okay?
And then if the condition holds, we jump
to the beginning of the loop, to execute
the body, which is what we have here.
Okay?
And now there's one extra step.
So, we have the init here, the, the,
sorry the update.
the update for the induction variable now
happens at the end of the body of the
loop right there.
So it looks, looks very similar to a y
loop.
See you next time.