[MUSIC].
Hello again.
Now that, that we know how to implement
conditionals and loops in assembly.
Let's see how we implement a little more
complex control structure.
we talk, we're going to talk about switch
statements.
And the way switch statements work in C
is as follows.
You have an example here.
If I say switch x, what I'm saying is now
there's going to be a bunch of options
that depending on the value of x, I'm
going to execute a different piece of
code.
Okay?
So here in our example if x happens to be
set to 1, we execute this piece of code
here.
And then this break statement just says
that this piece of code is going to be
executed.
And then we're going to stop and continue
executing past the end of the switch
statements.
There are some other cases called fall
through cases that do not have a break
statement.
For example, if x is happened to be set
to 2.
This piece of code is going to be
executed and is going to continue
executing through the next block, until
it see's the next break statement.
Then [INAUDIBLE] jumps it out of the
switch and continues executing.
Okay?
And now so if you have any missing values
in a set cases, for example if x happens
to be set to 4, since there's no value,
no case for 4 here.
What gets executed is the default value.
So the default block of codes.
So, the way to think about the default
set is there, if the value that you're
switching on is not in any of the case.
You have to view the default case.
And why could implement this with branch
instructions that we say earlier.
It gets really complicated quickly, so
another way of oftentimes and this is
using what we call a jump table.
And a jump table works as follows.
Say here we have our example we have an
example of a switch statement.
Now we going to have a table that has
roughly as many entries as the number of
cases in our, in our switch statement.
The number of cases now in the switch
statement.
It's, now in each one of these entries
the table points to the address of a code
block.
Which is course, corresponds to the code
block that has to be executed, based on
the case value.
So, for example, if our x happens to be
val 1.
we're going to jump, we're going to look
at the jump table, get the corresponding
address.
And select the tag1 and that's the code
that we're going to execute.
We're going to execute this piece of code
here.
now what we are going to think about this
is the following.
You could have a variable called target
which holds the target address for a
given option.
We're going to look up our jump table,
which is just an array of instruction
addresses.
We're going to index that array with x
and we're going to get the value storing
target and we're going to jump on it.
We're going to do a Go To and use that as
[UNKNOWN] Go To and to jump to that
address, go to that address.
So, these are the way of looking at this
more visually.
I have another switch statements in
fourteen other cases I have the
corresponding vision of memory.
Just in the color matching there and then
our jump table is going to map back to
the corresponding
To the corresponding memory region that
implements that block of code
corresponding to the, to the case
statement.
So, now 1 is green, so that means that
the [INAUDIBLE] 1 here has to point to
green.
That's this one.
And same, same thing for orange and so
on.
Okay?
Now notice an interesting case here,
which is the default case.
The default case, as I said before, gets
executed if none of the value if, if the
value of x doesn't happen to, happens to
be none of the values explicitly defined
by cases, okay?
So, here it happens to be 0, right?
We're going to jump to the default case,
and also happens to be four.
We're going to jump to the default case.
Okay?
And we can use a jump table as long as
the value is lower than six.
For any other value that's greater than
six, we go to execute the default code.
The default block.
for this jump table, just a list of
addresses.
And he's how we get setup.
in assembly, you would see a declaration
of long words that point, that happen to
be the same value as the label that maps
to the address of the code block.
So now this, for example, if we take
.L61, that's where the default code block
starts.
So, the corresponding structured address
is going to be stored here, and same
thing for the other case values.
So, let's see how we use this table in
assembly now.
so here we have the jump table.
And what we're going to do, is we're
going to, depending on the value of x,
which is loaded in edx here.
We're going to find the corresponding
entry.
And the way this is done, this is done
using a indirect jump.
The indirect jump says that, instead of
jumping to specific address, it jumps to
an address containing an address.
So, the way this works is this .L62 here,
is the base address of our, jump table.
Now the value of edx gets multiplied by
four and [UNKNOWN] because a long word is
four bites.
So, if the x is say four, we're going to
add zero, we're going to add four, one,
two, three, four.
And that's the value that's going to be,
jumped to.
'Kay?
So, another thing to note, here, is that
we are comparing whether x happens to be
greater than six.
And if it greater than six, it jumps
straight to default.
So, now lets see how the code blocks are
implemented.
So here, suppose that we have we're
interested in case two here.
And in case two happens to be mapped to
label .L57.
It means that this is where, the assembly
codes that implements the block for case
two is located.
So, we have a division here, so that's
why we must have a division instruction.
And note that this a fall through case,
so it's going to be in case x is 2, is
going to be executing.
And it's going to continue executing
through the next case block, until the
break statement.
And the break statement here is
implemented by essentially just finishing
the execution.
Returning from the function in which the
switch block is inserted.
And note here that the default case also,
after this there is a return.
So, if you look at here in label .L61
you're going to see here.
That after, right after being done with
the corresponding code block, we also
leave and return from the function.
So, here's the, the rest of the code
block for our example.
again you see, the important thing to
notice here is that, you have returns
after every single block that had breaks.
And for both case five and, and case six,
they're both mapped to case L60, which is
the label right here.
Now let's look at how these labels are
defined now.
If you look at the object code, they, you
see that they become an instruction
[INAUDIBLE] before as chosen by the
linker, okay?
And there'll be one of those for each one
of the the case values in our switch
statement.
So, if you go look at entire table you
see there will be one address for case
statement.
And those have two as we saw before put
points at a code block.
So now we can look at each one of those
you see mapped to a block of codes
corresponding to the code inserted in
the, in the case block for that value.
so here's our, our, our list of
instruction addresses for the jump table,
and each one of them points to a block of
code.
And notice that we have some repeated
ones.
Remember that some, some of the cases
has, for example, follow through or cases
that are not defined.
So, in this case here it's, it's the
default value.
For value four, if you remember it has to
go through the default case, so it points
there.
So the same thing for value zero.
Now let me ask you a question.
Would you implement this one with a jump
table?
Well, look at the size of this value
here.
Probably not.
This table would be very, very, very
large.
Okay?
So, jump jump tables are, are, are used
normally when you have few case values
and you can build a small table for it.
In this case here, it would be much more
efficient to just implement this with
branch instructions.
So, now we conclude our exodus six
assembly programming section.
And I'll see you next time.