[MUSIC].
Hi there, I'm just here to do a quick
tutorial on how to use the new debugger
inside our virtual machine.
I have a little terminal pulled up here,
and we can jump over into that terminal.
And quickly look at the files we have
accessible to us.
There's this handy little test.c program
that I'll use to do a quick demo of some
simple GDB features.
And then, we're going to jump into
looking at the first stage of lab two,
which may be useful to you when you start
working on that yourself.
So, here's our little test program, it
prints, hello world.
You may have seen something like this at
some time previously in your life.
we're going to compile it.
but we're going to add the special flag G
for adding Debug information.
I know Debug doesn't start with G but it
does end in G.
So, small, you know, favors.
so we can compile that and then we have
this a.out file.
Going to run that in GDB, the new
debugger.
And we're going to put a break point at
main, the method that we definitely have,
actually a function.
And we're going to say run the program
until that point.
Now it's going to stop here, and we can
say, let's see what the source code looks
like.
Say, List, shows us all our source code.
We can also look at the assembly code
that actually executes each of these
steps.
There's a number of ways that we can look
at this.
we can step through a single step of the
C code.
We've already printed hello world now,
and we're about to return 0.
Now what if you didn't have all that
handy debug information.
What if instead we compiled it maybe
accidentally without the debug
information, we left our source file at
home.
So, we can now look at this new a.out
compiled without debug info.
So again, break at main, run the file,
and what do we try and list?
Well, there's no single table listed.
We don't have the debug information, we
can't look at our source.
We can still look at our assembly, and
this is going to be true pretty much
regardless of what you do or don't put
into your file.
Which is a little detail that will come
in extremely handy in lab two.
We have also this mysterious executable
file called Bomb.
We don't know what's in it.
We can run the disassembler against, or
the debugger against it.
But if we try to list the source, we
don't have any of it.
So, this is a small difficulty for our
debugging, but we can I've learned from
my sources that we may have a method
called Phase One.
Somewhere in this bond and look there it
is.
We tried to break against a function that
didn't exist, it's not going to do it.
So, there definitely is a function called
Phase One.
If you also try to look at the current
assembly code being executed before you
start running the program, you're also
not going to have any luck.
Alright, so let's go look at this Phase
One program.
put together by a madman I see.
So, what is something that we can
recognize in assembly code?
Often programmers like to use words like
Foo and Bar to easily detect them later
when they turn up in their tests.
But they're not particularly obvious if
they're not represented as strings.
So, maybe we should use something that we
can definitely recognize like a whole
bunch of A's.
All the A's will be represented the same
way, and we can definitely see them
later.
Alright, so well put this input in, now
we've hit our break point.
Well again we can't list we don't have
any source, so what if we disassemble
instead.
Alright here's an assembly code that
looks pretty interesting to us pretty
familiar too.
GDB, by the way has a vast amount of help
you can get help on pretty much any topic
you are interested in.
And then once you've looked at the help
for it, you can get help on your help.
So, for instance if we want to look at
health info, it gives us a whole bunch of
different commands that we can do with
info.
We can look at sources, we can look at
records, we can look at, well, in this
case, I guess we can't look at sources,
can we?
But, we can definitely look at Registers.
so here's our SP, which you may already
have learned is the Stack Pointer, this
is pointing into the stack.
Here's our IP, the Instruction Pointer.
C, here's the name of the function that
we're inside of.
RAX often holds a return, and the first
two parameters to a function, will often
be an RDI, and RSI.
Certainly in a 62-bit machine like this,
62?
Goodness.
Certainly in a 64-bit machine like this
one.
Alright, so we will go back to the
assembly code, and if you take a step
like we did before we're going to run all
the way to the single line of execution
in the source code and blow off the Bomb.
So, instead we're going to type all those
A's back in, and we're going to take one
step instruction by instruction.
So, now if you see this little arrow on
the screen here, this is pointing to the
func, or the instruction that we're about
to execute, not the one we've just done.
This one is particular is pretty
interesting.
We're about to make a call to a function
called Strings not equal.
Well that sounds like the kind of thing
that we might care about.
So, let's look again at these registers,
and it looks like there's a little more
going on here than there was before.
So, you may recall that we can look at
what's on the stack.
That could be interesting, looking at the
stack, NGDB, can be a little bit complex.
but, basically, any, data source that you
want to look at, you can type this X.
And then what we're going to type in is
in the format number, number of units
that we want to look at and format, how
we want to see this data represented.
If you just type it like this it'll get
confused, it doesn't understand what
you're talking about.
So we say, X, we're going to look at
let's say 24 words, quad words in this
case, and oh, let's say HEX.
Everybody likes HEX, and we're going to
look at it on the stack so we'll say RSP.
And here we have all of the things on the
stack.
And you'll recognize this address from
previously when we looked at RSP to see
where it is.
Alright, great.
But, the stack isn't too interesting to
us because we're looking at a 64 bit
program.
So, it's going to be putting its
arguments to this string's not equal
function that we're interested in, right
into registers.
Well, specifically, the registers that
we're interested in are likely to be the
first two registers that arguments get
stored in.
So, again we can look at this X, and we
can say look at two words maybe.
And we'll represent them in HEX, and
we'll look at the first argument register
RDI.
It's a bunch of 61's, it's almost as if a
single value is being repeated a bunch of
times like those A's we typed in.
Now if there's an easy way that we can
look at them, that might be better.
We could say, let's look at these as
Strings instead of as HEX numbers.
Oops RDI, sorry about that.
And look, there's our A's, you can also
look at them as integers which is not
particularly useful for us right now.
by the way, just a quick tangent, I know
that the way we are representing
registers in GDB is an awful lot like the
way that assembly represents Constance.
This is an unfortunate, but true fact
that you're just going to have to get
used to.
It can be a little confusing at first.
if we try and tell it to look at a
register using the assembly code method
of a percent sign.
It's not going to know what we're talking
about.
I'm not sure why they decided to do it
this way, they just did.
Alright, so let's look at that other
register because we already found our
input.
But what could we be looking to see if
it's equal to.
Well, we could say let's look, and if
looking for Strings not equal, so we
probably want to look at them in String
format.
And we'll look at RSI, oh, now there's an
interesting String.
I'll put a couple breaks in so that you
can see it more clearly higher on the
screen.
Well I didn't type that string in so I
wonder where it could have come from.
Maybe it's important to look at in HEX,
59?
That doesn't look nearly as meaningful,
but let's copy it.
Oops, that's the wrong kind of copying.
Copy it, and we'll leave GDB, so I can
show you really quickly one last feature
of this Bomb that we have prepared for
you.
You can look at a text file, user.txt.
And we can paste in this value that we've
just received.
And we can run this Bomb.
First let's just run it without any
input.
We say Foo Bar Baz, I know what computer
scientists like, that's not the key.
Alright, we'll say bomb diffuser.text.
Well, that's not the key either, but you
see that I didn't need to enter any
input.
It's taking input from this diffuser.text
file.
So, is there any input that we've seen
earlier?
That might actually be the key to this
Bomb?
You should check it out.