Hello again, before we see processes in
virtual memory lets talk a little bit
more about control flow.
There'll be some special things about
control flow that's going to be useful to
implement process extractions in virtual
memory, okay?
So, if you recall, processors do one
thing, right?
They execute one instruction after the
other.
From start up to shut down.
'Kay.
So the CPU simply reads and executes a
sequence of instructions one at a time.
'Kay.
This is what we call control flow.
From start up to shutdown we execute one
instruction after the other.
This is control flow.
Okay.
So, how do we change the control flow?
Up to now we saw two ways.
First, we saw jumps seen them when we saw
Sandy program.
Remember, there were jump instructions
that changed the control flow.
We used that to implement things like
loops, conditionals, if then else etc.
And we also saw call and return, which is
used to implement procedures, okay?
It's used to implement procedure calls
and so on.
And both of these changes of a control
flow, they react to program states,
they're part of your program and they
react.
To the program state, okay?
So but the processor also needs to change
the control flow to react to changes in
system state, not, not program state,
okay?
So by, by, [INAUDIBLE] changes to system
state I mean things like, what if the
user hits control C at the keyboard?
Somehow the program has to been
interrupted, right?
And if the user clicks on the mouse, or
like me I'm using the pen here to write,
on, on the slide, I'm changing the system
state, and there's a program, in this
case a Powerpoint program, is reacting to
my pen touching the tablet here.
Okay?
So these are all things that external to
the program.
They're part of the system state, somehow
the program has to react to it.
And the way the program reacts to it is
by changing its control flow.
Okay?
Other examples are when data arrives from
the disk or the network adapter, somehow
the program has to go and read data.
From the network adapter and the disk and
to, to process it.
Okay?
And also there's things like if you do
division by zero, something that's
undefined.
So somehow the program has to, to do
something it's control flow to deal with
that situation.
Or if the system timer expires, you know,
from time to time.
This is device, called the timer, the
real timer, the real time timer in your
system.
That, from time to time it, it's,
interrupts the processor to tell it like,
a,a,a certain amount of wall clock time
has passed.
It's going to be useful to implement
contact switches that we're going to see
later in this module.
But now the real question is, can jumps
and procedure cause implement this.
Well, you really can't, right, so they're
not sufficient.
We need systems for exceptional control
flow for things that are not part of the
program state.
So, the way we implement control,
exceptional control flow is by using what
we call exceptions.
Okay, so, an exception is transfer
control to the operating system okay, in
response to some events.
For example, some change in process
through a stage.
So, here's how it happens.
Okay, so, say that our, our user process
is executing our codes and then this is
the current instruction being executed.
Then when, when, when a certain event
happens that leads to a exception, for
example we have a division by zero, or we
have something called a page fault, or
some I/O request completes, or even when
you type Ctrl+C.
In your in your keyboards.
So the program gets interrupted and then
there's, then exception happens.
Okay?
And the control is transferred to the
operating system.
Okay?
So in this exception processing the os is
done by the exception handler.
Okay?
The exception handler is nothing more
than a piece of code in the operating
system that handles what should be done
when a certain event that's an exception
happens.
Okay, and whenever the operating system
is done with processing that exception,
it returns to the instruction that was
that was being executed by the user
process.
It will return to the current
instruction, it could be return to the
next instruction or it could even decide
to simply abort.
The program, okay?
So an important question is how does the
system know which exception hander,
handler to execute?
Well, that's going to depend on the
exception that happens.
So, and there's something in your system
called interrupt vector that all it does
is it maps the exception.
An exception, in each exception has a
number.
To the codes that handles that exception.
So it's not, so the interrupt vector is
just a table that's indexed by the
exception number.
And the contents of this table is a
pointer to an instruction that many, that
the first instruction to block off codes,
that, treats that deals with that
exception.
Okay?
So, it, it's an interact jump table.
Great.
So, and the way we do this, well each
type of event has a unique exception
number, okay?
And, and that's, a number K.
And this K is an index to the exception
table.
Also known as interrupt vector.
So and then this handler is called every
time a certain exception is executed.
So, whenever exception K happens, the,
handler K is executed.
Okay, so there's two types of exceptions.
The first time, the, the, the first type
is an asynchronous exception.
Also known as interrupts.
And the reason they're called
asynchronous it's because they are caused
by events external to the processor.
So they are indicated by setting the
processors interrupt pins so the
processor, right as you saw there's a
bunch of pins in the processor.
So these pins, we call interrupt pins.
So whenever we put a signal in this
interrupt pin, something happens inside
the processor.
So an exception is raised.
And then the processor, executes, jumps
to, to the piece of code responsible for
dealing with that interrupt.
For example this interrupt could be, time
stopping the timer.
Okay?
Or you could be the mouse click, and so
on, okay?
So, for example, it could be hitting the
Ctrl+C on the keyboard, as I said, just
clicking on the mouse button or touching
the touch screen like what I'm doing
right now.
A packet arrives from the network, and so
on.
Okay?
So, now the other type of exceptions that
we called synchronous exceptions and
synchronous exceptions are caused by
events that are triggered by executing an
instruction, an instruction to something
that's undefined, that's potentially bad.
There's three types of synchronous
exceptions.
One is called traps is a just an
intentional way of transferring the
control flow to the operating system to
perform some functions.
In fact, that's, that's a fact of the
operating system, API.
A trap is a way of an application to
transfer the attention to the operating
system so you can do something for the
application.
Okay.
We, we call that system calls.
Okay?
So that's, that's the operating system
API.
But there are also other types of traps.
Whenever using GDB, we insert a break
point into your code.
It adds what we call break point trap.
So you code continues, your code
executes.
Whenever it reaches this break point it
sets a trap, it diverts execution, to the
debugger.
Okay?
And, and so on.
Great.
So and the traps, they return control to
the next instruction that's that call,
the instruction after the one that caused
this intentional trap.
The other type of synchronous exceptions
that we call fault.
These are unintentional, was not
intention of the program.
Okay?
But they are possibly recoverable.
For example, if you have a page fault
which you're going to see in more detail
in in, in future memories when the
program touch a piece of memory that is
not actually in memory, that's a fault in
the tran, trans, the transfer is, is the
control is transferred to the operating
system to deal with that situation.
Okay.
we're going to see an example on that a
little later in this video, okay?
So or we have, segment protection fault,
which you might have seen segfault when
execute some of your programs.
It's exactly what happened.
So, you, you might have touched a piece
of memory that's undefined and then
that's unrecoverable so your program is
aborted.
Another example of a fault is when you do
division by zero, [UNKNOWN] division by
zero is undefined that leads to an
exception, and your program might have to
deal with it.
It can potentially be unrecoverable,
okay?
So, and in the case of a fault, the
program either re-executes the faulty
instruction or the program aborts.
Finally, the last type of synchronous
exceptions will be called aborts.
They are unintentional and unrecoverable,
okay?
One example is when you have a parity
error or machine check that happens
because an instruction has touched
something that is bad in your system,
okay?
And it just simply aborts the program
because it is just unrecoverable.
So now let's see an example of a trap.
Okay an example, we using it to transfer
control to the operating system.
Okay.
So, opening a file requires an operating
system, service, okay?
And that's going to be done using a trap,
so for example every time your program
opens a file, eventually it's going to
open call this open function that takes a
file name as a parameter and then some
options on whether the file is for read,
write or both.
Okay.
And if you look at the assembly code for
this function open, you're going to see
this instruction here int hex 80, okay.
So, this diverts, this int is a, is a
trap that diverts the execution to, so
your process executing here.
So, the it is example that your program
is execute, whenever it reaches, it
executes int.
It, it's a, as I said it's an exception,
it's a trap.
Control is transferred to the operating
system.
And the operating system knows, based on
a number it needs to open a file.
So it opens a file and returns to here's
the code so you can go have the
manipulator file.
Okay so in what the OS does here is has
to find or create a file.
And get it ready for reading or writing,
okay?
And then it returns the file descriptor.
So that's why there's a pop here.
Okay?
Now another example, this is similar of a
trap.
Lets look at a example of a fault.
Okay.
Remember that a fault is an, is a
asynchronous exception that happens due
to something that you instruction that an
instruction does, okay.
So let's see what happens here.
See that we have this piece of code here.
Okay.
So eventually we're going to touch
memory.
An now so the, the user just writes
memory location.
And if it so happens that if the portion
of the users memory is currently on disk,
it's not in actual memory, okay, you're
going to see that in more detail in
virtual memory, but it could happen that
whenever you touch a memory location, the
memory actually isn't there yet.
So we have to transfer control to the
operating system to actually map that
page in.
Okay?
So here's our instruction that's being
executed.
Whenever we execute that instruction it
could be that if it so happens that the
page is not in memory yet.
This leads to what we call page fault
exception.
Okay?
The transfer again, transfer control to
the operating system that's going to
create a page and load it into memory.
And whenever that's done it's going to go
back.
And note that now the difference that
it's going to re-execute the memory
access because now the page is there.
So we can go and actually execute the,
the memory access.
Okay?
So in a, in this case the page handler
here that's executed by the operating
system loads the page into physical
memory.
And returns to the faulty instructions.
So, move has to be executed again.
Okay.
So, and hopefully the second time it's
going to be successful it could map, if
it could map the, the page.
Now, if you touch a bad memory location,
like let's say you just have a pointer
problem, okay.
You just had a pointer problem in your
codes, so that could be an invalid memory
reference.
So, in that case, if you touch a piece of
memory that's not mapped, but the OS
cannot find a, the operating system
cannot find a valid mapping as for
[INAUDIBLE] codes.
Okay, your execution, the execution of
your program.
So, let's look at this example again.
We have our move instruction here.
For re-executing [SOUND], it reaches the
move instruction and then that leads to
page fault because it's unmapped but the
OS determines that, you know what, not
only it's unmapped but this address is
invalid.
So what it needs to do, so just have to
go and signal the processing like,
unfortunately, I'm going to have to abort
you.
So it send this zigzag fault to the user
process and the user process exits with a
segmentation fault here.
Okay?
So, now to, to summarize.
Exceptions are events that require non
center control flow.
That means that, not, with you know,
jumps, or, call.
Okay?
They can be generated externally because
of interrupts or internally in case of
traps and faults.
And, the exception is handled by the
operating system.
And when your operating system handles an
exception, one of three things could
happen.
It re-executes the current instruction,
in the case of, for example, page faults.
It could resume the execution with next
instruction.
That is the case of doing a trap and
using operating system services like
opening file, reading or writing to a
file.
Or you might choose to abort the process
in case, the exception is unrecoverable.
See you soon!