[MUSIC].
Hi, there.
We're now starting a new section.
We're going to be talking about
processes, which is an abstraction
provided by the operating system together
with the hardware.
Just so we can run programs in
interesting ways, okay?
So then, we're going to see, we're going
to start seeing what a process is.
Then, we're going to see how we create
processes using operating system
services.
And then, we'll see how we can do
interesting things with processes.
So, what is a process?
And, but first of all, why are we
learning about processes?
Well, because they're an abstraction of
the computer system that provides this
interface between the program, and the
underlying CPU plus memory.
Okay, and this is provided by the
operating system.
Okay, so what the process have to do with
exceptional control flow?
Well, the operating system's going to
have to use tricks with exceptional
control flow to give the illusion that
multiple processes are running
simultaneously in the system, okay?
So what is a program?
A program is just a list of instructions,
a collection of instructions and data
that form your code, that form your
software, okay?
A processor, obviously, is the piece of
hardware that runs these structures in a
program.
In a process, well a process is an
instance of a running program.
When you start running a program, you
create a process to run the program,
therefore the process is an instance of a
running program, okay?
So, that's a very important idea in
Computer Science, and it's not the same
as a program or a processor, okay?
A processor executes instructions, and a
program is a collection of instructions
and data.
A process is an instance of a program
running in a processor, so and they
provide two key abstractions.
The first one is logical control flow.
So, that means that each process has the
illusion that it has full control of the
CPU as exclusive use of the CPU.
Which might actually be in the, in
reality the case, but processes give this
abstraction to programs that so to
processes such that it seems like they
have full use of the CPU, okay?
And now, the other one is private virtual
address space.
Means that each, this gives the illusion
that each process.
Has control over the entire memory.
Nobody else is touching memory.
Okay, so this is very important because
it makes it much easier to isolate
programs to manage memory layout and so
on, okay?
So why are they important?
Well, we simplify writing programs a lot
because you give the illusion that they
have the program, the program has entire
memory.
And also gives it illusion that it has
complete control of the process, or
complete use of the process.
And how are these illusions maintained?
Well, first of all process, process
executions are interleaved.
That means from the process point of
view, which means it's a switch between
one process and the other.
And the address space is managed by
neutral memory by, by the visionary
system which is going to be a topic of
our next section.
So processes can be concurrent.
And it means if they run concurrently, if
the instruction flows overlap in time.
Otherwise, they are sequential.
So, let me give you an example.
Suppose that I have Process A here,
Process A is running, having control in
the CPU, then now it's paused for a
second.
And then it continues running and it ends
here, okay?
Process B starts here and ends here.
Process C starts here, runs, pauses for a
bit and ends right there.
So, it means that processes that are
concurrent are A and B are concurrent,
okay?
And also A and C, because you see, they
are actually running parallel.
However, B and C are not concurrent
because B ends here right before C
starts.
now, the user view of concurrent
processes as if they are actually running
at the same time.
Okay, that's the illusion that they have
full control of the CPU.
When in reality, what's going on is that
one, a processor might be paused, but
still conceptually executing, but not
really.
It's not actually making use of the
processor.
so we can really think of concurrent
processes as executing in parallel.
Now, how, how does that work?
Let's say they have a single process or
you have multiple processes running at
the same time, how does that work?
We need some mechanism that bounces
between processes that are running at the
same time.
So, this is what we call context
switching, okay?
So, the process are managed by a shared
chunk of OS code called the Kernel, okay?
And it's important to note that the
kernel is not a seperate process, but
it's just a piece of code.
A special piece of code that runs as part
of a user process.
But the kernel code has special
privileges.
So, here's how the context switch
happens.
Say that Process A is running, and then
suddenly it's time-based on a timer.
There's a timer interrupt that says okay,
the time, processor time for Process A,
CPU time for Process A is up.
So now, there's an interrupt here, time
interrupt, that switches to kernel code.
And the kernel code is going to save the
state.
You save A here, save the state of A.
And then you restore B, and then B
executes then times up again.
The, the kernel code executes through the
context switch, and the context switch
saves B here and restores the state of A
and continue.
So that's, that's a process called
Context Switch.
Now what's actually saved here?
What will we have to save here?
We have to save the instruction pointer
because the we have to know where Process
A stopped.
So, we need to restore it again and
continue allocating from that point.
It also needs to save register states,
okay?
Because we need to restore those to
continue executing the program.
And the, there are a few other things
that also happen there, but that's that's
subject for a another time.