[MUSIC].
Now that we know how, what a process is
and how to create processes, let's see
how we do interesting things with
processes.
We're going to be talking about this
fork-exec model.
And as we saw before, fork creates a copy
of the current process, the process that
called fork and execve what's going to
do, is going to replace the current
process code and address space with a
code for a different program.
okay?
In fact there's a whole family of exec
calls I encourage you to explore them,
'kay.
So for example here, in this, in this
code we are calling fork so if the PID is
not zero, that's the parents they created
a child, okay.
And otherwise if the PID is 0, that's the
child, okay.
And when we coexecve the figure the child
is going to replace its codes and its,
its data in its address space with the
codes and addresses from a different
Program.
And this line here is going to be printed
by the parent only.
And we'll see.
And, and that's, that's because execv is
now going to return.
So let's, let's see an animation, of how
this happens.
Okay?
So this, this is the parent process right
here.
Parent process, okay?
So, and, when you say that's, that's,
that's the bash process right the shell
that you might be probobaly running in
your system, okay.
When you type alas for example, what its
going to do is bash is going to fork
because it needs to create a new process
to execute the command alas.
Okay and here's how its going to happen.
So bash calls fork, okay.
So that's the parent, that's the original
process here and now its going to create
a child, that at that point is exactly
the same.
These two are the same but now what it
needs to do, it needs to call exec and
replace what was there in the child with
the stack, the, the address space, and
the codes for the program LS it's
going to list a directory.
Okay?
So that's a high level view, okay?
So the bash which is process happens to
be the shell when you type LS, it's going
to create a new process.
And it's going to replace the child
process with the code and address space
for ls, because ls is, is just a program.
Okay?
Okay, so now here is how execve works, in
more detail.
That's the prototype of the function,
'kay, recieves three parameters.
'Kay, one is a filename, it's a filename
of the executable containing the program
that we want to, to exec.
Then the argument that were going to pass
to, to, to the program in this MPSD
environment that the lift of environemt
varibales things like for example the
current directory and so on.
Now note that execve does not return, why
is that?
Well, because it's going to be executing
a different program now.
And the execve call was part of the
original program that was it's, it's part
of the program was running that, that was
running before execve.
So as soon as you do execve, that current
program is no longer running, that's why
it doesn't return.
Unless there's an error, then it's going
to return.
Okay.
And as I said before it overrides the
code, the data, and the stack, okay.
It keeps the, the process ID open files
and a few other files.
Okay.
Now, let's see how this collection of
data structures here look like in memory.
Okay, so, that's, that's a stack frame
for main.
Now we have what, we have D argument
count, the, vector of arguments.
Okay, that's five points to a list of, it
points to a vector.
And it each intuit is vector is a
pointer.
To the strings of the command line
arguments.
Okay.
Now the environment NP points to a,
another vector.
It's a list of pointers to the contents
of the environment variables, so it's a
pretty beefy data structure.
Okay.
alright, so this is how exit field works.
And now how do we end the process?
We're going to use a call called exit.
And we use a parameter a status of why
the process exits.
So, status code zero is normally used for
normal exits and non zero is abnormal
exit like, you know, there was an
exception or there was something,
something happened to the process.
Okay?
So, and if you, if you want to register
functions to be executed when you exit
the process, you can call at exit, it's
something to be executed at exit.
For example, say that you call cleanup
here.
So if you say atexit cleanup, when, when
the process here exits, it's going to
call this function cleanup here.
Okay?
So, but once this happens it doesn't
really completely destroy the process.
It creates what we call a zombie, zombie
process.
Okay, so and the reason we call it a
zombie is because when the process
terminates.
It still consumes resources.
Okay.
So things like, many tables in the OS
keep track of processes, and so on.
We call it zombie because kind of like a
living corpse half alive and half dead.
But what happens if they build up, well
there's a process called reaping that
cleans up after a dead process and its
performed by the parent process on a
terminated child.
OK, so when a parent process creates a
child process, and the child process
exits, dies, the parent is given it's
exit status information and with the
reaping process tell the kernels to
discard.
Whatever was left from the process and
recycle those, those resources mm-hm.
Now what if a parent doesn't reap?
Well, that could be a problem if the
parent runs for a long time.
But if any parent terminates without
reaping, then the child will be reaped by
init process, by the init process.
By the way the init process is a process
that is a parent of all processes in your
system.
'Kay, when your operating system boots,
and is ready to execute something it
increases an init processes it's sort of
like the canonical process from which all
other processes arrive, kay.
So if a parent terminates without reaping
a child, then the child will be reaped by
the init process.
Okay, but one thing to note is that if
you have a long running process you need
to do explicit reaping otherwise nobodies
going to reaping and it's going to be
using resource and it's eventually it's
going to exhaust it's resources.
An example of long live processes that
need to do reaping are things like shells
and servers and so on, okay.
Alright, so now that we know what happens
when the process dies, let's see how we
use that for synchronization.
There's this function called "wait"
that's used to synchronize with children
processes.
'Kay?
So, what it does is, when you call wait,
it suspends the current process, for
example the parent, until one of its
children terminates, okay.
And the return value is the PID of the
child process that terminated because a
parent could have multiple child that its
waiting to die on.
And on successful return the, the child
process is then reaped, okay?
And by the way, if the child's status is
set to, this is a parameter to, to the
wait function if it's set to not know,
then the, the integer that it points to,
because note that's an integer pointer
and that it points to will be set to a
status indicating why the child process
terminated.
Okay?
So because now we can read the exit
status of the process.
This int return here just returns the
pid.
That's the pid.
'Kay.
And this points to the status at exit
that the child had.
'Kay.
So and are there are special macros for
this to interpret this status.
And you can see wait two[INAUDIBLE] ,
wait two and, and see what those mean.
So, now note that if apparent processes
multiple children, if you call wait, it
will return the, when any of the children
terminates, that's why there's another
call called waitpid.
And here's what it does, you can wait on
a specific child process by passing it's
PID as a parameter.
Okay?
So, let's an example of wait here.
So, we have this function called fork
wait.
It forks here.
If it's zero, again it's the child.
It says hello from child.
Otherwise that's the parent, that's and
it's going to do the following, the child
pid is going to wait on the, on child
status, just an integer here.
Okay?
And when, when that returns it's because
the child has died.
So, now when, when that happens we're
going to print the pid of the child, note
that this returned by weight.
Okay, and it's going to say it has
terminated, okay, and then it's goign to
say bye.
So let's see how this works here.
There you have it, originally the process
was running, then it forks, okay, then
eventually the child is going to say bye.
Whenever the says bye its because he has
returned, therefore we come back here,
and then the parent calls bye.
Pretty interesting, right?
Super simple and effective, you can
imagine very complicated trees and what,
arrangements of how, of how, parents and
childs, synchronize.
So to, to summarize, recall that fork
gets two copies of the same process.
Okay?
But it, but fork returns different values
to the two process.
In fork is a special function.
You call once, but return twice, because
that's the point where it replicates the
process, okay?
So execve has a new process, replaces
itself with one, with the one that called
it, okay?
So it's a two process program, okay?
So when you you call fork, so heres an
example of a two process you first call
fork and if the pid is zero thats a child
code otherwise exit the parent code.
And that's where you'd use in the child
code thats where you call exactly to
replace itself with a new program.
Okay, so now at that point you have two
completely two completely different
programs.
'Kay?
Great.
So, inwait and waitpid is used to
synchronize parent and child execution
and whenever you do this execution
process, the child the like remains of
the child process is collected when it
exits, okay.
So in the final sumary of this section we
are now ending our section processes so
that keeping in mind that at any given
time the system has a lot of active
processes in fact if you type in Linux PS
for example minus ZF to, to, to make it,
to make it return here.
To make it easy to read.
When you type that you're going to see
the list of all processes running.
Okay, that's, that's your prompt here you
type ps minus ef you're going to get a
list.
But if you have a single CPU only one can
execute at a time.
And the process has the illusion that it
has full control of the CPU.
That's pretty cool right?
It's a really important abstraction
Alright, okay.
And from time to time the OS has to do
the context switch because there's a
single CPU, you want to give the illusion
that things are running at the same time.
So, it keeps bouncing back and forth
between, between the running processes.
Okay?
So, and we do process management with
this fork-exec model that you just
learned.
That concludes the section, see you soon.