[MUSIC].
Well, we've come to the end of the
course.
And we'd really like to thank you all for
having made it this far with us.
this has been an incredible learning
experience for us on how to deliver this
kind of material.
Over Coursera and over the over the video
format and Distance Learning.
And we hope that you learned a lot about
the computer systems we've been talking
about as well.
the course might, might not, this course
format may not have been as new to some
of you.
you might have done other courses like
this before.
we'd be very interested to hear about
your experience and, and how, what you
thought of how we ran this.
for us, it's brand new, so we have a lot
more to learn than you do about that
aspect.
and
Well, thank you very much for putting up
with us all of the way through.
>> And well.
We also hope that you, you learned how,
your programs run in a computer system.
Have a better idea how, how computers
work.
And we hope that, this, course has
spurred your interest in learning more
about programming in C.
And learning more about, and, and other
programming languages.
And in learning more about how operating
systems work and computer architecture
and, and so on.
We also hope that the, the labs and
assignments were more rewarding than
frustrating.
We know some of them were quite time
intensive, but we really hope that they
gave you a much better understanding of
how things work.
So in case that you noticed that Gaitan
and I wore the same shirt throughout the
entire course.
So and as a gift for you at the end of
the course, we decided to show you how we
normally dress.
>> So as you can see we like dressing
pretty differently.
Luis is very formal, loves dressing up.
>> And this is his regalia from the
University of Illinois.
And I'm a little less formal.
>> Right as you can see guys, Gaitan
really likes football.
But most importantly you see that his
number is 32, which is a power of 2.
Really to, you know, as homage to his
Computer Science devoted life.
[LAUGH] And I'm sure you saw this number
32 in the course a lot.
And you're going to continue seeing the
number 32, in doing Computer Science.
>> Well, so, again we'd like to thank
you for taking the course with us.
And we hope it was valuable for you, it
certainly was for us.
And we look forward to maybe seeing you
again sometime soon.
so from Seattle, take care, and keep on
programming.
>> Thank you very much, keep on