Hello, again.
Now, we are ready to start a new section.
What we are going to be seeing now is how
we can use a special type of memory
called caches to make the process of
memory interaction faster.
The process memory is actually very, very
important for overall computer
performance.
So, understanding that is very, very
important.
So here's what we're going to see in this
section.
We're going to see the basics of caches,
then we're going to understand why caches
work.
we're going to see how to put several
caches together into a hierarchy.
We're going to see how we organize caches
In a way that makes them fast and
effective.
And finally, we're going to see how we
can make software better at using caches.
So, let's start with a question.
So, how does execution time of this
program go, grows with the value of size?
So, in, in this example we have.
We have an array with as many elements as
the value of this size, the size define,
and we have a variable called a.
And all this is doing is adding the value
of several of the array elements into a
we're accumlating them into a.
This inner loop here is iterating over
the array repeatedly.
Now as so it iterating over the entire
array.
And the outer loop is iterating over the
entire array repeatedly.
So we have an inner loop and an outer
loop.
Okay.
So how to expect the plot of execution
time to do with respect to size.
Certainly this doesn't go down it
probably goes up because as size goes as
a value size, goes up this[INAUDIBLE] is
going to take longer the because the
inner loop is going to be longer.
So let's see how it looks, so here's the
actual data of this experiment.
Okay.
So we had was here's time, and here's
size.
And there's two interesting things to
note here.
First is, there's a knee in this curve,
here.
Okay, there's a knee here.
And then there's too other essentially
flatlines here.
And, and they don't have exactly the same
slope.
So at some point, there's some threshold
that makes, that after you go above the
threshold in size, the execution time
grows.
Faster, so something is getting slower as
we grow the value of size.
Distance height turns out to be exactly
the cashes.
If the array, if the array fits in cash
entirely we're going to have a slope as
long as it does not fit in cash any more
we're going to start to have to go memory
more often.
Then your going to have a different
curve.
We have a different slope.
Okay.
So and the problem here is that, there's
this processor memory bottle neck that we
need to address.
And the reason this bottle neck exist is
that the CPU it's self had it's
performance growing every 18 months.
Okay, growing very, very fast.
That's why we have super fast computers
today.
And as we saw early on in this course,
you see there was a dramatic increase in
number of transistors.
Dramatic increase in performance, and so
on.
Memory, although memory also evolved, it
did not evolve as fast as the processor.
Not the memory latency.
Nor the, the bandwidth to move data in
and out of the processor.
So the, the problem here is that there's
a lot of waiting fundamentally, right?
If the process is getting faster, much
quicker than memory's getting faster,
that means the disparity is going up.
It is also known as a memory wall.
Okay?
So, ultimately, the big problem is that
there will be lots of waiting on memory.
Processors do not like to wait.
If they're waiting, they're wasting time,
it hurts performance.
But because memory, didn't get as fast,
can it get fast enough compared to the
processor that will be waiting?
So how do we solve this problem?
Well, what we're going to do is put this
little bit of memory closer to the
processor here, okay?
Called the cache, okay?
And that's going to hold data that's
accessed frequently.
And since the cache is smaller and closer
to the processor, it's much much faster
to access data stored in the cache.
Okay?
One of the reasons that caches are fast
is because they are small.
Right?
Fundamentally[INAUDIBLE] speed of light,
so if you make things small, it can make
them fast.
The larger you make them, fundamentally
they're going to be slower.
Okay?
So let's think about the word cache for a
second.
The English definition is a hidden
storage, space for, hidden storage space
for provisions, weapons, or treasures.
In our case, our treasure is data, okay?
In Computer Science, the definition is a
computer memory with short access time
used for storage of data that's accessed,
data or codes that's accessed, frequently
or recently.
'Kay?
So and more generally the section used to
optimize data transfers between system
elements with different characteristics.
Okay?
You could imagine caches, you, you know
we have a, a caches cache for pages in
your browser's a form of cache.
You can cash you know to disk, because
disks are also not very fast.
So if you access it repeatedly you can
put data in a faster memory these, these
are all forms of caches, okay?
So let's see now have the general cache
mechanics works.
Okay, so we have our cache here.
And we have memory.
And memory's going to have a bunch of
locations or blocks.
And so, and the, the unit of transfer
between memory and caches is this block.
Okay?
So that means we're now going to move a
byte at a time.
And we're going to see that actually
helps us a lot.
We're going to that why soon.
But here see the, let's see the
mechanics.
Okay?
So and one thing that's important to note
here, by the way, is that the cache
stores a subset of memory.
Okay?
So again, the reason that caches are fast
is because they're small.
So they're going to be much smaller than
memory.
So it can only hold a subset.
Of the data stored in in memory.
So the first concept is what we call a
hit.
'Kay.
A hit means whenever you want to access
the data.
'Kay, let's say that the processor that's
right here, 'kay, that's, that's where
the CPU is, asks for 14.
Well, it happens to be in the cache.
We call a hit.
It means that the data, the CPU asks for
the data and then the cash can provide
the data back.
So that's much, that's fast, right,
because we took advantage of, that's a
good thing, right, we took advantage of
the fact that caches are fast and
provided that they're in the cache.
This is in contrast to what we call a
miss, so suppose that a data block these
needed by the CPU here.
Okay and we happen to need 12, so we're
going to ask does it, is 12 here.
Well, the answer is, no it's not.
Okay so, it's a miss.
So, what happens now?
What do you think?
Well, we're going to have to go to memory
and get the data.
So the cache requests 12 from memory, so
the[INAUDIBLE] 12 is gotten, is obtained
from memory.
And then it gets transferred to the cash
and now it's stored in the cache.
And note, let me show you, notice
something else got kicked out.
What happened?
Nine has to be kicked out.
To store 12.
We're going to see in detail later why
this is this is important.
And since the cache is finite I've had to
kick things out.
So, the choice of what's going to be
kicked out is very, very important.
Okay?
So, one thing I don't want you to forget
from this, this first video on caches, is
that a cache is this little bit of very
very fast memory in between CPU and lots
of lower memory.
'Kay?
So we can give the CPU the illusion that
memory is faster by putting a little bit
of storage closer to it.
'Kay?
See you soon.