[MUSIC].
Hello.
Let's see now why caches work, which the
principle of locality.
So why do caches work?
There's something programs called
locality, which says that they tends to
use data and instructions set at either.
Nearby in space, they're close by,
addresses are close by.
Or, they tend to be written to reuse
data, the same data over and over again.
So this is called locality because it
tends to stay close by, either in space,
or in time, okay?
So we have two types of locality.
One is called temporal locality.
That says that data items that were
referenced recently.
Are likely to be referenced again, in the
near future.
So if you gotta a given data in a, in a
block here, I give you piece of data that
start a new that, that is accessed by
your program.
You tend to access it over and over again
in time, 'kay.
Then there's another thing called spacial
locality.
That says that if you have a piece of
data that you're interested in.
It's likely that you're also going to
you're also going to need a piece of data
that that happens to be located very
nearby in the address space.
'Kay.
So how do caches take advantage of
temporal locality?
Well, just by storing recently accessed
data we take advantage of temporal
locality.
'Kay.
But now.
How, how do caches take as either spatial
locality, take space, or do the spatial
locality by bringing entire blocks of
data from memory, as opposed to a single
byte at a time.
So, essentially, if you need say, address
A, when you go to the cache, you're not
only going to get A, but you're also
going to get A plus 1, A plus 2, and so
on.
Up up to a certain limit.
So let's see an example of a program that
has locality.
Suppose you have this loop here, and this
loop is iterating over a rate a and
adding it to the sum variable.
Where is locality here?
Where's locality, locality here?
Let's start with data.
Well, so with data the variable sum, is
referenced multiple times.
Okay?
We act so, we act over and over again
here inside our loop.
At each iteration of the loop read it,
and write it.
It reads it because you're doing sum,
equals sum, plus a of i.
Now, we also have spatial locality
because we're accessing array a in all of
it's elements.
So if you have memory here, so we're
going to have your a of a and then right
next to it, you're going to have a of
one.
And then we're going to have a.
Of two and so on.
They're all near by in memory.
So since they're close by, we can, we can
take advantage of spacial locality.
So the other, type of locality that we
have here is instructional locality,
okay?
So we have instructions, well remember
that instructions are just stored in
memory.
It means the processors have to read
them, right?
And system tend to read one instruction
after the other, right?
So in, I mean, so we already have special
locality right off the bat, because, you
know, we read, we read references.
We, we read instructions in the sequence
that they appear in the program, okay?
So when you have a series of instructions
one after the other in your program,
they're going to reside close by memory,
right next to each other.
So when you bring one, you might as well
just bring a few instructions ahead as
well, okay.
And we also have temporal locality
because we have things like, loops.
See this loop here is just executing it's
body over and over and over again.
If we have a cache that stores the code
for the body of the loop, it's going to
be very effective, right?
Because instead of going to memory every
time you execute a body of the loop, you
can just go, to the cache, and and get
the data.
Okay?
So it's very important to be able to
assess locality of your program
effectively.
Because it will help you lay out data and
memory in a way that's more effective for
cad, that makes caches more effective for
your program.
Okay?
So if you know that there's a certain way
of accessing your data structures, such
that it can take advantage of spatial
locality, you should definitely do it,
because it is going to make your program
faster.
And, same way, if there was, if there's a
way of writing your program that
increases the possibility of taking
advantage of temporal locality.
It's also very important.
So let me give you an example here.
Suppose I have this piece of code here.
It's a, it, it, it recieves.
an array.
A three-dimensional array, okay?
A three-dimensional matrix as as a
parameter.
And then we trade over the entire array.
That's why we have three loops, okay?
One loop that varies i, which is one of
the index here.
The other one varies j, which is this
index here.
And then another that varies k, which is
this index here.
And the way C lays out matrices in memory
is just by putting an entire row at a
time.
'Kay, but since this program here is not
accessing all of the elements of a row
before moving to the next one, right?
So then we see the inner loop here is
varying the outer most dimension.
Now we're just, going all over memory,
instead of, reading memory one after the
other here, we're going to read one
place, another place, another place,
another place, and it's just not going to
take advantage of locality, especially if
the, matrix does not fit in cache.
'Kay.
I know this was quick, but we're going to
show you another example later on as we
teach you more about caches, it's
going to make this make sense.
This is mainly to show that if you, you
have to pay attention to your code to
understand how we can take individual
locality and whether you might have, be
having performance issues because of
that.
'Kay.
So what's wrong with this code is that
we're accessing it out of order.
So, how can we fix it?
Well, we should first loop through the
last dimension, then the middle dimension
then the first dimension.
Because we access we access data in a way
that that follows how it's laid out in
memory.
Okay?
See you soon.