Now, we're going to do our last topic in
our memory and caches section.
We're going to talk about program
optimizations that considered cache.
Okay.
So the optimization code for the memory
hierarchy has, you know, essentially
boils down to write code that has better
locality.
Okay.
That has better locality properties.
And remember, there are two types of
locality spatial locality and temporal
locality.
Okay .
And spatial locality, what we want to do
is symmetrically access data contiguously
as much as possible.
Even lays out data in memory in a way
that increases .
the spatial locality properties.
And the second one is temporal locality.
Make sure the algorithm, the code should
make sure that if there's a data item
that's going to be accessed multiple
times, try to access them closer in time.
So you can take advantage of temporal
locality and increase the likelihood that
the data is going to be in the cache...
And ways of achieving that, there's
multiple ways.
Two basic ones, one is a proper choice of
algorithm.
Of course the algorithm itself determines
a lot of the, how the data is laid out
and the order of operations in the data.
And the second one is loop
transformations.
How to reorder loops when you're
traversing data structures.
So let me give you an example that's
going to showcase how important this is.
When we talk about matrix multiplication.
In matrix multiplication, what happens is
for example, suppose that i have a matrix
c that multiplier by multiplication
between matrix a and matrix b.
So this element here of c which is
element i, j is equals.
First column of the ith row of a
multiplied by the first row of column j
in matrix b plus this one times this one
plus this one times this one, this one
times this one and so on.
Okay.
So that means that the, this loop here, I
don't want to read the corner detail
because it's going to be it's going to be
hard for you.
So, but, what you need to understand is
that this code is reading this, reading
this, and then reading this, then reading
this, then reading this, then reading
this.
And so on.
It's going to read the entire row of a
and this entire column of b.
Just to produce a single element in, in
c.
Okay?
So this is a matrix that's n by n
elements, okay?
So we're going to do n squared of these
operations.
Okay?
So it's a lot.
It could, specially if the matrix as big,
this could be a lot of operation.
So now, let's look at Cache Miss Analysis
of this matrix duplication, okay?
We are going to assume that matrix
elements are doubles, o they take 8
bytes.
And if our cache block is 64 bytes, each
cache line, each cache block holds 8
doubles.
Let's also say that our cache size c,
capital c it's much smaller than, than n.
'Kay, which is the dimension of our, our
which is our dimension of our matrix.
The dimension of our matrix n by n.
So let's see what happens in the first
situation.
Remember, in the first situation we're
going to be arranging entire row of this
matrix and entire columns of this matrix,
okay.
So one thin to keep your mind to, the way
data's laid out in memory.
What we're doing is, we are storing an
entire row in memory, then another row,
then another row.
Then another row, and so on.
So, let's say if this is row zero, row
one, row two, and row three.
The way it's laid out in memory here.
Is we're going to have entire row zero,
then entire row one, entire row two,
entire row three.
And so on.
'Kay, so the number of misses that we're
going to have is going to be, what, it's
going to be n divided by 8.
Because as we're reading this one line
here, we know that, since each line here,
each cache line, each cache block has.
Eight doubles.
So like, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
We go back to the first one's going to be
a miss.
Then the second one's going to hit, a
hit, a hit, a hit, a hit, a hit, and then
the next one here is going to be a miss.
So that's why it's n divided by 8.
Okay, that's taking advantage of that,
because of spacial locality, we're taking
only n over 8.
'Kay?
Now, we're going to add n here because
for each column here, 'kay?
So each, each for each column here we're
going to, so for this column here, for
each row of this column, we're going to
have a cache miss, right?
We're going to mess up this one and then
this one, this one, this one, this one,
so forth.
Like all of them, because.
Just this is, bigger than a block.
Remember that if the cache is much
smaller than n, definitely a blocks much
smaller than n.
So, and then when we are done with the
saturation, only this part and this part
is going to be in the cache.
And why is it?
It is because we just read the first
element, and everything else, we didn't
read.
Okay?
Great.
So we're going to have 9n over 8 misses
for the first iterations.
Now, if we extend this to all of the
other iterations, what we're going to do
is going to have 9n over 8 misses
multiplied by n squared, which is the
number of iterations.
Remember that we're going to do this,
this is n.
By n, and we're do this for each one of
the elements here, so that means there's
n square elements.
So this, that means that our final cache
miss the number of cache misses is 9 over
8, multiplied by n squared, so it's a lot
of cache misses.
'Kay?
So one way to solve this problem is to do
what we call a blocked matrix
multiplication.
So instead of doing an entire row and
entire column, were going to do this
block by block, okay.
Such that we're going to, when we read a
part of a here, we're going to read.
All of these.
And then for b here, instead of reading
just, just the first one we're going to
need, we're going to read multiple rows,
'kay?
But smaller, in a subset of the row, such
that this stays in cache and this stays
in cache.
'Kay?
And then when we need to cycle over this
multiple time we're not going to have to
take the miss again.
Isn't that cool?
So, now lets, let's do a, cache miss
analysis of this one, okay?
So now how many blocks are we going to
have?
Well we're going to have n over b blocks,
because b is the size of the block, okay?
So, and we know that three blocks fits in
the cache.
Kay, so and, and that means that 3b
squared is smaller than the cache size c.
So, now, what we're going to have is,
we're going to have b squared over 8
misses for each block, right?
Because we have this repeatedly.
And then.
so if we do, when, when we add this up,
we're going to have 2n over b times b
squared over 8 which then, which ends up
being nb over 4 misses.
So now, in the end, after it went in the
cache, we're going to have, is we're
going to have all of this, because we
access all of these blocks that happen to
fit in the cache.
Great.
So, now this is the first iteration.
When we do this over all iterations you
know, all these are going to be the same
as the first one.
We are going to do this.
But now, since we are dividing we do this
in blocks, now we are doing n over b
squared.
That would be, because were going to do
this one for each block but were going to
do it a few times were going to do n over
b times square.
So in the end what were going to do is
our caching is going to be n squared
divided by 4b so there's a huge impact in
our cache miss.
So in summary, if we don't do blocking
we're going to have 9 over 8 n squared
misses, but if we do blocking it's going
to be 1 over 4b multiplied by n squared
misses.
Okay.
So if B equals 8, the difference is 36
times.
If B is 16, the difference number of
misses is 72x.
It's just really, really, really big.
Okay?
So, and the reason for dramatic
difference is that, makes the duplication
inherently has temporal locality.
But you have to reorder the operation in
order to take advantage of that.
Okay.
So they put data is 3n squared.
In the computations 2 and cube, so every
element is accessed, order and times.
Okay.
But the program really has to be written
properly otherwise the different
localities are too far apart in time and
the cache can't capture it.
Okay.
So...
The important thing to re, to keep in
mind for cash friendly code is that the
programmer, you, can optimize code for
case performance.
But it really depends on how the data
structures are organized, how data are
accessed How the loop nest structure
works is think about blocking.
Because blocking is a general technique.
You can always try to reorganize how the
order that you do things.
That you try to keep a dully of blocks.
Only parts of it in memory.
Okay.
So and one thing to keep in mind is that
all systems like cache-friendly code but
to get absolutely optimum performance
really depends on the platform.
Because it depends on knowing the actual
cache organization cache geometry.
Things like cache sizes, line sizes,
associativities and so on.
'Kay.
So you can get most of the advantage with
generic code.
'Kay.
So not, when you're writing generic code,
just keep in mind that keep working set
size reasonably small so it fits in the
cache and you take advantage of temporal
locality.
Uses small strides so you take advantage
of spatial locality, right, because it's
to be close by.
And focus on inner loop codes because
those are the ones that are going to be
accessed close by in time, okay.
Let's edge our, memory and caches
section, what we call the Memory
Mountain.
Okay, this is, this is very cool.
Okay, we are, we are, we ran some
experiments in Intel core I7, okay.
And what we're showing you here in the
access in, is read through put, megabytes
per second.
So that means, up is good, is better,
okay.
And our one cache is 32 kilobytes, so and
this is the working set size which grows
this way, and the stride size grows this
way, okay.
First thing to notice, as you increase
the stride size, you see there's a
general drop in throughput, because
you're not taking as much advantage of
temporal locality.
Now, the other thing is if you go, if you
increase the working set size, if it fits
in the L1 cache you'll have really,
really good high through put...
But then as the, as this doesn't fit in
the L1 cache, now we're going to drop to
the other plateau here which is whatever
fits in the L2.
And then the next plateau is whatever
fits in the L3, whatever doesn't fit here
in L3, have to go to memory.
Isn't that cool?
So, that means if you keep the working
set size as much higher, as low as small,
there's much higher chance to stay within
the L1 which is good.
Or with the L2, and so on.
So things to keep in mind is, take
advantage of spatial locality, so you
keep the stride low.
Take advantage of the working set size,
you can do blocking to keep to focus on
the working side size for reachable parts
of your code.
Okay.
And if you keep it small, you're going to
get very high throughput.
It has a huge impact on performance.
This concludes out memory and caches
section, and I'll see you soon.