[MUSIC].
We've seen multidimensional arrays now,
at least two dimensions, but things
extend, in the same way to three
dimensions and four and more dimensions.
what I want to do now is introduce you to
a multi-level arrays which are a little
bit different.
They try to do some similar things but in
a very different way using pointers
rather than a continuous allocation in
memory.
Lets take a look at the multi-level
array.
Here I'm showing three one-dimensional
That we've that we declared are zip digit
arrays.
one for each zip code of five digits
each, okay?
One-dimensional arrays we're now going to
declare a multi-level array called a univ
that is actually an array of pointers to
integers.
You notice the star there in front of it
and it's going to have this number of
elements in this case set 23 and the
three elements will be our three
one-dimensional arrays from above.
And you'll see that that looks like it
should be a two-dimensional array, right?
We've just organized three zip codes into
an array of three elements.
each element having five digits.
But is this a two-dimensional array?
well it's not.
It's a little bit different.
and the reason it's different is because
they, the the three a, the three sub
arrays do not have to be continuous in
memory.
and they don't have to be in row major
order like we had before.
In this case, you'll notice that the
three arrays have been allocated to three
different locations in memory.
Separately, each one of them in isolation
they were declared as separate arrays
initially.
Then our array univ has three pointers in
it it's an array of pointers after all
and these were point to those the
beginning of each of those three one
dimensional arrays.
But [INAUDIBLE] not in any set order.
It doesn't expect them to be in a
particular arrangement in memory.
This turns out to be also the way Java
represents arrays all the time.
It does not have really multi dimensional
arrays, it only has multi-level arrays,
involving pointers like this.
Although, this is made invisible in the
language, but this is what's going on
underneath.
Okay, so our array univ has three
elements, each one of them is a pointer
that's 4 bytes long and of course, it's a
one-dimensional array of pointers.
So, they're represented one after the
other, in memory, each one of them points
to an integer basically the starting
integer of the three one-dimensional
arrays that we have.
So let's take a look at how access works
to this.
So, here we're going to have the same
procedure we had before for getting a
digit of the zip code only this time
you'll notice, although we address it, it
looks the same, let's see what actual
assembly code gets generated, okay?
So see at the beginning, we'll have our
first index in the register ECX.
And we're going to multiply that by four
and put the result in EDX.
And why are we multiplying it by four?
Well, because we're indexing into our
univ array and we need to know how much
of an offset to have to get the right
pointer.
Once we have that pointer, you'll notice
we will use that, to get that pointer we
will use that offset we've just computed
added to the starting address of the
array, and then access that memory
location.
Ac, this is actually reading that memory
location, getting the pointer, and
putting it into EDX.
Okay, so we've done one memory access
already into the univ array to get the
right pointer.
Once we have the pointer, we're going to,
use that as an offset to four times the
other parameter, the other argument to
this function, the index of the digit,
okay?
And the four there is because of course
we're doing integers and they're four
byes each so we're computing the address
along the one dimensional, the offset in
the one dimensional array, adding that to
the starting address of the one
dimensional array that we just got from
the univ array.
So, that gives us a second memory access,
we're now going to that memory location
and actually reading the digit.
So, the important thing to understand
here is that in this case we must do two
memory reads.
First to get the address to the row, the
pointer to the row and then access within
that row.
In the multidimensional case, we could do
that in one address computation because
we had the guarantee that each row
followed one after the other.
Okay, so, the access does look similar in
the C code okay, in fact they look
identical, but in reality because of the
different structure, here a continous
arrangement in row major order.
And here first the level of pointers that
get us to the start of the row.
And then a one-dimensional array.
this requires only one memory access.
we can do, compute the entire address in
one expression.
here we have to do it in two parts.
First, to get the pointer and then to add
on the offset and access again.
So two memory accesses.
So these arrays are a little bit more
expensive in performance because we have
to do those two memory accesses rather
than one.
Okay let's complete this video the same
way we did the previous one.
With some examples of accesses.
so let's go to univ two, three.
the address computation here, you'll
notice is first to get the the starting
address of the third element of the univ
array.
That would be the 56, that address is the
UCB zip code.
And then the offset within that, four
times the second index of three.
So that gives us an address of 68 which
in fact yields the fourth digit of that
zip code, or the number two.
And that is absolutely guaranteed to
always be the right answer, because
we're, we're doing the right thing here.
Let's look at a case where we use an
index that's a little off this one, five.
Okay, in this case the same address
computation is done.
this time we yield an address of 36.
which is a not part of the
one-dimensional array we were really
going after.
We were going after the second element of
the univ array which should have been to
the start of the CMU array, and then
because we have an offset of five
elements, we're going off the end of that
array and we go to address 36 out here.
Turns out by pure coincidence, that is
the first address of the UW zip code
array, but that is a pure coincidence.
It just happened to be that way the UW
array could've been somewhere else in
memory.
And then, wouldn't have had any idea what
value would've come up here.
In this case, we do get the nine, but
there's absolutely no guarantee that that
will be the case if we run our program
again, because we might end up in a
different that UW array might end up in a
different part of memory.
Okay let's do that 2 minus 1 example
next.
Again, the same address computation.
We go to address 52, but that is outside
of the element we were really trying to
address.
And again, it's only working out by
coincidence that we get the 5.
no guarantee at all that that would be
consistently that value.
Similarly for this one, we're even going
outside of the university array to the
next element where the next element would
be.
but who knows what's there and what
address we'll be reading.
That will take us to some random part of
memory.
We'll then go 4 bytes before that,
because of the minus 1.
And who knows what's there even.
so we have no idea what address it is, we
have no idea what value is there, of
course.
and no guarantee that anything will ever
be consistent in this case.
for the last one here 1, 12 the same
address computation yields a seven.
just because of pure coincidence that
there happened to be something there, but
again those arrays could've been shuffled
around, so no guarantee on that either.
Remember again the code doesn't do any
bounds checking C doesn't do that.
We'll see later that Java does and will
actually give us a warning that we're
accessing out of bounds that's a very
useful thing.
At an added cost of an extra check every
time.
C doesn't bother with that extra check,
just does the address computation.
Alright, so the add, the location of each
lower level array in memory is not
guaranteed in this case.
In the previous multidimensional case, we
had a guarantee because of row major
ordering in memory.
and this time we do not.
All we know is that there's a first set
of of pointers, and then we follow the
pointer to the one-dimensional array.
no guarantee of how those will end up in
memory.
Alright, to do a little bit of a
summarization of arrays in C then is
arrays themselves are a contiguous
allocation in memory.
there is no bounds checking.
we can usually treat the array like the
array name like a pointer to the first
element.
And then elements are offset from that
start of the array.
multidimensional arrays are continuous in
memory and in row major order.
multi-level arrays, these ones we've just
been discussing, are not contiguous, not
contiguous, and pointers are used between
levels, so we have many less guarantees
about how things are arranged.