[MUSIC].
We've seen multi-dimensional and
multi-level arrays.
now let's take a look at how we represent
some other structures besides just plain
integers or pointers, in memory.
In C, we have the concept of a struct.
a struct is a definition of a composite
data type that has sub-elements that are,
are in turn other data types themselves.
In this case, we have a small struct here
with three elements inside of it.
One is an integer.
One is an array of integers, in this case
a three element array.
And the other is a pointer to an integer.
So those are three parts to that struct.
In memory, is going to be laid out as a
continuous set of bytes for each of those
parts.
The first four bytes will of course be
the integer i.
the next 12 bytes will be the three
integers of the array a, contiuously
allocated.
And then finally, the last 4 bytes will
be a pointer to an integer in a 32 bit
architecture.
So, total for this struct is a 20 bite
chunk of memory, continuously allocated
and we can refer to the members of this
structure, by the names we've given them.
but the members can be of different
types, they don't have to be the same.
in this case these are either integers or
pointers intergers, but those are very
different data types.
OK.
So how do we access, a structure member?
well, given, an instance of a struct, we
can use the dot operator, just like in
Java.
So for example, if we declare one of
these str, rec structs that we just
defined, declared here, we can give it
the name r1.
Then we can refer to that first integer
in r1 by writing r1 dot i, and that
refers to just that first Integer, that
is part of that larger struct, that has a
couple of other things in it.
OK, if we have a pointer to a struct,
rather than the struct itself, in other
words, we've declared not the struct r1,
as we did in this case, but in pointer r
to a struct of type rec.
in other words, we, that would be
something like the address of the r1
struct we declared previously.
we're now using, we're going to be using
the star and dot operators, because we
first need to de-reference the struct
pointer.
get to the starting location of that of
that struct in memory, and then
offsetting that by the position of the
member within the struct.
OK?
So this happens so often in C that we
actually give it a shorthand.
we give it the shorthand r right arrow i.
and the arrow is drawn as a - followed by
a > sign.
and that's just a shorthand for doing
that de-reference first, that's what the
parentheses indicate, and then the dot.
OK?
So you'll often see this kind of
construct in C because we have pointers
to structs rather than the structs
themselves.
So, here you see a simple function that
is used to set the value of that first
element of this type of struct.
So it takes a pointer to that struct as
an argument, and a value to put in that
first member.
And it says, well, I have that pointer,
let's de-reference it, and offset to i,
that first member of the struct, and then
give it the value of val.
The way that ends up looking in assembly
code, is very straight forward actually.
Because we have the value val in eax, and
we're going to have the pointer to the
element in edx, and we're just going to
say move that value val to edx at that
address.
So the parentheses, again, are the
de-reference operator.
In this case, we don't have an offset,
because that was the, i is the very first
element of the struct.
So it's at that starting address.
If if we had to provide an offset, there
would have been an additional offset
here, in front of the parentheses.
OK.
So let's take a look at a slightly more
complex case.
generating a pointer to one of those
elements of that array inside of the
struct.
so in this case what we would like to do
is find the particular element that we're
interested in, by providing an index.
So we're going to provide a pointer to
the struct, and then an index into the
array.
And in this case, what we want to return
is a pointer to that integer element.
OK?
So to return the pointer what we will do
is first do that r Arrow a.
that gets us to the starting address of
the array within memory within that
struct.
And then, index that array with the
appropriate offset, and then the
ampersand says well I don't want the
value there, I want the address of that
value, and return that.
Mm-kay.
How we see that in assembly code, is just
two simple instructions.
the very first instruction computes the
offset into the struct.
So in this case, the offset is is four
times the index to get to the right
position within the array.
you'll then notice we'll take that value,
which we store in eax, here and add
another 4 offset to it, because that
array starts at four bytes into the
struct.
then, of course, eax has the offset
within the array.
And the edx is the starting address of
the struct, that first parameter.
We add all of those together, so we start
from r, add on the 4 to get to the a
portion of the struct, the array portion
of the struct.
And then we add on the, 4 times the index
to get to the right element inside the
array.
And since we're returning just the
address, we can stop there after we've
computed the address, we don't need to
actually do a memory reference.