[MUSIC].
The last part of this section is to
discuss alignment of our data structures
in memory.
let's see what we mean by that.
A structure contains multiple elements.
In this case, we have a struct that has a
single byte first element.
then two ints in an array as the second
element.
And finally, a double floating point
number as its third element.
So, what we would see and expect to see
in memory is a starting address for our
struct, the first byte being that
character C.
Then the next 8 bytes being the two ints
in the array I.
And then, the third part, the next 8
bytes, the double floating point number.
And we would expect this struct to occupy
17 bytes of of memory.
In reality we have to align this
structure.
And what we mean by alignment, is taking
a data type that's of K bytes, like an
int is of size 4 bytes and making sure
that it starts at an address divisible by
that by that number.
So what we want to do is make sure ints
start at addresses divisible by four.
And double started addresses divisible by
eight.
So you'll see that, in fact, our struct
will end up looking more like this in
memory.
where we have to pad an extra three
wasted bytes that we're not going to use
just in order to get the integer to line
up at an address divisible by four.
Similarly, we're going to have to pad an
extra four bytes here to get the to get
the the double float to be at an address,
start at an address divisible by eight.
Okay, and those are totally wasted space.
that's called internal fragmentation
uh,unused fragments of memory at the
inside of our struct that we don't see in
the declaration at all but that the
compiler puts in, in order to meet this
alignment requirement.
why what is the basic alignment
principle?
as I said, it that data type of size that
requires K bytes start at an address that
is in fact a multiple of K.
this is an absolute requirement on some
machines.
it's comple It's very much advised on the
IA32, although not requ not required all
the time there.
we're going to assume it is, and always
do things that way.
But what is the motivation for this
alignment?
well the reason for the alignment is
because we want to access physical memory
and be able to get an entire piece of
data in one access.
So for example, imagine that we had a 4
bytes int, and the first two bytes were
in one worded memory, and the next 2
bytes were in a separate word.
We wouldn't want to have to read two
words and then shuffle bytes around in
order to get our int.
so we'd like to make that be an efficient
single memory read that would read the 4
bytes directly.
We're going to see this alignment issue
come up also in virtual memory which
would be discussing a little bit later in
the course.
But for now the thing to remember is that
the program it doesn't worry about this.
The compiler takes care of this
alignment, and that's why we're provided
with the special function in C called
size of which returns the, the size,
given a data type as an argument returns
the size of that data type and bytes in
the number of bytes of memory.
And that's important because depending on
the architecture we're on, we'll have
slightly different alignment
requirements, and the size of the struct
might actually vary, because we have to
insert different amounts of unused bytes
in different places.
So, size of lets us get to the size of
the struct as the compiler decided it had
to be.
So in the case of IA32 a single byte, a c
a char eh, of course has no restriction
on where it's placed in the memory,
because a char is a single byte.
And we can always have an address to any
byte.
a two byte short int, on the other hand,
the a addresses lowered a bit must be a
zero, meaning that that address is
divisible by two.
For things that are 4 bytes in size like
ints and floats, and pointers, pointers
to any type of data any address well then
the lower 2 bits have to both be zero,
because those addresses have to be
divisible by four.
Similarly for doubles the address has to
be divisible by eight or have end in
three zeros.
Now it turns out that on some IA32
architectures doubles can only only have
required to align to 4 bytes
But for our part, we'll always kind of
consider that perfect alignment eight
byte things on eight byte multiples.
Okay, how do we satisfy alignment with
structures?
Here's our example from before, remember?
The, the one byte character, two ints in
an array, followed by a double float.
in our 64-bit architectures the value K,
the alignment requirement that we have to
meet, is eight.
Because that, it goes for the largest
element in the struct.
In this case, that double float is eight
bytes.
so everything m, must be aligned to those
eight byte boundaries.
So our struct must start at a multiple of
eight byte address.
we can put that initial character there
but then have to waste 3 bytes, so we can
start our int at a multiple of four.
then again those four wasted bytes, so we
can start our float at a multiple of
eight for its address.
So, in 64-bit architectures we end up
with this.
What would happen in a 32-bit
architecture?
Well in this case, the double is only 4
bytes, so K is equal to 4.
That is the largest data type that we
use.
And we can actually arrange things a
little bit differently, because you
notice that now we do not need to add the
extra 4 bytes there to move the float to
an 8-byte boundary.
We can leave it on a 4-byte boundary
without wasting those 4 bytes.
So you'll see, you see here why sizeof is
an important function.
In this case sizeof would return 24.
In this case sizeof would return 20 as
the size of the struct.
In neither case is it 17 however.
We always need these 3 bytes here in
order to make our integers line up.
Let's take a look at another example that
shuttles around the elements of the
struct.
again here is our original struct, and we
can do a different definition where we
put the largest element first, the double
first, then the ints and then the
smallest elements last the, the single
byte character in this case.
So, that instead of having this 24 byte
struct, we can actually arrange for
something that looks like this.
You notice it loo, that it appears to be
much more compact.
We don't have those wasted bytes, and in
fact, we don't have that internal
fragmentation in this case.
However, as we think about maybe having
an array of these structs and having them
follow each other, well they all have to
start at boundaries that are divisible by
eight.
so to do that we end up having to add
some padding at the end of the struct in
fact we will have to add 7 bytes at the
end of the struct.
So, we end up having the same size struct
anyway in this case, but in general we'll
do better if we put the largest elements
first.
Okay but you can see here in the array,
since we have to hit addresses that are
divisible by eight, we end up with an
extra 7 bytes of external fragmentation,
some extra bytes at the end of the
struct.
All right, let's take a look at how
elements of the array of structs are
accessed.
in this case we want to access an element
'I' of the array and then the J of or the
J element of that particular struct.
so first we're going to need an offset
that gets us to the right array element,
the right struct.
That'll be 12 times I the index to get us
to the right struct, and then we need an
offset within the struct.
and that offset is going to be an
additional eight, because in this case
that's where J will fall.
Remember, in this case we have a 2-byte
integer to start.
some 2 bytes of padding in order to make
sure that our float that is only four
bytes now starts at an address divisible
by four.
which puts J at plus eight from the
starting address.
And of course, we end up having to put an
extra 2 bytes to the next, between that
and the next struck so that the next
struct can start on a four byte boundary.
That's how we can an overall size of 12,
alright, and why we multiply the index by
12.
The code for the, the summary code we
might see for some functions for
accessing these arrays.
here we have a function get_j, which
given an index goes to that element of
the array and gets the J element of the,
the struct at that position.
the way this is computed is using just
two instructions.
You'll notice that the first one, this
LEAL, is simply used to get three times
the index.
So that we can then multiply it by four
to get 12 times the index.
remember we can't just do that multiply
by 12 directly.
Those multipliers have to be powers of
two.
so we first compose a partial result
that's three times the index, then
multiply that further by four and add the
offset from the start of the array A.
That's the starting point of the, the
entire array.
And then, an additional eight to get us
to the J element of the struct the offset
within the struct.